[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of the crust under the mountainous areas and in particular the Himalayas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-55 km",
            "b) 60-65 km",
            "c) 70-75 km",
            "d) 30-35 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is believed that the thickness of the crust under the Himalayas is 70 to 75 km and under the Hindukush it is said to be 60 km thick."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The discontinuity which marks the lower boundary of the crust is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crust-Mantle discontinuity",
            "b) Oceanic discontinuity",
            "c) SIAL layer",
            "d) Mohorovicic discontinuity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mohorovicic discontinuity marks the lower boundary of the crust which is the first layer of the Earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "The granite layer in the crust is also referred to as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIAL",
            "b) SIMA",
            "c) SLAM",
            "d) SILA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SIAL stands for Silicon and Aluminium and as per the name it is made up of the two elements and hence the name."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The density of the oceanic layer in the crust is said to be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.00 g/cc",
            "b) 2.50 g/cc",
            "c) 1.90 g/cc",
            "d) 2.00 g/cc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The oceanic crust is estimated to have a volume of 2.54*109 cc with an average density of 3.00 g/cc."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "The depth at which the Mohorovicic discontinuity occurs is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90-100 km",
            "b) 50-60 km",
            "c) 70-80 km",
            "d) 30-40 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mohorovicic discontinuity from seismic evidence is determined that it is approximately at a depth of 30-40 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the speed attained by the P-waves in the C-layer under the Continental crust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 to 7.6 km/sec",
            "b) 3 to 4 km/sec",
            "c) 5 to 6.3 km/sec",
            "d) 1.8 to 2.5 km/sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The C-layer is the lowermost layer of the continental crust and here the P-waves attain velocity as high as 6 to 7.6 km/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "The layer under the continental crust with the density of 2.4 to 2.6 g/cc is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-layer",
            "b) B-layer",
            "c) C-layer",
            "d) D-layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Middle layer or B-layer of the continental crust is relatively dense compared to A-layer and the density is said to be 2.4 to 2.6 g/cc."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The expansion of SIMA is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon and Manganese",
            "b) Silicon and Magnesium",
            "c) Strontium and Manganese",
            "d) Strontium and Magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Silicon and Magnesium. The C-layer under the continental crust is rich in Silicon and Magnesium and hence the layer is also sometimes called SIMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The least dense layer among the layers under  the continental crust is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-layer",
            "b) B-layer",
            "c) C-layer",
            "d) D-layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The oceanic crust is the extension of C-layer of the continental crust that makes the top layer of the oceans in most cases, A and B layers being practically absent from there."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The area not considered under the crust is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mountainous area",
            "b) Continental area",
            "c) Oceanic area",
            "d) Glacial area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The A or the upper layer is between 2 to 10 km thick and is of low density, 2.00 g/cc."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The depth up to which the mantle is said to exist is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000 km",
            "b) 1500 km",
            "c) 2900 km",
            "d) 1800 km"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The second layer, Mantle, lies beneath the crust and this zone starting from the lower boundary of the crust continues up to a depth of 2,900 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "The thickness of the 2 layers of the upper mantle is approximately said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 and 600 km",
            "b) 300 and 500 km",
            "c) 450 and 800 km",
            "d) 300 and 400 km"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation:  The upper mantle is further divided into two layers of 400 and 600 km thickness respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Asthenosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is present in the upper mantle",
            "b) It is in solid state",
            "c) It is the source of volcanic activity",
            "d) It is in plastic rather than solid state"
        ],
        "Answer": "   Answer: b\nExplanation:  It is said that the exact nature of the mantle is as yet incompletely understood. "
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to tell about the Core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graham Bell",
            "b) Albert Einstein",
            "c) Isaac Newton",
            "d) R.D. Oldham"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: It is in solid state is not true and the remaining options are true and they are characteristics of the asthenosphere. In Greek, “asthenes” means without strength and hence the name. "
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The depth at which the core layer starts and ends respectively is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2900 and 6371 km",
            "b) 2000 and 5371 km",
            "c) 2500 and 4771 km",
            "d) 2000 and 5000 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The existence of the core was suggested by R.D. Oldham in 1906 and subsequently confirmed by other seismologists.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about the inner core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is believed to be a semi solid body",
            "b) It is believed to be a solid body",
            "c) It is believed to be a liquid body",
            "d) It is believed to be a gaseous body."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The mantle extends up to the depth of 2900 km and from that depth it is the core that is said to be present and the radius of the Earth is 6371 km and hence the core is said to extend till 6371 km. "
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "The density of the Earth in the core immediately after the mantle is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 g/cc",
            "b) 7.6 g/cc",
            "c) 9.9 g/cc",
            "d) 8.7 g/cc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The inner core with a thickness of around 1790 km is believed to be a solid body. "
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The layer which does not transmit the S-waves is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outer core",
            "b) Crust",
            "c) Mantle",
            "d) Inner core"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  At the base of the mantle, density is inferred as 5.7 g/cc that jumps to 9.9 g/cc at the top of the core. "
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "The density of the Earth at its centre is said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.9 g/cc",
            "b) 8.8 g/cc",
            "c) 13 g/cc",
            "d) 12.7 g/cc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The outer core behaves more like a liquid because the S-waves from the earthquake shocks reaching this zone are not transmitted through this zone at all.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "The layer which is said to support the slow moving tectonic plates is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asthenosphere",
            "b) Lithosphere",
            "c) Mohorovic sphere",
            "d) Core layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  As regards the chemical composition of the inner core, the hypothesis that it is made up chiefly of iron and nickel elements has found support from many accounts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of the inner core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 790 km",
            "b) 1790 km",
            "c) 2790 km",
            "d) 3790 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of density reaches 12.7 g/cc at the boundary of the inner core and becomes 13 g/cc at the centre of the Earth.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "The layer which is believed to be the source of volcanic activity is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inner core",
            "b) Outer core",
            "c) Asthenosphere",
            "d) Mohorovicic layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Asthenosphere is believed to be located entirely in the upper mantle and supports the slowly moving tectonic plates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Which of the following about weathering is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a natural process",
            "b) Mechanical disintegration is involved",
            "c) Chemical decomposition is involved",
            "d) It is a rapid process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Weathering is defined as, a natural process of in-situ mechanical disintegration and or chemical decomposition of the rocks of the crust of the Earth by certain physical and chemical agencies of the atmosphere. It is a very slow process."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "The process that is not considered under mechanical weathering is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbonation",
            "b) Temperature variation",
            "c) Unloading",
            "d) Insolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carbonation is a chemical weathering process whereas the rest viz., temperature variation, unloading, insolation are processes of mechanical weathering. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "What is the change in volume when water freezes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10% decrease",
            "b) 20% increase",
            "c) 20% decrease",
            "d) 10% increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is said that water on freezing undergoes an increase in its volume by about ten per cent. This is expansion is accompanied by the exertion of pressure.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The form of rock not found by freezing-thawing cycle is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angular",
            "b) Sub angular",
            "c) Spherical",
            "d) Irregular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frost formed fragments are angular, sub angular, irregular in outline and remain spread over the parent rock having flat surface or flat slopes. Spherical form or outline of rock doesn’t come into picture here."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "The processes by which Scree deposits are formed are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical attack",
            "b) Exposure to sunlight",
            "c) Water movement",
            "d) Heaving and rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the original surface forms a significant slope, as is commonly the case in the hilly and mountainous regions, the frost fragments get heaved up from the crevices and cavities and then roll down the slope under the influence of gravity. Finally, the fragments accumulate at the base as heaps commonly called as Scree deposits. "
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What are the slopes covered by Scree called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scree slope",
            "b) Frost slope",
            "c) Talus slope",
            "d) Trist slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slopes covered by frost formed scree are often referred to as Talus slopes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Where can one find the process of exudation occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plains",
            "b) Seashore",
            "c) Hills",
            "d) Waterfalls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Exudation is a process similar to frost action but in this case disintegration takes place due to the formation of sodium chloride etc., within the cavities of rocks thereby causing disintegration. This process is seen in good measure in porous rocks near seashore. "
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The stress developed in the top layers of the rocks which disintegrate due to repeated variations in temperatures is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile stress",
            "b) Compressive stress",
            "c) Shear stress",
            "d) Bending stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Repeated variations in temperature experienced by a body of rock gradually break it into smaller pieces, especially in the top layers, by development of tensile stresses developing from alternate expansion and contraction.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following facts about Exfoliation is false?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the phenomenon of peeling off of curved shells from rocks",
            "b) The change is accompanied by chemical weathering",
            "c) Internal structure of the rock is affected",
            "d) It occurs in thick or layered rocks."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The internal structure of the rock is not affected due to the process of exfoliation. The phenomenon of peeling off occurs only in the layered or thick rocks and is accompanied by chemical weathering, mostly near the margins and develop curved surfaces. So basically surface is affected and not the internal structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "The large-scale development of fracturing in confined rock masses occurs under which process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frost action",
            "b) Unloading",
            "c) Unfolding",
            "d) Insolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of mechanical weathering where large-scale development of fracturing in confined rock masses is attributed to removal of the overlying rock cover due to prolonged erosional work of other agencies is called unloading. "
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "The formation of sheets and subsequently joints occurs in which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frost action",
            "b) Insolation",
            "c) Flow of water",
            "d) Unloading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rock masses under the effect of unloading remain confined from sides but due to relief of pressure from above, they expand upwards; consequently joints develop in them parallel to the uncovered surface dividing them into sheets.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "In Kara Qum desert, the rocks are exposed to what temperatures in summer and winter respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70-80° C and -10° C",
            "b) 20-30° C and -1° C",
            "c) 40-50° C and  0° C",
            "d) 25-35° C and  -3° C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The above statement is true because, for scree deposits to be formed, the rock fragments have to heave up and also roll down the slope under the influence of gravity.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The main processes which does not come under chemical weathering are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solution",
            "b) Hydration and hydrolysis",
            "c) Insolation",
            "d) Carbonation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The processes, solution, hydration and hydrolysis, carbonation are all chemical processes and involve chemical reaction, whereas, insolation is a process of mechanical weathering. "
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "The rock-mineral insoluble in water is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock salt",
            "b) Gypsum",
            "c) Calcite",
            "d) Pyrite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pyrite is insoluble in water, whereas, rock salt, gypsum and calcite are examples of minerals that are soluble in water to some extent.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Minerals like Orthoclase and Felspar undergo which method of chemical decomposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydration",
            "b) Hydrolysis",
            "c) Oxidation",
            "d) Reduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pure water is not a good solvent of minerals in most cases, but when the water is carbonated, its solvent action for many common minerals is enhanced. Thus, limestone is not easily soluble in pure water but carbonated water dissolves the rock effectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following is reduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of hydrogen",
            "b) Removal of electron",
            "c) Removal of oxygen",
            "d) Addition of oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ions may be exchanged whereby some ions from water may enter into the crystal lattice of the mineral. This process of exchange of ions is called hydrolysis. It is a very common process of weathering of silicate minerals and is best explained with reference to weathering of mineral Orthoclase, Felspar."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which of the following about Spheroidal weathering is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a complex type of weathering",
            "b) Both mechanical and chemical weathering are believed to happen",
            "c) Formation of joints is involved",
            "d) Formation of joints is not involved"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oxidation means of either removal of electron or hydrogen or addition of oxygen but, reduction may involve removal of oxygen or addition of hydrogen or electron. "
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Factor not affecting weathering is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour of the rock",
            "b) Nature of the rock",
            "c) Climate",
            "d) Physical environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reaction of orthoclase with carbonic acid yields kaolinite {Al2Si2O5(OH)4 } and Pot. Carbonate and silica.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "It is said that Sandstone is more resistant to weathering compared to Granite. What is the basic reason behind this phenomenon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The external outline form of sandstone",
            "b) Sandstone is harder than granite",
            "c) Granite is mainly made of quartz",
            "d) Sandstone is mainly made of quartz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spheroidal weathering is a complex type of weathering observed in jointed rocks and characterized with the breaking of original rock mass into spheroidal blocks. Both mechanical and chemical weathering are believed to actively cooperate in causing spheroidal weathering. The original solid rock mass is split into small block masses by development of parallel joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Identify the pair mismatched.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cold and humid – Both mechanical and chemical weathering",
            "b) Dry and cold – Neither of them",
            "c) Hot and humid – Mechanical weathering is predominant",
            "d) Hot and dry – Mechanical weathering is predominant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weathering is affected by the factors like nature of the rock, climate, physical environment but is not affected by colour of the rock. It has no influence over its weathering.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following rock forming minerals is more resistant to weathering compared to Hornblende?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Augite",
            "b) Biotite",
            "c) Olivine",
            "d) Calcite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among granite and sandstones exposed to atmosphere simultaneously in the same or adjoining areas having hot and humid climate, the sandstone will resist weathering to a great extent because they are made up mainly of quartz(SiO2) which is highly weathering resistant mineral. "
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about Eluvium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is that category of end product of weathering that has been moved to some distance after its formation",
            "b) It is associated with weathering of slopes",
            "c) It is the end product of weathering that happens to lie over and above the parent rock",
            "d) Regolith is not the other name for Eluvium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the hot and humid conditions chemical weathering is predominant and not mechanical, since, there is presence of moisture. "
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "The zone consisting of mixed composition is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zone A",
            "b) Zone B",
            "c) Zone C",
            "d) Zone D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistance to weathering increases in the following order for dark coloured minerals- Olivine, Augite, Hornblende, Biotite. Hence only Biotite is most resistant. Calcite as it is very reactive among the rock forming minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Among the following the term which is not effect of chemical weathering is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scree formation",
            "b) Disfiguring",
            "c) Pitting",
            "d) Honeycombing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The basic definition of Eluvium is “It is the end product of weathering that happens to lie over and above the parent rock”. Regolith is another term for eluvium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The winds are formed basically due to which reason?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform heating",
            "b) Non-uniform heating",
            "c) Precipitation",
            "d) Tectonic activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Winds are born mainly due to non-uniform heating of the surface of the earth at different places causing differences in atmospheric pressure. The pressure difference so created makes the atmospheric gases (the air) to move from areas of high pressure to areas of low pressure in the form of winds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "The removal of particles of dust and sand by strong winds is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasion",
            "b) Depletion",
            "c) Deflation",
            "d) Aeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of removal of dust and sand by strong winds is called deflation. In Latin, ‘deflare’ means ‘to blow away’. It is the main process of wind erosion in desert regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The water in an oasis is obtained from which source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rain",
            "b) Erosion from other place",
            "c) Water table",
            "d) Water released from adsorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sometimes due to deflation, huge depressions are created in the deserts to such an extent that the depression becomes so deep that it intersects with the groundwater table. And it gets partially filled up with water and this is called an oasis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "The type of erosion which involves rubbing, grinding is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deflation",
            "b) Attrition",
            "c) Deflection",
            "d) Wind abrasion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The type of erosion involving rubbing, grinding, abrading and polishing the rock surfaces by any natural agent (wind, water or ice) with the help of its lead while passing over the rocks is termed as abrasion.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which among the following is called “Mushroom rocks”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestal rocks",
            "b) Yardangs",
            "c) Ventifacts",
            "d) Desert pavements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pedestal rocks are also often called mushroom rocks because of their likeness to mushrooms popping up closely in a level land. "
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "The rock which is well polished by wind abrasion is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yardangs",
            "b) Pedestal rock",
            "c) Ventifacts",
            "d) Desert pavements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ventifacts are small sized rock fragments showing one, two or three or even more typically wind-polished surfaces called faces. The polishing of different sides of originally rough fragments is caused by prolonged wind abrasion.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "The factor which does not affect the attrition by wind is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nature of the region",
            "b) Velocity of wind",
            "c) Duration",
            "d) Sunlight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Factors that affect attrition by wind are nature of the region, velocity of wind and duration. It is not affected by sunlight. "
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following about saltation is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In this process the heavier and coarse sediments are lifted up",
            "b) They are lifted up periodically and for short distances",
            "c) In this process the light-density particles are carried away",
            "d) It is the process of sediment transport by series of jump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The heavier and coarse sediments such as sand grains, pebbles and gravels etc. are lifted up periodically during high velocity times and only for short distances and that too for smaller heights above the ground. The uplifting of lighter particles is called suspension."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Which among the following has S-shaped outline?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crescentic dune",
            "b) Barchans",
            "c) Transverse dunes",
            "d) Sigmoidal dunes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transporting power of wind depends on its velocity as also on the size, shape and density of the particles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The type of dune which is short lived is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barchans",
            "b) Sigmoidal",
            "c) Transverse dunes",
            "d) Fixed dune"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A typical sigmoidal dune is characterized with the absence of horns or cusps and a curved outline. In its simplest form, a sigmoidal dune is a steep sided ridge that extends in a sinuous or S-shaped outline. "
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "The particle size in a Loess is around _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-3 mm in diameter",
            "b) 1-2 mm in diameter",
            "c) 0.01-0.05 mm in diameter",
            "d) 0.1-1 mm in diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the dunes are migratory in nature and among all, Barchans are especially known to move ahead at the rate of 25 to 250 meters a month. Hence barchans are said to be short-lived relative to other dunes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What is the term used for wind blown deposits of silt and clay grade particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dunes",
            "b) Loess",
            "c) Hills",
            "d) Ventifacts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A typical Loess is unconsolidated, unstratified, and porous accumulation of particles of the size range 0.01-0.05 mm in diameter. This size fraction makes almost 40 percent of a particular loess deposit rest being made up of still finer clay grade material.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "The branch of geology which deals with the morphology, classification, mechanism and causes of development of these rock structures is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock geology",
            "b) Structural geology",
            "c) Basic geology",
            "d) Lithology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basic definition of structural geology is “the branch of geology which deals with the morphology, classification, mechanism and causes of development of these rock structures”. Hence the answer Structural Geology."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Stratification can be seen widely in which of the following rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rocks",
            "b) Metamorphic rocks",
            "c) Sedimentary rocks",
            "d) Fossil rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most sedimentary rocks are deposited under conditions which favour development of distinct layers piled up one above another, from bottom to top. These layers also called beds or strata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Most widespread rock on earth is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) All are in equal quantities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solid rocks are not exposed everywhere on the surface of the earth. These are mostly covered with a thick or thin layer of loose deposit called alluvium or in most common language as soil. Hence rock or the outcrop is not seen everywhere on earth.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which of the following about lamination is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is closely related to stratification",
            "b) It is literally paper thin",
            "c) It is a layered structure developed in extremely fine grained igneous rocks",
            "d) It is a layered structure developed in extremely fine grained sedimentary rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is said that sedimentary rocks are superficially the most widespread rocks, forming more than 75% of the exposed surface of the earth.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "The maximum angle of inclination of a layer of a rock with the horizontal is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dip",
            "b) Heave angle",
            "c) Strike",
            "d) Depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term lamination is closely related to stratification. It is a layered structure developed in extremely fine grained sedimentary rocks made up of clay and silt. The layers are paper thin literally speaking."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Angle of dip is measured using which instrument?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compass",
            "b) Theodolite",
            "c) Tacheometer",
            "d) Clinometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The definition of dip is “The maximum angle of inclination of a layer of a rock with the horizontal”. It is expressed both in terms of degree of inclination and direction of inclination."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a type of dip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Widespread dip",
            "b) Primary dip",
            "c) Secondary dip",
            "d) Local and regional dip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The direction of dip is determined with a simple compass whereas the angle of dip is determined with an instrument called clinometer, which comes built in with the compass. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The term “intrusion” is basically associated with which type of rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) Not associated with any type of rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The types of dips are primary, secondary, local and regional. Widespread dip is not considered as a dip. "
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The dip which involves tectonic forces is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary dip",
            "b) Secondary dip",
            "c) Local and Regional dip",
            "d) No dip involves tectonic forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Igneous rocks are formed from cooling and crystallization of hot molten material called magma/lava depending on the place of occurrence. The magma gets intruded or injected into the pre-existing rocks of any type- called the host rocks and takes variously shaped forms on cooling. These forms are commonly termed as Intrusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "A coal seam is exposed on a horizontal ground. If it is 30° towards West. Its width of outcrop on a level ground is 360 m. What is its true thickness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 m",
            "b) 150 m",
            "c) 160 m",
            "d) 180 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Secondary dip is the inclination induced in the strata after its deposition due to the tectonic forces to which such strata have been subsequently subjected. Secondary dips may range in value up to vertical. "
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "At a dam site, a bed of sandstone is exposed on horizontal ground. If it is 25° towards East. Its width of outcrop on a level ground is 240 m, what is its vertical thickness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101.9 m",
            "b) 99.9 m",
            "c) 111.9 m",
            "d) 121.9 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The equation to calculate True thickness is given by\nTrue thickness = Width of outcrop * Sin 30°\nBy substitution and calculation, we get 180 m.\nTrue thickness = 360 * sin (30°) = 180 m "
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "The study of outcrop dimensions doesn’t involve which of the following aspect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Width",
            "b) Thickness and depth",
            "c) Dip and strike",
            "d) Rock composition and type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vertical thickness = Width of outcrop * tan (angle of inclination)\nVertical thickness = 240 * tan (25°) = 111.91 m "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Foliation is a primary structure of which type of rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) Not associated with any rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The study of rock composition and type of rock is not done under the outcrop dimensions whereas the rest are thoroughly studied under the topic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "The dip of a layer measured in the direction that is at the right angle to strike is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) True dip",
            "b) Apparent dip",
            "c) Straight dip",
            "d) Normal dip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stratification and lamination are the most common primary structures of sedimentary rocks; crystalline structure is typical of igneous rocks and foliation is a typical primary structure of metamorphic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "What are the undulations or bends developed in rocks called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faults",
            "b) Joints",
            "c) Folds",
            "d) Uncomformity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Folds may be defined as undulations or bends or curvatures developed in the rocks of the crust as a result of stresses to which these rocks have been subjected from time to time in the past history of the Earth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Folds develop in which type of rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) Any type of rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The folds may develop in any type of rock and may be of any shape and flexures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which type of deformation is folding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brittle",
            "b) Ductile",
            "c) Tensile",
            "d) Malleable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In general, folding is a ductile type of deformation experienced by the rocks compared to the brittle deformation where the rocks actually get broken and displaced when stressed.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Folding is ________ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very slow",
            "b) Rapid",
            "c) Quick",
            "d) Moderate rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Folding is a very slow geological process and indicates an effort of the rocks in a particular environment to adjust themselves to the changing force fields operating on, within or around them.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a part of fold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limbs",
            "b) Hinge",
            "c) Axis of fold",
            "d) Height of fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parts of a fold include, limbs, hinge, axis of a fold, plunge of a fold and crest & trough. Height of fold is not referred as its part.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "The minimum number of limbs for a fold are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An individual fold will have a minimum of two limbs but when the folds occur in groups, as this is common, a middle limb will be common to two adjacent folds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "The point where the curvature is maximum is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hinge",
            "b) Axial surface",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) Fold point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a folded layer, a point can be found where curvature is maximum and one limb ends and the other limb starts from that point. This is the hinge point.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "When the plunge said to be zero, then the axis of the fold is said to be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical",
            "b) Horizontal",
            "c) Inclined at 60° to the horizontal",
            "d) Inclined at 60° to its normal."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Axis is a line and plunge is the angle which the line makes with a horizontal. A fold having a horizontal axis will obviously have a zero plunge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "What is the axis of a fold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line drawn normal to the hinge line",
            "b) Line drawn at 60° to hinge line",
            "c) Line drawn parallel to hinge line",
            "d) Line which doesn’t pass through hinge line."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The line running through the highest points in an uparched fold defines the crest and similarly the line running through the lowest point in a downarched fold makes its trough. The crest and trough may or may not coincide with the axis of the fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "How is the plunge of a fold measured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direction",
            "b) Degree",
            "c) Depth",
            "d) Both direction and degree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Axis of fold is defined as a line drawn parallel to the hinge line of a fold. In other words, line representing the intersection of the axial plane of a fold with any bed of the fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following about axial plane is not true.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axial plane is imaginary",
            "b) Axial plane may be vertical, inclined or horizontal",
            "c) Axial plane may be planar or non-planar",
            "d) Axial plane need not pass through all points of maximum curvature in a folded sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The plunge is measured like a dip of a bedding plane, both in terms of the direction of plunge and degree of plunge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "The type of fold in which the limbs dip away from each other at the crest is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anticline",
            "b) Syncline",
            "c) Countercline",
            "d) Doesn’t exist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Anticlines are defined as those folds in which the limbs dip away from each other at the crest in the simplest forms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "The fold which is convex downwards is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anticline",
            "b) Syncline",
            "c) U-cline",
            "d) Crestcline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Synclines are the reverse of anticlines in all details and the strata are downarched, that is, these become convex downwards. "
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Anticline?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The strata are uparched",
            "b) Geologically older rocks occupy a position in the interior of the fold",
            "c) The limbs dip away from each other at the crest",
            "d) They are convex downwards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anticlines are said to convex upwards and not downwards. Synclines are convex downwards.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is the other name for upright fold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Symmetrical fold",
            "b) Asymmetrical fold",
            "c) Overturned fold",
            "d) Isoclinal fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Symmetrical folds are also called normal folds or upright folds. In such a fold, the axial plane is essentially vertical.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Fold in which the limbs lie exactly one over another?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isoclinal",
            "b) Symmetrical",
            "c) Recumbent",
            "d) Asymmetrical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In recumbent folds, one limb comes to lie exactly under the other limb so that a drill hole dug at the surface in the upper limb passes through the lower limb also.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also an overturned fold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isoclinal fold",
            "b) Symmetrical fold",
            "c) Asymmetrical fold",
            "d) Recumbent fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Recumbent folds are described as extreme types of overturned folds in which the axial plane acquires an almost horizontal attitude.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Fold with flattened top is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square fold",
            "b) Plateau fold",
            "c) Box fold",
            "d) Conjugate fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Box fold may be described as a special type of fold with exceptionally flattened top and steep inclined limbs almost forming three sides of a rectangle. "
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The type of fold in which fold angle is between 10° to 90°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tight fold",
            "b) Loose fold",
            "c) Gentle fold",
            "d) Acute fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When it comes to fold angle as the basis of classification, the fold with a fold angle between 10° and 90° is called tight fold.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of fold based on behaviour with depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentric fold",
            "b) Similar fold",
            "c) Supratenuous fold",
            "d) Asymmetrical fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The first three options are the types based on behaviour with depth where asymmetric fold is based on position of axial plane.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Where can folds be observed in the southern part of India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vindhyan region only",
            "b) Satpura region only",
            "c) Vindhyan and Satpura ranges",
            "d) Cannot be observed in southern India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In class 1 folds, isogans converge inwards whereas in class 3, these converge upwards."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Where is the Liddar Valley Anticline situated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kashmir Himalayas",
            "b) Uttarakhand Himalayas",
            "c) Sikkim Himalayas",
            "d) Himachal Pradesh Himalayas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the peninsular mountains, only the Vindhyan and the Satpuran ranges show folding in a prominent manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about recumbent fold.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has the arch, which is zone of curvature",
            "b) It has the shell, which is the inner zone, made up of mostly igneous rocks",
            "c) It has the shell, which is the outer zone, made up of mostly sedimentary rocks",
            "d) It has the core, which is the innermost zone, maybe made up of igneous rocks and metamorphic rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shell part of a recumbent, which is the outer zone, is mostly made up of sedimentary rocks. Hence the second statement is wrong regarding it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "The type of fold which is actually a group of folds is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Symmetrical folds",
            "b) Asymmetrical folds",
            "c) Isoclinal folds",
            "d) Recumbent folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Isoclinal folds are group of folds in which all the axial planes are essentially parallel, meaning that all the component limbs are at equal amounts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "In which class of folds, the Isogans converge inwards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class 1",
            "b) Class 2",
            "c) Class 3",
            "d) Class 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ramsay divides all types of folds into three main classes on the basis of relative curvature of the outer and the inner arcs of a fold. They are Class 1, Class 2 and Class 3 folds."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which is the type of fold with a similar degree of folding for indefinite depths?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentric fold",
            "b) Similar fold",
            "c) Conjugate fold",
            "d) Uniform fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Determination of dips may be made and then lines of equal dips are drawn. These are called Isogans. In Class 1 folds, the Isogans converge inwards. "
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Gentle folds have fold angle between ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10° to 90°",
            "b) 90° to 170°",
            "c) 170° to 180°",
            "d) They don’t belong to this type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In class 2 folds, the isogans would run parallel to each other and hence the fold shown in the figure belongs class 2. "
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which is the class of fold with the degree of curvature greater on the outer arc compared to the inner arc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class 1",
            "b) Class 2",
            "c) Class 3",
            "d) Class 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Similar folds are the folds in which the degree of folding is observed to be similar for indefinite depths. "
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "The fold which is associated with the formation of mountains is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geanticline",
            "b) Geosyncline",
            "c) Homocline",
            "d) Basin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Supratenuous folds show differences in thickness at the crestal and the trough regions, not induced by folding process but essentially due to erosional and depositional processes operating in the folded regions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "The anticlines signifying larger bending are called  ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geranticlines",
            "b) Geosynclines",
            "c) Geanticlines",
            "d) Geoantinclines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the classification of folds on the basis of fold angle, a fold is said to be gentle fold if the fold angle is between 170° to 180°. "
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "The folds caused due to the drag effect are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monocline",
            "b) Homocline",
            "c) Basins",
            "d) Drag folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Class 3 folds are just the reverse of class 1 folds; in these folds, the degree of curvature as measured on the outer arc is greater than that of the inner arc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "How many types of folds are there with plunge as a basis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only two main types are recognized as the types of folds on the basis plunge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is a plunging fold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fold with fold axis horizontal",
            "b) Fold with fold axis only vertical",
            "c) Fold with fold axis not horizontal",
            "d) This is not a type of fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any fold in which fold axis is not horizontal, that is, it makes an angle with the horizontal, may be described as a plunging fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "A fold in which the folding continues in the direction of the axis of the fold is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plunging fold",
            "b) Non-plunging fold",
            "c) Similar fold",
            "d) Doesn’t exist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any fold in which the axis of the fold is essentially horizontal, that is, the plunging continues indefinitely in the direction of the axis of the fold is specifically described as non-plunging fold."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "A fold which is not based on the profile of the folded strata is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cheveron fold",
            "b) Conjugate fold",
            "c) Cuspate fold",
            "d) Plunging fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cheveron fold, conjugate fold, cuspate fold are the types of fold based on the profile of the fold surface whereas, plunging fold is based on plunge of the fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Folds with two hinges and three planar limbs are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugate folds",
            "b) Cheveron folds",
            "c) Cuspate folds",
            "d) Cylindrical folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conjugate folds are composite folds characterised with two hinges and three planar limbs in which the central limb is exceptionally flattened. "
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Folds characterized by well-defined, sharp hinge points are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugate folds",
            "b) Cheveron folds",
            "c) Cuspate folds",
            "d) Cylindrical folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cheveron folds are the folds characterised with well-defined, sharp hinge points and straight planar limbs."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Pick the non-planar fold from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Box fold",
            "b) Cheveron fold",
            "c) Conjugate fold",
            "d) Cuspate fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The limbs of the cuspate fields are not planar, they are quite clearly curved becoming concave upwards in the case of anticlines and concave downwards in the case of synclines.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about cylindrical folds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They resemble sections of pipes",
            "b) They have very well defined axes of folds",
            "c) These well defined axes are repeated parallel to each other",
            "d) These well defined axes are not repeated parallel to each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Folds in which repetition of axes parallel to themselves is not possible, are classified as non-cylindrical. The first three statements are true about the cylindrical folds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Folds which mostly occur in groups are based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Profile of the fold surface",
            "b) Mode of occurrence",
            "c) Plunge",
            "d) Relative curvature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we can observe, there are two hinge points and three planar limbs. This is seen in conjugate fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of the following about drag fold is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The axes of the drag folds are parallel to those of the major folds",
            "b) The drag folds plunge in the same manner as the major folds",
            "c) The layers on the upper side of the drag folds slide away from the synclinal axis",
            "d) The axes of the drag folds are not parallel to those of the major folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cuspate folds are quite clearly curved becoming concave upwards in the case of anticlines and concave downwards in the case of synclines. The hinge zones are, therefore, not very sharp. "
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "What is Orogeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat land building activity",
            "b) River forming activity",
            "c) Rock breaking activity",
            "d) Mountain building activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geosynclines serve as depositional fields to which sediments are derived by the erosion of adjoining geanticlines and the sediments get accumulated and compacted. This material is then compressed and uplifted in the second stage of orogeny, which is the mountain building activity, to gradually take the shape of mountain systems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "The fold associated with magmatic activity is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anticlinorium",
            "b) Synclinorium",
            "c) Diapiric fold",
            "d) Box fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diapiric folds are anticlines or domes in which uparching of strata is attributed to the rising of viscous magma from below. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "A group of strata centrally centrally uplifted is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dome",
            "b) Basin",
            "c) Valley",
            "d) Cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Domes are a group of strata centrally uplifted in such a way that seen from the top, these dip away in all directions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Pick the incorrect statement about basins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basins are the reverse of the domes",
            "b) They are a group of strata that are centrally depressed",
            "c) Group of strata that are centrally uplifted",
            "d) Involved layers dip towards a common central point from all sides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Basins are a group of strata that are centrally depressed in such a way that the involved layers dip towards a common central point from all the sides. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which among the following is considered as compound anticline?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dome",
            "b) Valley",
            "c) Basin",
            "d) Depression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In any two cross sections drawn mutually at right angles to each other in a dome, a fold of anticlinal character will be seen to emerge. As such, a dome may be considered as a compound anticline."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which is the fold depicting localized warping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homocline",
            "b) Drag fold",
            "c) Dome",
            "d) Monocline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A monocline is described as essentially a localized warping in which case otherwise horizontal strata show a single bend for a limited length and attain the horizontal attitude once again. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The fold which actually is just strata dipping in some direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dome",
            "b) Homocline",
            "c) Monocline",
            "d) Basin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A homocline actually describes a sequence of strata dipping in the same general direction at a uniform angle, especially when such structure is established to be a limb of major fold. "
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "The folds which develop within body of weaker rocks are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscous folds",
            "b) Internal folds",
            "c) Drag folds",
            "d) Monocline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An anticline or syncline of big magnitude, for instance, will each show two homoclines, one on either side of the hinge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "What would the two cross sections drawn at mutually right angle directions in a basin show?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anticlinal characters",
            "b) Synclinal characters",
            "c) Both characters",
            "d) Drag fold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drag folds may be defined as minor folds developed within the body of incompetent or weaker rocks surrounded on both sides by layers of competent or stronger rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Pick the option which is not the cause of folding.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folding due to tangential tension",
            "b) Folding due to tangential compression",
            "c) Folding due to intrusions",
            "d) Folding due to differential compression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The various causes of folding that are studied are, folding due to- tangential compression, intrusions and differential compression. Hence first option is not correct."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Bending or warping is studied under ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tectonic folding",
            "b) Non-tectonic folding",
            "c) Volcanic folding",
            "d) Intrusional folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Folding may be either due to tectonic causes or due to non-tectonic causes. The tectonic folding of the rocks is bending or warping of rocks due very conspicuously to superficial processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "The cause of folding which does not occur due to the tangential stresses is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexural folding",
            "b) Flexural creeping",
            "c) Flowage folding",
            "d) Shear folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Under the influence of tangential stresses, folding may develop in either of the three ways: flexural folding, flowage folding and shear folding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "How does the thickness of the layer affect flexural folding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thinner the layers, greater is the slip",
            "b) Thicker the layers, lesser is the slip",
            "c) Thicker the layers, greater is the slip",
            "d) Has no effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thickness of the layers and nature of the contact are important factors on which the amount of slip depends. Thicker the layer, greater is the slip. "
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which are the rocks more prone to flexural slip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) Basalt",
            "c) Soft clay",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Types of the rocks involved: siltstones, sandstones and limestones are more prone to flexure slip folding compared to soft clays and shales."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "In which cause of folding, the thickness of fold does not remain uniform?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexural folding",
            "b) Shear folding",
            "c) Flowage folding",
            "d) Flexural tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the compression due to flowage folding, the material of the involved layers behaves almost as a viscous or plastic mass and gets buckled up and deformed at varying rates suffering unequal distortion. In such cases the thickness of the resulting fold does not remain uniform. "
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Flowage folding occurs in which type of rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Competent rocks",
            "b) Incompetent rocks",
            "c) Any rock",
            "d) Sedimentary rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flowage folding is the principal process of folding in incompetent or weaker, plastic type of rocks such as clays, shales, gypsum and rock salt etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "How does the distance from hinge point affect displacement due to folding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater the distance, larger is the displacement",
            "b) Lesser the distance, larger is the displacement",
            "c) Doesn’t depend on the distance from hinge point",
            "d) Greater the distance, smaller is the displacement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distance from hinge point is also an important factor on which displacement of folding depends. Greater the distance from the hinge points, larger is the displacement."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "The process of folding which causes fracture in rocks initially is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexural folding",
            "b) Flowage folding",
            "c) Shear folding",
            "d) Intrusion folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flexural folding is also distinguished as flexural-slip-folding in which the slip or movement of the strata involved takes place parallel to the bedding planes of the layers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement. The converging plates maybe ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two continental plates",
            "b) A continental plate and an oceanic plate",
            "c) A continental plate and an island plate",
            "d) Two oceanic plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In many cases, folding is attributed to shearing stresses rather than simple compression. It is assumed that in such a process, numerous closely spaced fractures develop in the rock at the first stage of the process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which rock is lifted up during the folding due to intrusions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overlying metamorphic rocks",
            "b) Overlying igneous rocks",
            "c) Overlying sedimentary rocks",
            "d) Overlying petroleum rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In magmatic intrusions, highly viscous magma may be forced up gradually and with considerable force so that sedimentary host rocks overlying are lifted up to provide the space for the rising magma."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The process of folding which is considered to be non-tectonic is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differential compression",
            "b) Tangential compression",
            "c) Intrusions",
            "d) Tangential tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Folding due to differential compression is totally dependent on the load from above and are attributed to superficial causes. These are, therefore, non-tectonic folds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "What is the indirect cause for warping or folding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogenous strata",
            "b) Non-homogenous strata",
            "c) Inclined strata",
            "d) Curved strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the strata in question is not homogenous, the bending may not be uniform in character and results in warping or folding of different types."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "What is the reason for rock bursts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change in attitude of rocks",
            "b) Shattering of rocks",
            "c) Intense precipitation",
            "d) Strained nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the stresses that have acted on the rocks during their folding are generally absorbed by these rocks by undergoing strain. Enough stored energy is released as soon as the excavations are made and this leads to rock bursts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "What is affected when the layers of undesirable nature are encountered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project cost",
            "b) Time schedule",
            "c) Safety of the project",
            "d) All the three are affected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Same layers may be repeated along an alignment or one or more encountered layers are of undesirable nature, the project cost may be affected as also the time schedule and safety of the project."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Shattering makes the rocks ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-porous",
            "b) Impervious",
            "c) Stronger",
            "d) Pervious"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Folding is the response of the rocks to the stresses induced during the process. These stresses are often strong enough to break or shatter the rocks, especially in the axial zones, which are the places of maximum concentration of these forces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "The process of folding which mainly causes uparching is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folding due to differential compression",
            "b) Folding due to tangential shearing",
            "c) Folding due to intrusions",
            "d) Folding due to differential tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shattering effect is of utmost importance because shattered rocks become: weak in strength parameters of all types; porous and pervious in character. "
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "What is the cause of downward bending?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differential compression",
            "b) Differential shearing",
            "c) Intrusions",
            "d) Flowage folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Axial regions should be thoroughly studied and avoided if possible. If it is not possible to avoid them, these areas must be subjected to suitable processes of rock treatment for developing in them desired qualities of strength and imperviousness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Which rock might undergo flowage folding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Siltstone",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Gypsum",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Intrusion of magma or even rock salt bodies from beneath has been found to be the cause of uparching of the overlying strata.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "At what angle is the primary lateral compressive force said to act in tangential compression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60° to the trend of the folds",
            "b) 90° to the trend of the folds",
            "c) 30° to the trend of the folds",
            "d) 45° to the trend of the folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strata that are being compacted under load in a basin of sedimentation develop, with the passage of time, downward bending especially in the zones of maximum loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What are the fractures along which there has been relative movement of blocks called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folds",
            "b) Joints",
            "c) Faults",
            "d) Intrusions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The definition of faults is “Those fractures along which there has been relative movement of the blocks past each other”. The entire process of development of fractures and displacement of the blocks against each other is termed as faulting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "What is the key word in the definition of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fracture",
            "b) Movement",
            "c) Both fracture and movement",
            "d) Dip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The key words in the definition are fracture and movement. The exact significance of these key words must be clearly understood. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Faulting is a _________ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tectonic",
            "b) Non-tectonic",
            "c) Both tectonic and non-tectonic",
            "d) Precipitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There can be no fault if there is no fracture surface or zone and also evidence of some relative movement of the blocks against each other is a must for qualifying that fracture as a fault. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "In which direction does the displacement of blocks happen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal",
            "b) Vertical",
            "c) Inclined",
            "d) Any direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Faulting is a major tectonic process of great geological importance. The geological history of the Earth bears innumerable events recording in the script of folding, faulting and jointing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "What is the angle that can be made by fault plane with the horizontal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acute angle only",
            "b) Obtuse angle only",
            "c) Right angle",
            "d) Any angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The displacement of blocks created in the rock due to faulting may take place in any direction: parallel to the fault surface; in an inclined manner or even rotational. "
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "What is the planar surface of fracture along which relative displacement of bodies has taken place called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault plane",
            "b) Fold plane",
            "c) Stress plane",
            "d) Strain plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fault planes may be vertical, horizontal or inclined at any angle with the horizontal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "What is the angle of fault plane with the horizontal called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hade",
            "b) Strike",
            "c) Dip",
            "d) Inclination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fault plane is the planar surface of fracture along which relative displacement of the blocks takes place during the process of faulting. When it is not planar, the same surface is simply described as fault surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Parameter(s) considered for dip is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direction",
            "b) Angle",
            "c) Direction and angle",
            "d) Neither direction nor angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dip of the fault is its inclination with the horizontal as measured in a vertical plane at right angles to the strike of the fault. "
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "What is hade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inclination of fault with horizontal",
            "b) Inclination of fault with vertical",
            "c) Inclination of fault with any strata",
            "d) Bearing of the fault with ground"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dip is measured both in terms of the direction of dip as well as angle of dip just as in the bedding plane of strata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "What is the bearing of a line of intersection of fault plane and horizontal called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike",
            "b) Dip",
            "c) Hade",
            "d) Intersection line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The hade of the fault is the angle which the fault makes with the vertical. In other words, it is the complimentary to the dip angle. "
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "A fault has how many walls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In faults, the concept of walls is very important and must be understood very clearly. In a rock body, when a fracture takes place, it divided the rock into two parts or two blocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What is the block which suffer displacement in faulting called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Walls",
            "b) Parts",
            "c) Sections",
            "d) Blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It may be easy to locate fault planes or fault surfaces in small scale and in rather recent faults. In older and especially major faults spreading over miles of area, however, extensive field work including drilling or subsurface investigations using geophysical methods may be required to determine these structures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The block which lies on the under surface of fault plane or zone is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hanging wall",
            "b) Sub-wall",
            "c) Foot wall",
            "d) Lower wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The blocks which suffer displacement and stand on either sides of the fracture are called as walls. Generally there exist two types of walls, hanging wall and foot wall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Who coined the terms “hanging wall” and “foot wall”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scientists",
            "b) Geologists",
            "c) Engineers",
            "d) Miners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term foot wall is used for that faulted block which lies on the under surface of the fault plane or zone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "What is a small region with definite thickness and distinct composition having numerous closely placed parallel fractures called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear zone",
            "b) Fault zone",
            "c) Fracture zone",
            "d) Slikensides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Actually the terms “hanging wall” and “foot wall” have been coined by the miners: while traversing along a track excavated in fault plane, the wall under their feet would be foot wall whereas the other block would hang above their heads. "
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is the nature of displacement in shear zone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ductile",
            "b) Brittle",
            "c) Malleable",
            "d) Sonorous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fault zone is a small region with definite thickness and distinct composition having numerous closely placed parallel fractures within itself along which there have been clear displacements. "
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Slip is expressed in terms of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Millimetres",
            "b) Metres",
            "c) Kilometres",
            "d) All the three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The displacements in shear zones are generally ductile in nature compared to brittle fracturing in simple faults or fault zones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The type of slip not considered for study is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike slip",
            "b) Dip slip",
            "c) Hade slip",
            "d) Oblique slip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We can observe numerous parallel placed fractured blocks in the shown region and this is possible in a fault zone. The picture depicts fault zone with distinct thickness and closely placed parallel fractures."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the vertical component of dip separation called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Offset",
            "b) Throw",
            "c) Heave",
            "d) Strike gap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slip is defined as a relative displacement of any points that were formerly contiguous to each other, as measured along the fault plane. It may be expressed in millimetres, metres or even kilometres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Heave is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal component of dip separation",
            "b) Vertical component of dip separation",
            "c) Normal horizontal displacement measured",
            "d) Signifying separation between two beds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heave is the horizontal component of dip separation measured in a direction perpendicular to the strike of the fault in a vertical plane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What signifies the actual separation between two beds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Throw",
            "b) Offset",
            "c) Heave",
            "d) Stratigraphic throw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stratigraphic throw signifies actual separation between two beds with a known stratigraphical position in a sequence of rocks that are now brought into contact by faulting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "What is the term related to slickensides and used to express the angular relationship?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rake",
            "b) Tweak",
            "c) Slick",
            "d) Offset"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rake is a term related to slickensides in faults. It is used to express the angular relationship of slickensides or some other line with the fault plane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Pick the term which is not a crushed material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gouge",
            "b) Fault breccia",
            "c) Kaolynite",
            "d) Mylonite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rubbing and mutual shearing of blocks during faulting, especially in brittle rocks, often produces typical crushed materials from the involved blocks that are useful indicators of faulting in that region. The most common and important products are: Gouge, Fault breccia and Mylonite."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "What is also called as Micro breccia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gouge",
            "b) Mylonite",
            "c) Kaolynite",
            "d) Shale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mylonite is also called as micro-breccia and is similar to fault breccia but contains very fine-grained broken particles from the involved rocks that get thoroughly cemented and compacted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The finely pulverized, clay-like powdered rock material is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gouge",
            "b) Fault breccia",
            "c) Mylonite",
            "d) Illite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gouge is finely pulverized, clay-like powdered rock material, which occurs at or near the base of the faulted zones."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Identify the region marked as “OP2”.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip",
            "b) Throw",
            "c) Heave",
            "d) Strike"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The evidence of slickensides may be expected only on the recently faulted surfaces because in the old faults such an evidence is more likely to be removed by subsequent weathering. "
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which type of classification emphasises on appearance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Based on direction of slip",
            "b) Based on apparent movement",
            "c) Based on mode of occurrence",
            "d) Based on amount of dip of the fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The emphasis in the case of faults based on apparent movement as basis is only on appearance because actually it may require to be established which of the two parts, hanging wall and the foot wall, has moved during faulting and by how much. "
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Type of fault not considered under apparent movement as basis is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal fault",
            "b) Reverse fault",
            "c) Hinge fault",
            "d) Strike fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The various faults under apparent movement as basis are, normal faults, reverse faults, hinge faults and strike-slip faults. Strike faults is not studied under this basis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Fault in which hanging wall has apparently moved down with respect to foot wall is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal fault",
            "b) Reverse fault",
            "c) Strike-slip fault",
            "d) Hinge fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normal fault is a fault in which hanging wall has apparently moved down with respect to foot wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "What do the normal faults cause to the crust of the Earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shortening of crest",
            "b) Cracking of crest",
            "c) Extension in the crust",
            "d) Strengthening of crust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to the inclines nature of the fault plane and downward displacement of a part of the strata, normal faults cause an extension in the crust wherever they occur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Most common angle of normal faults is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30° to 45°",
            "b) 45° to vertical",
            "c) 60° to horizontal",
            "d) 0° to 180°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nothing can be said with certainty whether it was the hanging wall which moved down or the foot wall which moved up or both the walls moved down, the hanging wall moving more than the foot wall and hence the appearance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What is the other name for normal faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform faults",
            "b) Hade faults",
            "c) Similar faults",
            "d) Gravity faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In normal faults, the fault plane may be inclines at any angle between horizontal and vertical, but most commonly, the fault angles are between 45° and vertical. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Alps in an example of which type of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graben",
            "b) Horst",
            "c) Hinge fault",
            "d) Vertical fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Normal faults are also often termed as gravity faults especially when it is established that the hanging wall has actually moved down with respect to the foot wall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Horst and graben are physiographic features of which type of faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal faults",
            "b) Reverse faults",
            "c) Thrust faults",
            "d) Strike-slip faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Numerous small and big examples of horsts are found in major mountain systems such as Alps, Central Europe and East Africa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The type of fault which appears in such a way that the central wedge appears raised high up with respect to the sides is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graben",
            "b) Horst",
            "c) Nappe",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Horst and graben are the physiographic features caused by normal faults occurring in pairs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Block mountains are caused by which type of faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horst",
            "b) Graben",
            "c) Thrust",
            "d) Nappes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When two normal faults appear on either side of a central wedge shaped elongated block in such a way that the central wedge appears raised high up with respect to the sides, the outstanding structure is called a horst. "
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which fault is the reverse of horst?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reverse fault",
            "b) Radial fault",
            "c) Graben",
            "d) Hinge fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes the horsts may be high and extensive enough to be called a Block mountain. In many horsts, the border faults are almost parallel in strike and very high angled."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Horsts and grabens are believed to occur due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral compression",
            "b) Shear compression",
            "c) Lateral tension",
            "d) Bending"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The origin of horsts and grabens is believed to be due to lateral tension in the crust in most cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Faults involving extensive blocks and resulting in horsts and grabens are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extensive faults",
            "b) Block faults",
            "c) H-B faults",
            "d) Vertical faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Faults involving extensive blocks and resulting in horsts and grabens are often called as block faults and the process as block faulting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Faults in which the fault plane is vertical and the resulting movement is vertical is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical faults",
            "b) Straight faults",
            "c) Reverse faults",
            "d) Enecholon faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Faults in which the fault plane is vertical or nearly so and the resulting movement of blocks is also in a vertical direction are termed as vertical faults. It is customary to group vertical faults along with normal faults while discussing their origin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "In which fault the hanging wall appears to have moved up with respect to the foot wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal fault",
            "b) Reverse fault",
            "c) Hinge fault",
            "d) Radial fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reverse fault is such a type of fault in which the hanging wall appears to have moved up with respect to the foot wall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The fault in which the fault plane is generally inclined between 45° and horizontal is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reverse fault",
            "b) Normal fault",
            "c) Strike-slip fault",
            "d) Enechelon fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In reverse faults, the fault plane is generally inclined between horizontal and 45 degrees although reverse faults with steeply inclined fault surfaces have been also encountered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What does the reverse fault cause to the crust of the Earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extension of the crust",
            "b) Strengthening of the crust",
            "c) Weakening of the crust",
            "d) Shortening of the crust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By virtue of their inclination and direction of movement, reverse faulting involves shortening of the crust of the crust of the Earth (compared with normal faults). "
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Thrust faults belong to which variety of faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal faults",
            "b) Reverse faults",
            "c) Strike-slip faults",
            "d) Hinge faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thrust faults are, broadly speaking, such varieties of reverse faults in which the hanging wall has moved up relative to the foot wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is the fault angle of the thrust faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than 45°",
            "b) Less than 45°",
            "c) Lesser than 60°",
            "d) More than 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thrust faults are the types of reverse faults in which the hanging wall has moved up relative to the foot wall and the faults dip at angles below 45 degrees. Faults dipping above 45 degrees with hanging wall having gone up are then called as reverse faults. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The type of thrust in which the hanging wall seems to have been actively and actually displaced with respect to a passive foot wall is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Under thrust",
            "b) Over thrust",
            "c) Upper thrust",
            "d) Intermediate thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thrusts are further distinguished into two sub-types: The over thrusts and the under thrusts. In the over thrusts, the hanging wall seems to have been actively and actually displaced with respect to a passive foot wall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which mountain range presents example of thrust faults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Alps",
            "b) The Andes",
            "c) The Rockies",
            "d) The Himalaya"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Himalayan Mountains in the Indian sub-continent present numerous examples of thrust faults developed all along its extension from northwest to southeast. "
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "What is the term used for blocks or rocks that have been translated to great distances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrusts",
            "b) Imbricate structures",
            "c) Nappes",
            "d) Enecholon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nappes is the term used for extensive blocks of rocks that have been translated to great distances, often ranging to several kilometres, along a thrust plane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The term which studied under faults but also is associated with folding is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nappes",
            "b) Thrusts",
            "c) Radial fault",
            "d) Graben"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The large-scale movement of nappes may be attributed to a major thrusting or a recumbent folding followed by thrust faulting."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "The phenomenon not associated with imbricate structures is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Series of thrust blocks occur in close proximity",
            "b) Thrust blocks are piled up one above another",
            "c) All fault surfaces dip in the same direction",
            "d) Thrust blocks aren’t piled up one above another"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a series of thrust faults occur in close proximity, thrust blocks are piled up one above another and all the fault surfaces dip in same direction. The resulting interesting structure is known as an imbricate structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Most common term used for strike-slip faults is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip fault",
            "b) Transform fault",
            "c) Tranlational fault",
            "d) Hinge fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the Himalayan Mountains, many well defined nappe zones have been recognized among which may be mentioned the Kashmir Nappe, the Nappe zone of Shimla Himalayas and the Nappes of the Garhwal Himalayas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The type of fault where the faulted blocks have been moved against each other in horizontal direction is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reverse fault",
            "b) Hinge fault",
            "c) Strike-slip fault",
            "d) Vertical fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are some other terms used for strike slip faults such as lateral faults, transverse faults, wrench faults and transform faults. Of these, the transform faults are very common and denote strike slip faults specially developed in oceanic ridges."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which fault is developed in oceanic ridges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wrench faults",
            "b) Transform faults",
            "c) Lateral faults",
            "d) Transverse faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Strike-slip faults are defined as the faults in which faulted blocks have been moved against each other in an essentially horizontal direction. The fault plane is almost vertical and net slip may be measured in great distances.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "San Andres fault is the best example of which type of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike-slip fault",
            "b) Vertical fault",
            "c) Normal fault",
            "d) Reverse fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The transform faults are very common and denote strike slip faults specially developed in oceanic ridges. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "If the left block appears to have moved towards the observer, then which type of fault does it belong to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Left-handed fault",
            "b) Right-handed fault",
            "c) Enecholon fault",
            "d) Radial fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best example of a strike-slip fault is the great San Andres fault of California. It extends for almost about 1000 km in an NW-SE direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "What are pivotal faults called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reverse faults",
            "b) Radial faults",
            "c) Hinge faults",
            "d) Normal faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the figure it is clear that the hanging wall has moved up with respect to the foot wall and hence clearly it is a reverse fault."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The movement of blocks in hinge faults is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translational",
            "b) Rotational",
            "c) Lateral",
            "d) Sliding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strike-slip faults are further distinguished into right handed or left handed depending on the direction of movement of the block with respect to an observer: it is a left-handed fault if the left block appears to have moved towards the observer and a right handed fault if the right block seems to have moved towards the observer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which is the rare type of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical fault",
            "b) Reverse fault",
            "c) Thrust fault",
            "d) Hinge fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hinge faults are also called as pivotal or rotational faults. A hinge fault is characterised by a movement of the disrupted blocks along with a medial point called the hinge point. "
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "What is the displacement range of strata in San Andres fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 km to 100 km",
            "b) 20 km to 80 km",
            "c) 50 km to 200 km",
            "d) 100 km to 500 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The movement in hinge fault, is rotational rather translational. "
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "The fault not belonging to the classification of fault with the attitude of fault as basis ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heave fault",
            "b) Strike fault",
            "c) Dip fault",
            "d) Oblique fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mutual relationship of attitude of fault and of the disrupted rock has also been used in some cases for classifying faults into three types: dip faults, strike faults and oblique faults. "
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Faults that are developed along bedding planes are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike faults",
            "b) Dip faults",
            "c) Bedding faults",
            "d) Hade faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sometimes he faults are developed along the bedding planes; in such cases, they are aptly called bedding faults."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "The fault where fault strike is parallel to the dip of the layers broken and disrupted by the fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dip faults",
            "b) Strike faults",
            "c) Oblique faults",
            "d) Hade faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dip faults are the faults which develop parallel to the dip of the strata. In other words, the fault strike is parallel to the dip of the layers broken and disrupted by the fault. "
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "The fault which is also called a diagonal fault is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wrench fault",
            "b) Transform fault",
            "c) Oblique fault",
            "d) Dip fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oblique faults are sometimes called diagonal faults. In such a fault, the fault strike makes an oblique angle with the strike of the rocks in which it has caused the displacement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "The type of fault which is observed in both continental and oceanic environment is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike-slip fault",
            "b) Dip fault",
            "c) Oblique fault",
            "d) Wrench fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strike-slip faults are the most important and widely developed faults in the crust of the earth, which have been observed both on the continental and oceanic environments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which is the type of strike-slip fault in which the fault plane has developed transverse to the regional structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transform fault",
            "b) Wrench fault",
            "c) Translational fault",
            "d) Tear fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wrench fault is a strike slip fault in origin in which the fault plane has developed transverse to the regional structure and even the net slip has taken place in the same manner. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Transverse fault is the other name for __________ fault.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transform fault",
            "b) Tear fault",
            "c) Wrench fault",
            "d) Normal fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dip of the wrench fault is very steep nearly vertical. These are also sometimes referred to as transverse faults. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Where do the transform faults occur extensively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continental blocks",
            "b) Oceanic ridges",
            "c) Island blocks",
            "d) Volcanic ridges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transform faults are strike-slip faults occurring in oceanic ridges on an extensive scale."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Identify the group of small sized faults from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel faults",
            "b) Enechelon faults",
            "c) Peripheral faults",
            "d) Radial faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enechelon faults may be defined as a group of small sized faults that overlap each other in the region of their occurrence. A second fault appears on the surface at a distance before the first fault ends and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Group of faults which appear emerging outward from a common central region are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enechelon faults",
            "b) Parallel faults",
            "c) Peripheral faults",
            "d) Radial faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A group faults that appear emerging outward from a common central region are classified as radial faults. The area is divided into blocks with inwardly tapering ends. "
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The type of fault not belonging to the classification based on the mode of occurrence is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel fault",
            "b) Peripheral fault",
            "c) Enechelon fault",
            "d) Wrench fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some cases, the intervening blocks are down thrown in the same general direction so that viewed from one side, the group gives a step-like appearance in the structure. These are then called step faults."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "What is the effect of faulting on outcrop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changes in the elevation of the ground",
            "b) Omission of some strata where they are normally expected",
            "c) Repetition of some strata in a given direction",
            "d) Changes in elevation, omission of some strata, repetition of some strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Faulting is essentially a process of rupturing and displacement along the plane of rupture. Its effects may involve- changes in the elevation of the ground, omission of some strata where they are normally expected, repetition of some strata in a given direction and displacements and shifts in the continuity of the same rocks in certain regions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What is the effect of strike faults to the strata?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extension",
            "b) Repetition",
            "c) Omission",
            "d) Repetition and repetition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Strike faults are those, which are developed parallel to the strike of the outcrops. These faults produce, besides other changes, two pronounced effects on the outcrops repetition and omission of strata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "When the downthrow is against direction of the bed, it leads to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omission",
            "b) Repetition",
            "c) Extension",
            "d) Weakening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Repetition of the strata occurs, when the downthrow is against the direction of the dip of the bed in which faulting has taken place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "When the downthrow is _____________ direction of the dip, it leads to omission.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel to",
            "b) Against",
            "c) Inclined at certain angle",
            "d) Doesn’t depend on downthrow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Omission of the strata takes place in a strike fault when the downthrow is parallel to the direction of slip of the faulted bed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What has to be studied at first to tell about the effects with certainty?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aerial photographs",
            "b) Globe",
            "c) Geological maps",
            "d) Topographical photographs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is only after the study of geological maps that the existence of faults at the first place and their effects on the rocks may get established with some certainty. "
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Dip fault leads to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal shift",
            "b) Vertical shift",
            "c) Inclined shift",
            "d) Outburst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In dip faults which occur parallel to the dip of the outcrop, the most prominent effect observed after faulting and erosion of the upthrown block is a horizontal shift between the two parts of the outcrop. "
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Which fault causes offset?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal fault",
            "b) Reverse fault",
            "c) Oblique fault",
            "d) Dip fault"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oblique faults cause an offset in the sequence, which is associated with either a gap or an overlap depending upon the downthrow direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Gap or overlap depends upon ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upthrow direction",
            "b) Downthrow direction",
            "c) Heave",
            "d) Hade angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oblique faults cause an offset in the sequence, which is associated with either a gap or an overlap depending upon the downthrow direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "What will result in an offset with overlap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Downthrow to left side",
            "b) Upthrow to left side",
            "c) Downthrow to right side",
            "d) Upthrow to right side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oblique faults with downthrow to the left side result in an offset with an overlap. "
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "What will result in an offset with gap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Downthrow to left side",
            "b) Upthrow to left side",
            "c) Downthrow to right side",
            "d) Upthrow to right side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oblique faults with downthrow to the right side result in an offset with a gap. "
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "What is the effect of faults on topography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault gaps",
            "b) Crust extension",
            "c) Fault scarps",
            "d) Crevices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effects of faults on different types of folded sequence is broadly the same as in plainly dipping strata. But with changes in the altitude of the faults or that of rocks, quite complicated results may be seen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The type of scarps not considered under study is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault scarps",
            "b) Dip scarps",
            "c) Fault-line scarps",
            "d) Composite-fault scarps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the main effects of the faults on topography is that they very often result in the development of distinct types of steep slopes which are aptly called fault scarps. "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "The fault which is the result of both fault scarps and fault-line scarps is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compound-fault scarps",
            "b) Composite-fault scarps",
            "c) Dual-fault scarps",
            "d) By-fault scarps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three types of fault associated scarps are often recognized: fault scarps, fault-line scarps and composite-fault scarps. "
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The type of scarp involving erosion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault scarp",
            "b) Fault-line scarp",
            "c) Composite-fault scarp",
            "d) Dip-fault scarp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a given slope is believed to be the result of both of these processes, fault scarp and fault-line scarp, the scarp is of composite type, and is called composite-fault scarp. "
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "What is the criteria for a covered surface to be said a fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polished surface",
            "b) Grooves",
            "c) Striations",
            "d) Polished surface, grooves and striations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An exposed or covered surface may be suspected of being a faulted surface if it polished, and carries grooves and striations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "What is the reason for abrupt termination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breaking of strata into blocks",
            "b) Movement of the disrupted blocks away from each other",
            "c) Breaking of strata into blocks and movement of disrupted blocks away from each other",
            "d) Movement of the disrupted blocks towards each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A group of beds or some veins or dykes may abruptly terminate along a surface in a given region. This may generally be due to breaking of the strata into blocks and movement of the disrupted blocks away from each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "What is indicative of faulting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repetition",
            "b) Omission",
            "c) Repetition and omission",
            "d) Cracking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When in the field the same layer or rock is encountered more than once in a certain section, that is, it is repeated in space, faulting is indicated. Similarly, omission of certain of beds in some directions as proved by thorough study of stratigraphy of the region, is also indicative of faulting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Disruption of beds due to faulting results in their ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Displacement",
            "b) Settling",
            "c) Inclination",
            "d) Change in their composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Disruption of the beds due to faulting generally results in their displacement, which may be determined in terms of slip, separation, offset and gap etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "What kind of evidence the physiographic features provide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct",
            "b) Indirect",
            "c) Certain",
            "d) Uncertain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some physiographic features may serve as indirect evidence of faults. Among them, the most important are: aligned springs and offset streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "The important physiographic evidence studied is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aligned spring",
            "b) Offset stream",
            "c) Mountain range",
            "d) Offset stream and aligned spring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Some physiographic features may serve as indirect evidence of faults. Among them, the most important are: aligned springs and offset streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The resistance to stresses of rocks depend upon ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive strength only",
            "b) Internal friction only",
            "c) Cohesive strength and internal friction",
            "d) Hardness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any rock on or below the crust may withstand all the operating stresses up to a limit, which depends upon its cohesive strength and internal friction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "When are the normal stresses formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum stress is horizontal",
            "b) Maximum stress is vertical",
            "c) Maximum stress is inclined at certain angle other than right angle",
            "d) Intermediate stress is vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In highly oversimplified situation, the type of fault likely to form is related to stress field operating in a given area. Thus, talking in terms of the three principal stresses, normal faults would form when, the maximum stress is vertical. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "What is the assumed nature of the rock for the study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isotropic",
            "b) Anisotropic",
            "c) Uniform",
            "d) Non-uniform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: a\nExplanation: In all the idealized situations, it is assumed that the rocks are isotropic in character and the Mohr-Coulomb Law of rock failure holds good in those cases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What is the cause for compressive force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical tension",
            "b) Horizontal tension",
            "c) Vertical compression",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gravity or normal faults are believed to be caused under the influence of horizontal tension whereas thrust faults are the result of compressive forces that may throw the rocks into severe type of folding before actual development of faults. "
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What kind of joints do the faulted rocks form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong",
            "b) Weak",
            "c) Doesn’t change",
            "d) Extended"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The faulted rocks will form weak foundations and abutments for dam, despite the fact that originally they might have been strong and impervious. "
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "When do the faulted and shear zones become potential areas of further slip and slides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry",
            "b) Lubricated",
            "c) Weathered",
            "d) Heavy winds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Once the fault zones, shear zones or fault surfaces become lubricated with water, they become potential areas for further slips and slides. They may create critical conditions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Where should a site for a civil engineering project be located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On faulted zone",
            "b) On a folded strata",
            "c) On a joint",
            "d) Must be avoided to possible extent to be built on all three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As far as possible the location of a civil engineering project must be avoided on a fault or a fold or a joint. But when there is no other choice, the same location can be treated with necessary methods and then the project can be implemented. "
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "What is not considered about the shear zones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number",
            "b) Size",
            "c) Inclination",
            "d) Appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number, size and inclination of the shear zones should be given top consideration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Bhakra dam in India showed which occurrence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault zones",
            "b) Slickensides",
            "c) Shear zones",
            "d) Folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The embankment of the Bhakra dam in India showed occurrence of numerous shear zones in them; the site could not be changed because of other reasons; hence it was decided to treat the shear zones by extensive excavations of the shear zones and back filling with cement grouting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What are faults associated with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic activity",
            "b) Precipitation",
            "c) Earthquake",
            "d) Folds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Faults of any significance are always associated with earthquakes. The tectonic history of the area under consideration must be known thoroughly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is recommended to be introduced to the structures even on safe land?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proper dimensioning",
            "b) Proper planning",
            "c) Use high quality materials",
            "d) Factor safety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Some factor of safety has to be introduced in the building even though the tectonic history indicates not movement of the surface or plate. It is always recommended to introduce factor of safety for high raised buildings or even buildings which are built on active seismic zones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Studying tectonic history is basically like knowing ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of earthquake",
            "b) Effects",
            "c) Frequency, effects and magnitude",
            "d) Cost for recuperation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Study of tectonic history would virtually mean obtaining information about the frequency of the earthquakes as also their magnitude and effects that they have left from time to time on the rocks of the region. "
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "What is responsible for jointing of rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genesis",
            "b) Forces acting on the rock",
            "c) Genesis and various forces acting on the rock",
            "d) Precipitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We may find quite a large proportion of outcrop of any of these rocks practically free from joints at some places, but at other places the same type of rock may be heavily jointed, showing cracks of greater variety. Hence it is not only genesis of the rocks which responsible for these structures but also the forces acting on them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Fractures along which there has been no relative displacement is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faults",
            "b) Joints",
            "c) Folds",
            "d) Intrusions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Joints are defined as divisional planes or fractures along which there has been no relative displacement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The open joints are gradually enlarged due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rains",
            "b) Winds",
            "c) Weathering",
            "d) Sunlight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Joints may be open or closed. Open joints are those in which the blocks have been separated or opened up for small distances. In closed joints, there is no such separation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "The type of joint usually found is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open joints",
            "b) Close joints",
            "c) Open and close joints",
            "d) Faulted joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Open joints are those in which the blocks have been separated or opened up for small distances in a direction at right angles to the fracture surface. These may be gradually enlarged by weathering processes and develop fissures in the rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "When the joints are prominent and extending for considerable depth they are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous joints",
            "b) Discontinuous joints",
            "c) Deep joints",
            "d) Prominent joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There may be or may not be an opening up of blocks perpendicular to the joint planes. Hence the joints may be of open or close nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "What are the continuous joints also called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform joints",
            "b) Normal joints",
            "c) Prime joints",
            "d) Master joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answers: a\nExplanation: The joints which are quite prominent and extending for considerable depth and thickness are called as continuous joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "The streaks or bands filling material in the rocks are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour pigments",
            "b) Resins",
            "c) Veins",
            "d) Pores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The continuous joints are also called often as master joints. Almost all joints are discontinuous in the strict sense because these disappear with depth in the crust of the earth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "When the thickness is greater than 20 cm, the veins area called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thick veins",
            "b) Fissure veins",
            "c) Joint veins",
            "d) Broad veins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In many cases, open joints get filled up by solutions of secondary materials that crystallize or precipitate there forming thin or thick streaks or bands of the filling material. These are simply called veins. "
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A joint set is a group of joint surfaces",
            "b) The surfaces trend in same direction",
            "c) The surfaces have almost same dip",
            "d) The joint surfaces do no trend in same direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thin or thick filling material in the joints of the rocks are called as veins when thin and when their thickness exceeds 20 cm they are called fissure veins. "
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Group of joint sets are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joint system",
            "b) Joint group",
            "c) Joint class",
            "d) Joint collection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joints have dip and strike, the dip being their inclination with the horizontal and the strike being the direction of intersection of a joint plane with a horizontal plane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The classification which is not considered under study is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spatial relationship",
            "b) Number of joints",
            "c) Geometry",
            "d) Genesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Joints have been classified on the basis of spatial relationships, geometry and genesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "The type of joint which can be measured and mapped easily is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Systematic joints",
            "b) Non-systematic joints",
            "c) Irregular joints",
            "d) Homogenous joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Systematic joints show a distinct regularity in their occurrence which can be measured and mapped easily. "
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Example of systematic joints are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Columnar joints",
            "b) Mural joints",
            "c) Sheet joints",
            "d) Columnar and mural joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Systematic joints occur in parallel or sub-parallel joint sets that are represented in the rocks at regular intervals. The columnar joints and the mural joints are examples of regular or systematic jointing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "How many groups are classified based on the presence of regularities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All joints are divided into two main groups on the basis of presence or otherwise of some regularity in their occurrence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which type of rocks are classified based on geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudo-stratified",
            "b) Stratified",
            "c) Non-stratified",
            "d) Anisotropic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In stratified rocks, joints are generally classified on the basis of the relationship of their attitude with that of the rocks in which they occur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "How many types are further classified based on geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Under the classification based on geometry, three types are recognized: Strike joints, dip joints, oblique joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The type of joint not studied under the geometry as basis is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike joints",
            "b) Dip joints",
            "c) Hade joints",
            "d) Oblique joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only three types of joints are studied under the classification of joints on the basis of geometry; strike joints, dip joints and oblique joints. Hade joint is not a type of joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the other name for diagonal joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dip joints",
            "b) Strike joints",
            "c) Sheet joints",
            "d) Oblique joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oblique joints are those joints where the strike of the joints is at any angle between the dip and the strike of the layers. These layers are also called diagonal joints when they occur midway between the dip and strike of the layers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Joints parallel to bedding planes are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike joints",
            "b) Bedding joints",
            "c) Dip joints",
            "d) Oblique joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In stratified rocks, some joints ma develop essentially parallel to the bedding planes. These are simply referred as bedding planes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Joints running parallel to hinge lines are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hinge joints",
            "b) Radial joints",
            "c) Bedding joints",
            "d) Oblique joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the folded regions, joint orientation is conveniently described with reference to the hinge of the fold. Joints running parallel to the hinge line are called radial joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "In which rock, joints may be classified on the basis of their lineation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentary",
            "b) Igneous",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Igneous and metamorphic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In igneous and metamorphic rocks, the joints may be classified on the basis of their geometric relations with planar structures of those rocks such as lineation or cleavage."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Joints traverse linear structure right angles in which type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q joints",
            "b) S joints",
            "c) B joints",
            "d) T joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cross or Q joints are the joints that are traversing the linear structures at right angles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Which are the joints parallel to linear structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross joints",
            "b) Longitudinal joints",
            "c) Alternate joints",
            "d) Q joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Longitudinal or S joints, are the joints traversing parallel to the linear structure. In these rocks all the joint systems traversing at any other angular inclination with the linear structures are described as diagonal joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "The joints developed due to tensile forces are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tensile joints",
            "b) Compressive joints",
            "c) Shear joints",
            "d) No particular name"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tension joints are those, which have developed due to the tensile forces acting on the rocks. The most common location of such joints in the folded sequence is on the outer margins of crests and troughs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "The type of joint occurring in igneous rocks during cooling is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear joints",
            "b) Tensile joints",
            "c) Compression joints",
            "d) Bend joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tension joints are also produced in igneous rocks during their cooling. Joints produced in many rocks during the weathering of overlying strata and subsequent release of stresses by expansion are also thought to be due to the tensile forces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which joints are located in axial regions in the folded rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tension joints",
            "b) Compression joints",
            "c) Shear joints",
            "d) T joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shear joints are commonly observed in the vicinity of fault planes and shear zone where the relationship with shearing forces is clearly established. In folded rocks, these are located in axial regions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "The joints that are caused due to compressive forces are called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T joints",
            "b) C joints",
            "c) Longitudinal joints",
            "d) Compression joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rocks may be compressed to crushing and numerous joints may result due to the compressive forces in this case. "
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Compression joints usually occur in which part of fault?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crust",
            "b) Mantle",
            "c) Core",
            "d) Margins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the core regions of folds where compressive forces are dominant, joints may be related to the compressive forces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Tensile stresses in igneous rocks are developed during ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cooling",
            "b) Crystallisation",
            "c) Cooling and crystallisation",
            "d) Molten state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The igneous rocks are formed by cooling and crystallisation of hot molten material called magma or lava. As such, in most cases they show joint systems related to the tensile stresses developing during the process of cooling and crystallisation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The type of regular joint not belonging to igneous rocks is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet jointing",
            "b) Box jointing",
            "c) Mural jointing",
            "d) Columnar jointing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The three regular or systematic types of joints observed in igneous rocks are: sheet joints, mural joints and columnar joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which jointing gives layered sedimentary structure appearance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet jointing",
            "b) Mural jointing",
            "c) Box jointing",
            "d) Columnar jointing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In granites and other related igneous rocks, a horizontal set of joints often divides the rock mass in such a way as to give it an appearance of a layered sedimentary structure, called in this case as a sheeting structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Sheet joints are caused not due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consequence of loading",
            "b) Weathering",
            "c) Removal of overlying rock mass",
            "d) Consequence of unloading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sheet joints are sometimes caused due to weathering and removal of overlying rock masses, which cause expansion of the underlying igneous and other rocks as a consequence of unloading. "
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "The geometrical distribution where rock mass is divided into cubes is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet jointing",
            "b) Mural jointing",
            "c) Columnar jointing",
            "d) Radial jointing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mural jointing is a sort of geometrical distribution of joints dividing the rock mass into cubical blocks or murals and hence the name. "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Types of joint found in volcanic igneous rocks are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet joints",
            "b) Mural joints",
            "c) Columnar joints",
            "d) Radial joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Columnar joints are typical of volcanic igneous rocks although they may also be observed in other rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Columnar joints are also called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial joints",
            "b) Pyramid joints",
            "c) Prismatic joints",
            "d) Box joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Columnar joints are also called as prismatic joints. The joints divide the rock mass into polygonal blocks each block being bounded by three to eight sides. "
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "How are the main joints aligned to the cooling surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perpendicular",
            "b) Parallel",
            "c) At 45°",
            "d) At 30°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normally, the main joints are vertical or perpendicular to the cooling surface and may extend to varying depths ranging a few centimetres to many metres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "How and what are the polygonal cracks related to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly related to compressive forces",
            "b) Directly related to tensile forces",
            "c) Inversely related to tensile forces",
            "d) Directly related to shearing forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The polygonal cracks are thought to be directly related to the tensile forces developed during cooling (accompanied by contraction) of hot molten material (lava). "
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The contraction is equally developed in all directions in which kind of mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-homogenous",
            "b) Isotropic",
            "c) Anisotropic",
            "d) Homogenous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a homogenous mass undergoing uniform cooling throughout the surface, contraction is equally developed in all directions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "At what angle do the fractures appear to the lines of tensile stresses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 180°",
            "b) 90°",
            "c) 45°",
            "d) 60°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the strength of the rock is overcome, fractures appear at right angles to the lines of tensile forces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Joints in metamorphic rocks are due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect stresses",
            "b) Local stresses",
            "c) Regional stresses",
            "d) Local and regional stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since sedimentary rocks are often folded and faulted, the joints in them are genetically related to those forces that have caused the major structural deformations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The nature of sedimentary rock that can undergo some irregular jointing is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastic in nature",
            "b) Non-plastic in nature",
            "c) Rich in moisture",
            "d) Plastic in nature and rich in moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks especially those of plastic nature and rich in moisture in the initial stage (clays, shales, limestones, dolomites etc.) undergo some contraction on drying up which might have resulted into irregular jointing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Contraction or shrinkage is the cause of which joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial joints",
            "b) Vertical joints",
            "c) Sheet joints",
            "d) Mural joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the formation of igneous rocks, tensile forces are developed in them due to cooling and the force is strong enough to cause joints. Such contraction or shrinkage is generally, accepted to be the cause of the vertical type of joints in granites and the so well -known columnar joints of basalts and other effusive rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The wide range of temperature which vary in arid climate is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -10° to 100° C",
            "b) 10° to 80° C",
            "c) -50° to 60°C",
            "d) 50° to 60° C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Joints are caused in different rocks due to different reasons. No single theory can explain origin of all types of joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Removal of overburden causes ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expansion",
            "b) Contraction",
            "c) Shrinkage",
            "d) Rise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Repeated expansion and contraction is characteristic of regions with dry hot (arid) climates where day and night temperatures on the one hand and summer and winter temperatures on the other hand vary within a very wide range of -50° to 60° C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Sheet joints in sedimentary rocks are attributed to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erosional loading",
            "b) Erosional unloading",
            "c) Weathering loading",
            "d) Weathering unloading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Removal of overburden due to weathering or other processes of rock wasting may also cause expansion of the underlying rocks due to unloading. The previously loaded rocks get relaxed with the release of the forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What kind of impact do the joints have on activities of engineering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive",
            "b) Negative",
            "c) No impact",
            "d) Positive and negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sheet joints of sedimentary rocks and other rocks are attributed by many to the process of erosional unloading through geological ages. "
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What is/are related to jointed rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthquakes",
            "b) Landslides",
            "c) Slope failures",
            "d) Landslides and slope failures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Joints affect the properties of rocks both in a negative as well as positive manner with respect to the activities of a professional civil and mining engineer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "First step of treatment of joints is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grouting",
            "b) Filling with chemicals",
            "c) Detailed investigation",
            "d) Installing devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Many landslides and slope failures are directly related to the jointed nature of the rocks. This is due to instability of rocks in hilly regions and the jointed rocks get easily lubricated in presence of moisture and start sliding or falling from their places. "
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What has to be located during an investigation with great care?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macro joints",
            "b) Fissures",
            "c) Micro joints",
            "d) Macro joints and micro joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Treating the negative qualities of rocks due to joints will differ in different projects. The first requirement in all cases is, however, detailed investigations to establish full characteristics of the joints."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "What is a positive effect of joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instability in slopes",
            "b) Groundwater",
            "c) Oil reserves",
            "d) Groundwater and oil reserves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Great care has to be exercised in locating the presence, distribution patterns and magnitude of micro joints that are typical of many rocks. Such joints, if left unnoticed and untreated, may widen after the construction of the project and endanger its stability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about a mineral?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Naturally occurring",
            "b) Inorganic substance",
            "c) Organic substance",
            "d) Definite chemical composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A mineral, is defined as, a naturally occurring inorganic solid substance that is characterized with a definite chemical composition and very often with a definite atomic structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Mineralogy deals with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Individual properties of minerals",
            "b) Formation of minerals",
            "c) More of occurrence",
            "d) Properties, formation and occurrence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mineralogy is the branch of geology dealing with the wide range of aspects related to minerals like their individual properties, mode of occurrence and mode of formation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "A colour is produced due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflection",
            "b) Refraction",
            "c) Absorption",
            "d) Reflection and absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A particular colour is produced by reflection of some and absorption of other components of white light."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Colour of a mineral depends upon its?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomic structure",
            "b) Outer surface",
            "c) Composition",
            "d) Atomic structure and composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A mineral shows colour of that wavelength of the white light which is not absorbed by it by virtue of its composition and atomic structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Metallic minerals belong to which category with respect to colour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idiochromatic",
            "b) Pseudochromatic",
            "c) Allochromatic",
            "d) Iridescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Idiochromatic having a characteristic, fairly constant colour related primarily to the composition of mineral. Metallic minerals belong to this category. "
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "The type of mineral showing variable colour is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idiochromatic",
            "b) Allochromatic",
            "c) Iridescence",
            "d) Pseudochromatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Allochromatic minerals have a variable colour; the variety in colour is generally due to minute quantities of colouring impurities thoroughly dispersed in the mineral composition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "The type of mineral which shows a set of colours in succession is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idiochromatic",
            "b) Pseudochromatic",
            "c) Allochromatic",
            "d) Iridescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pseudochromatic minerals show false colour. Such an effect generally happens when a mineral is rotated in hand; it is then seen to show a set colours in succession. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Pseudochromatism occurs due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflection",
            "b) Transmittance",
            "c) Refraction",
            "d) Simultaneous reflection and refraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Many non-metallic minerals like quartz, calcite, fluorine, tourmaline etc. may occur in more than two colours depending on the nature of impurities. "
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The phenomenon due to which a mineral shows rainbow colours is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idiochromatism",
            "b) Allochromatism",
            "c) Iridescence",
            "d) Pseudochromatism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Psuodochromatism is attributed to simultaneous reflection and refraction from the mineral surface due to minute inclusions of impurities in the mineral at different locations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Colour changing phenomenon which involves oxidation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tarnish",
            "b) Iridescence",
            "c) Allochromatic",
            "d) Idiochromatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tarnish nay be described as a phenomenon of change of original colours of mineral to some secondary colours at its surface due its oxidation at the surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Lustre doesn’t depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Refractive index mineral",
            "b) Absorption of mineral",
            "c) Transmittance of mineral",
            "d) Nature of reflecting surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lustre depends on: refractive index of the mineral, absorption capacity of the mineral and nature of reflecting surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "High density, high refractive index is characteristic of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-metallic minerals",
            "b) Metallic minerals",
            "c) Semi-metallic minerals",
            "d) Metalloid minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lustre is entirely independent of colour of the mineral. A deeply coloured mineral may be lustreless and vice-versa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Type of shine or lustre associated with lustre of diamond is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adamantine",
            "b) Metallic",
            "c) Pearly",
            "d) Vitreous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metallic lustres are characteristics of high density, high refractive index and opaque minerals like galena, pyrite and chalcopyrite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Streak is an important diagnostic property of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-coloured minerals",
            "b) Coloured minerals",
            "c) Metallic minerals",
            "d) Non-metallic minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adamantine is the other name for shine of diamonds. Very brilliant; the best example is diamond. "
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which mineral gives streak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coloured and translucent",
            "b) Colourless and opaque",
            "c) Coloured and opaque",
            "d) Coloured and transparent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streak is an important diagnostic property of many coloured minerals. Simply defined as the colour of the finely powdered mineral as obtained by scratching or rubbing the mineral over rough unglazed porcelain plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "The mineral which is almost black but gives brown streak is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetite",
            "b) Garnet",
            "c) Hornblende",
            "d) Chromite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Colourless and transparent minerals will always give a colourless streak that has no significance. The coloured and opaque minerals, especially of ore groups, give typically characteristic streaks quite different from other similarly looking minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Hardness of a mineral depends upon ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical composition",
            "b) Atomic constitution",
            "c) Chemical composition and atomic constitution",
            "d) Physical makeup"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chromite and magnetite resemble closely in their other physical properties: both are almost black. These may be at once distinguished by their streaks: brown for chromite and black for magnetite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The scale of hardness is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ritcher",
            "b) Mohs",
            "c) Ohm",
            "d) Mho"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hardness may be defined as the resistance, which a mineral offers to an external deformation action such as scratching, abrasion, rubbing or indentation. Hardness of a mineral depends on its chemical composition and atomic constitution. "
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Hardness of human nail varies between ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 to 1.5",
            "b) 3 to 4",
            "c) 1.5 to 2.5",
            "d) 2.5 to 3.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some common materials have been assigned hardness values according to Mohs scale and may prove useful in determination of hardness of an unknown mineral quickly. Hardness of human finger nail varies between 1.5 and 2.5. "
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Hardness is which kind of property?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isotropic",
            "b) Anisotropic",
            "c) Homogenous",
            "d) Non-homogenous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hardness is an anisotropic property; a mineral may show different values in different directions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "How does hardness vary with decomposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases with decomposition",
            "b) Decreases with decomposition",
            "c) Does not change",
            "d) Either decreases or increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hardness decreases on the decomposition of a mineral due to atmospheric attack on the surface. Hence, it must be checked on unweathered and unaltered surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "The tendency of a crystallized mineral to break along certain directions yielding more or less smooth, plane surfaces is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tenacity",
            "b) Hardness",
            "c) Cleavage",
            "d) Fracture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hardness is a relative property. If talc has H=1 and Quartz H=7, it does not indicate quartz is seven times harder than talc."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Cleavage is described in terms of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of direction",
            "b) Degree of perfect splitting",
            "c) Degree of cracking",
            "d) Degree of perfect splitting and number of direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cleavage is defined as the tendency of a crystallized mineral to break along certain directions yielding more or less smooth, plane surfaces. In other words, cleavage are the planes easiest fractures and are essentially indicative of directions of least cohesion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The type of cleavage due to the mineral can be split very easily is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eminent cleavage",
            "b) Distinct cleavage",
            "c) Basal cleavage",
            "d) Cubic cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cleavage is described both in terms of a number of directions in which it is observed on a mineral and also in terms of the degree of perfect splitting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Mineral which shows parting is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthoclase",
            "b) Calcite",
            "c) Mica",
            "d) Corundum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In terms of perfection, the cleavage is described as eminent, perfect, good, distinct and indistinct in that order. In eminent cleavage, the mineral can be split very easily yielding extremely smooth surfaces, e.g., in mica. "
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about the fracture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the broken surface of a mineral along the direction of cleavage",
            "b) It is the broken surface of a mineral in a direction other than that of cleavage",
            "c) In some cases it becomes a characteristic property of a mineral",
            "d) Even and uneven are examples of fractures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parting is a property of minerals by virtue of which it can be split easily along certain secondary planes. Best example of parting can be seen in corundum where cleavage may be absent but parting may be very prominent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "The term which means, rough woody fracture is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uneven",
            "b) Conchoidal",
            "c) Splintry",
            "d) Hackly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The appearance of the broken surface of a mineral in a direction other than that of cleavage is generally expressed by the term fracture. In some cases, fracture becomes a characteristic property of a mineral. "
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "The behaviour of a mineral towards the forces that tend to destroy it is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness",
            "b) Resistance",
            "c) Tenacity",
            "d) Crystal degree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the mineral breaks with a rough woody fracture resulting in rough projection at the surface it is known as sprintly fracture. Example, Kyanite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The property of a mineral by virtue of which it can be cut with a knife is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parting",
            "b) Sectile",
            "c) Malleable",
            "d) Ductile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The behaviour of a mineral towards the forces that tend to break, bend, cut or crush is described by the term tenacity. Thus, when a mineral can be cut with a knife, it is described as sectile. "
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Mica is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible",
            "b) Rigid",
            "c) Flexible and elastic",
            "d) Elastic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some minerals are not only flexible but elastic, that is, they regain their shape when the force applied on them is removed. Micas are the best example. Hence they are both flexible and elastic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "When the mineral occurs in flattened or square form, it is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tabular",
            "b) Elongated",
            "c) Batroidal",
            "d) Box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mineral occurs in the form of a flattened, square, rectangular or rhombohedral shape if it is said to be tabular. In other words, flattening is conspicuous compared to lengthwise elongation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Example for elongated structure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcite",
            "b) Beryl",
            "c) Orthoclase",
            "d) Barite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the mineral is in the form of a thin or thick elongated, column-like crystals, it is said to be elongated. For example, Beryl. "
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Kyanite shows which form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Columnar",
            "b) Elongated",
            "c) Bladed",
            "d) Tabular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mineral appears as if composed of thin, flat, blade-like overlapping or juxtaposed parts, if it said to be bladed. Example: Kyanite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Structure or form which depicts leaf-like sheets is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foliated",
            "b) Lamellar",
            "c) Radiating",
            "d) Granular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mineral is made up of relatively thick, flexible, leaf-like sheets, if it is said to be lamellar. Example: Vermiculite."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Muscovite mica shows which structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamellar",
            "b) Foliated",
            "c) Fibrous",
            "d) Radiating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The foliated structure is similar to lamellar in broader sense but in this case, the individual sheets are paper thin, even thinner and can be easily separated. Example: Muscovite mica. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Identify the type of structure shown below.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamellar",
            "b) Foliated",
            "c) Radiating",
            "d) Granular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mineral is made up of needle like or fibrous crystals which appear originating from a common point thereby giving a radiating appearance, if it is said to be radiating. Example: Iron pyrites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Chromite shows which type of structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granular",
            "b) Globular",
            "c) Reniform",
            "d) Mammillary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mineral occurs in the form of densely packed mass of small garin-like crystals, in the case of globular structure. Example: Chromite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which form resembles a human kidney?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Globular",
            "b) Reniform",
            "c) Granular",
            "d) Mammillary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reniform is similar to globular but the shape of the bulbs or projections resembles to human kidneys. Example: Hematite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Malachite shows which type of structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reniform",
            "b) Globular",
            "c) Mammillary",
            "d) Granular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mammillary is similar to globular but the projections are conspicuous in size, overlapping in arrangement and rounded in shape, best example is malachite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The SI unit of specific gravity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ohm",
            "b) g/cc",
            "c) N/cc",
            "d) No unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Specific gravity is the ratio between the density of a mineral and that of water at 4° Celsius. Since it is a ratio, it has no units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "The density range lies between 2.5 and 4.5 g/cc for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metallic minerals",
            "b) Non-metallic minerals",
            "c) Metalloid minerals",
            "d) Ore minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The non-metallic minerals have low values of density, ranging between 2.5 and 4.5 g/cc, whereas metallic minerals and ores have densities as high as 20 g/cc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Atoms of greater atomic radii show __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less density",
            "b) Greater density",
            "c) No difference",
            "d) Doesn’t depend on atomic radii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minerals with atoms of greater atomic radii show less density values compared with those made of atoms of smaller atomic radii. "
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Form in which neither a crystal face nor a cleavage is seen is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crystalline",
            "b) Crystallized",
            "c) Amorphous",
            "d) Crystalline and crystallized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amorphous form is a form in which neither a crystal face nor a cleavage is seen. There is no evidence of orderly arrangement of atoms in this form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The minerals which develop electric charge upon heating are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyro-electric minerals",
            "b) Piezo-electric minerals",
            "c) Paramagnetic minerals",
            "d) Diamagnetic minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:a\nExplanation: In some minerals an electric charge may be developed by heating. These are called pyroelectric minerals. Examples: Tourmaline, boracite, quartz etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "The Phenomenon where electric charge develops due to application of pressure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyro-electric minerals",
            "b) Piezo-electric minerals",
            "c) Paramagnetic minerals",
            "d) Diamagnetic minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In some minerals, an electric charge is developed by applying pressure. This group is termed as piezo-electric. Examples: Tourmaline and quartz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "How many minerals are present in the scale of fusibility given by Von Kobell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A scale of fusibility has been suggested by Von Kobell. It consists of six minerals arranged according to temperature of fusion. Stibnite, Natrolite, Alamandine, Actinolite, Orthoclase and Bronzite.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the following minerals can scratch Topaz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corundum",
            "b) Apatite",
            "c) Gypsum",
            "d) Quartz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since temperature and pressure are both known to change volume of substance, it follows that density will also show a change when a mineral is subjected to elevated temperature or high pressures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following mineral shows phosphorescence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthoclase",
            "b) Calcite",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Galena"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only corundum can scratch topaz because, all the other minerals given have lesser Mohs number compared to topaz, whereas topaz as hardness number 8 and corundum has 9. "
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Quartz shows which lustre?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metallic",
            "b) Vitreous",
            "c) Pearly",
            "d) Resinous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It follows that the colour of a mineral may not be the same as its streak. For identification, streak is relied upon more than the colour of the mineral. "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which among the following shows silky lustre?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz",
            "b) Galena",
            "c) Gypsum",
            "d) Diamond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phosphorescence is similar to fluorescence in essential character but in this case light is emitted by mineral not during the act of exposure but after the substance is transferred rapidly to a dark place. Fluorite, quartz, willemite and diamond show this phenomenon. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which mineral group is abundantly found in the earth’s crust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mica group",
            "b) Felspar group",
            "c) Oxide group",
            "d) Silicate group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The felspars (The feldspars in American technology) are the most prominent group of minerals making more than fifty percent, by weight, crust of the Earth up to a depth of 30 km.    "
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Felspar is found abundantly or in majority in which kind of rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rocks",
            "b) Sedimentary rocks",
            "c) Metamorphic rocks",
            "d) Fossil rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Felspars occur chiefly, in the igneous rocks (more than 60 percent) but also occur in good proportion in the metamorphic rocks. Felspars are also found in some sedimentary rocks like arkose and greywacks."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The chemical composition of the feldspar group is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxide",
            "b) Aluminates",
            "c) Silicates",
            "d) Aluminosilicates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In chemical composition, felspars are chiefly aluminosilicates (also referred as alumosilicates) of Na, K and Ca with the following general formula, WZ4O8, in which W=Na, K, Ca and Ba and Z= Si and Al. "
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "In the atomic structure, each oxygen atom is shared by how many tetrahedra?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At atomic level, the felspars show a continuous three-dimensional network type of structure in which the SiO4 tetrahedra are linked at all the corners, each oxygen ion begin shared by two adjacent tetrahedral."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "The crystallographic system shown by felspar group is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monoclinic",
            "b) Triclinic",
            "c) Rhomboclinic",
            "d) Monoclinic and triclinic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The felspar group of minerals crystallise only in two crystallographic systems: Monoclinic and triclinic. Infact, the plagioclase division of felspars crystallizes only in triclinic system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "How many groups are the felspar minerals classified into, on the basis of chemical composition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Felspars are classified both on the basis of their chemical composition and also on their mode of crystallization, Chemically, felspars fall into two main groups: the potash felspars and the soda lime felspars."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The felspar minerals are free from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron",
            "b) Iron and manganese",
            "c) Magnesium",
            "d) Iron and magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The felspar group minerals are generally light in colour, because of the absence of Fe and Mg. The minerals have lower specific gravity (generally around 2.6), have doubly cleavage and a hardness varying between 6-6.5. "
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "What is the chemical composition of Orthoclase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K Al O8",
            "b) Ca Al Si3O8",
            "c) K Al Si3 O8",
            "d) Ca Al O8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Orthoclase mineral has the specific gravity around 2.56 to 2.58. Its chemical composition is K Al Si3O8. It is the most common and essential constituent of many igneous rocks, especially granite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is the distinguishing characteristic of microcline and orthoclase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour",
            "b) Streak",
            "c) Chemical composition",
            "d) Hardness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both orthoclase and microcline have same colour but microcline gives white streak whereas, orthoclase does not give any streak. Chemical composition and hardness are almost same for both the minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about plagioclase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is composed of K mainly",
            "b) It is composed of either Na, Ca, or Al",
            "c) It is of massive or crystalline structure",
            "d) It gives 2 sets of cleavages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plagioclase is usually composed of either Na or Ca or Al or combination of them. K is present in orthoclase and not in plagioclase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "The mica group minerals show which structure in the microscopic level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Box structure",
            "b) Sheet structure",
            "c) Hexagonal structure",
            "d) Columnar structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The micaceous cleavage is explained by their atomic structure: they constitute of SiO4 tetrahedra linked at three of their corners and extending in two dimensions. This is called a sheet structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "What percent of crust do the micas form approximately?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20%",
            "b) More than 60%",
            "c) 4%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sheets are held together in pairs by metallic ions. But the bond so resulting due to the metallic ions is the weakest and hence there is an eminent cleavage present in the micas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which is the less important and more important and less important minerals crystallize respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triclinic and monoclinic",
            "b) Monoclinic and triclinic",
            "c) Monoclinic and rhombohedral",
            "d) Rhombohedral and triclinic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Micas are, besides felspars, pyroxenes and amphiboles, very common rock forming minerals forming approximately 4 percent of the crust of the Earth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What type of cleavage is shown by mica group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perfect cubic cleavage",
            "b) Perfect octahedral cleavage",
            "c) Perfect basal cleavage",
            "d) Prismatic cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most important members of the Mica group crystallize in one system only: Monoclinic system. Some less important members crystallize in triclinic system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which mineral is flaky and black in appearance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biotite mica",
            "b) Muscovite mica",
            "c) Diamond",
            "d) Jaspar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crystals of the mica group show prism angles of 60° and 120°. Because of the atomic constitution, micas show excellent basal cleavage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "What is the other name of muscovite mica?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black mica",
            "b) Potash mica",
            "c) Vitreous mica",
            "d) Glossy mica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Biotite mica is flaky and black in appearance and appears in the form of thin sheets. They are usually translucent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "What is the diaphaneity of muscovite mica?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opaque",
            "b) Transparent",
            "c) Translucent",
            "d) Any form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The other name of muscovite mica is potash mica and biotite mica is also called as black mica due its appearance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "What is the streak given by muscovite mica?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White",
            "b) Black",
            "c) Yellow",
            "d) Colourless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Muscovite mica usually occurs in the form of thin colourless sheets, as a mass may appear pale yellow and is transparent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about mica.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They have high hardness",
            "b) They have low hardness",
            "c) They are usually transparent to translucent",
            "d) They are used as good electrical insulators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The colour of muscovite mica is usually colourless to pale yellow but gives no streak. "
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "What is the distinguishing property between biotite mica and muscovite mica?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streak",
            "b) Lustre",
            "c) Colour",
            "d) Hardness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The micas have a low hardness of about 2.5 to 3. Hence the first statement is wrong. The rest of the statements about mica hold good. "
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "What is the chemical composition of Quartz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SiO4",
            "b) Si2O3",
            "c) SiO2",
            "d) Al2O3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The chemical composition of the quartz minerals is SiO2. In other words, silicon dioxide is the basic chemical composition of the quartz minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which quartz mineral shows blue colour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rose quartz",
            "b) Blue quartz",
            "c) Smoky quartz",
            "d) Rock crystal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blue quartz shows a distinct blue colour compared to the other quartz minerals."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Rock crystal belongs to which mineral group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz group",
            "b) Feldspar group",
            "c) Carbonate group",
            "d) Ferro-magnesium group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basic chemical composition of the rock crystal is almost the same as other quartz minerals and also rock crystal is an important mineral of the quartz group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Pick the quartz mineral which is translucent among the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rose quartz",
            "b) Agate",
            "c) Amethyst quartz",
            "d) Milky quartz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amethyst quartz is usually translucent, i.e., it allows light partially to pass through it. Rest of the minerals are opaque. "
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The streak given by the quartz group is __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) White",
            "b) Colourless",
            "c) Blue",
            "d) Pale yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the main trait of the quartz group is that the minerals do not give any streak though are present in many colours in appearance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Pick the quartz which is colourless among the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rose quartz",
            "b) Smoky quartz",
            "c) Milky quartz",
            "d) Rock crystal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the minerals given above only rock crystal is colourless. The rest are coloured or either white in colour. "
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "What is the hardness of the quartz minerals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hardness is almost the same for all the quartz minerals and is about 7. This is one of the advantages of the quartz as they have high hardness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "What is the colour of rose quartz attributed to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron",
            "b) Titanium",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rose quartz is a special type of quartz and is known for its distinct rose red colour. The colour is attributed to presence of titanium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The mineral not belonging to the quartz group is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amethyst",
            "b) Agate",
            "c) Jasper",
            "d) Calcite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Amethyst quartz, agate and jasper belong to the quartz group, whereas, calcite belongs to the carbonate group whose chemical composition is completely different compared to the quartz group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "What is the cleavage shown by quartz minerals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basal",
            "b) Prismatic",
            "c) Rhombohedral",
            "d) No cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agate is also found in banded form and is known as banded agate. Agate is known to have massive structure which is also the same for banded agate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Quartz is found in which type of rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) Igneous, sedimentary and metamorphic rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cleavage is generally absent in the quartz minerals which is one of the defining characteristic of the quartz group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Carbonate minerals are found usually in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rocks",
            "b) Sedimentary rocks",
            "c) Sedimentary and metamorphic rocks",
            "d) Metamorphic and igneous rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The carbonate minerals are generally and most widely found in the sedimentary and metamorphic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Name the carbonate mineral which is found in ultrabasic igneous rocks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dolomite",
            "b) Calcite",
            "c) Magnesite",
            "d) Jasper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnesite is found in the ultrabasic igneous rocks which are not common among the other minerals and also among the other groups. "
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What is the structure or form of dolomite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhombohedral",
            "b) Columnar",
            "c) Tabular",
            "d) Flaky"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dolomite mineral is usually found in rhombohedral structure. In most cases, it is not found in any other form or structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "What is the colour of the magnesite when pure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow",
            "b) Bone white",
            "c) Blue",
            "d) Black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnesite mineral is found is colours like white, shades of grey and also sometimes brown. But when it is in the pure form, it is found in bone white colour. "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "What is the colour and diaphaneity of a calcite mineral respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow and opaque",
            "b) Blue and transparent",
            "c) White and transparent",
            "d) Grey and translucent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The calcite mineral is white in colour and its diaphaneity is transparent. The chemical composition of calcite is calcium carbonate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "What is the streak given by calcite minerals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colourless",
            "b) White",
            "c) Black",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The hardness of the carbonate minerals usually varies between 2.5 and 3. Hence they are said to have low hardness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Dolomite is formed by the action of magnesian rich sea water on which deposit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limestone",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Granite",
            "d) Basalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike the quartz minerals, the carbonate minerals give white streak which is an important distinguishing property of the minerals from other groups. "
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which carbonate mineral has this chemical composition- CaCO3 Mg(CO3)2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnesite",
            "b) Calcite",
            "c) Dolomite",
            "d) Jasper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  As a rock constituent, dolomite is believed to have been formed by the action of magnesian rich sea water on original limestone deposit. This process is called in petrology dolomitization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which lustre cannot occur to the calcite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adamantine",
            "b) Waxy",
            "c) Vitreous",
            "d) Silky"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dolomite has the chemical composition CaCO3 Mg(CO3)2. Whereas calcite doesn’t have Mg in its composition and magnesite lacks Ca in its composition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "How many sets of cleavage is shown by calcite minerals usually?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Calcite minerals show few lustres, vitreous, waxy, silky but they do not show adamantine lustre which is exclusively shown by diamond. "
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Which mineral is used as refractory material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcite",
            "b) Rock crystal",
            "c) Talc",
            "d) Magnesite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The calcite minerals are known to show three sets of cleavage which is pretty distinctive compared to other mineral groups. "
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "What is the chemical composition of Baryte?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BaSO4",
            "b) CaSO4",
            "c) BaCO3",
            "d) CaCO3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Baryte is found in massive and crystalline structures or forms and their basic chemical composition is barium sulphate (BaSO4). "
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "What is the use of corundum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Used as an abrasive",
            "b) Used as precious gemstones",
            "c) Used as Construction materials",
            "d) Used as abrasive and precious gemstones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corundum is used as both abrasive and also as precious gemstones. The former is due its high hardness of about 9 and the latter is due its appearance, and the names of some common semi-precious gemstones are ruby, emerald, sapphire etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "The semi-precious gemstone not belonging to corundum is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ruby",
            "b) Sapphire",
            "c) Diamond",
            "d) Oriental emerald"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some common forms of corundum used as precious or semi-precious gemstones are ruby, sapphire, oriental emerald and oriental topaz. Diamond is a completely different mineral and is not considered to be a form of corundum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Pick the correct statement about talc.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has very high hardness",
            "b) It is not used in the manufacture of talcum powders",
            "c) It is has lowest hardness",
            "d) It is found in igneous rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Talc mineral which is basically made of magnesium has the lowest hardness among the minerals which is equal to 1. "
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The ferro-magnesium mineral which occurs in ultra-basic igneous rocks is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnesite",
            "b) Olivine",
            "c) Baryte",
            "d) Corundum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Olivine is a type of ferro-magnesium mineral which is found in the ultra-basic igneous rocks. Magnesite is also found in the ultra-basic igneous rocks but do not belong to the ferro-magnesium group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "What is the diaphaneity of pure gypsum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opaque",
            "b) Transparent",
            "c) Translucent",
            "d) Opaque or transparent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gypsum is found usually in translucent and sometimes in opaque forms. In its pure form it is found in translucent form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about talc.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a very soft mineral",
            "b) It is used in talcum powders",
            "c) It is usually white or green in colour",
            "d) It is also used as precious gemstones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Talc has hardness number of about 1, used in talcum powders and is usually found in white or green colour. But it is not considered as a precious gemstone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Augite mainly consists of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fe",
            "b) Fe and Mn",
            "c) Fe and Ca",
            "d) Fe and Mg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Augite is a ferro-magnesium mineral and hence its basic and main composition is Fe and Mg. It is usually found in black colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "What is the form or structure of asbestose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Massive",
            "b) Flaky",
            "c) Tabular",
            "d) Globular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Asbestose is always found in the flaky or sometimes rarely in columnar form. Else it is not found in any other form or structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "What is the colour and streak of olivine respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White and green",
            "b) Olive green and white",
            "c) Yellow and green",
            "d) Green and no streak"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The olivine mineral is found in olive green colour and hence its name. The streak given by olivine is white. "
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What is the streak given by garnet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White",
            "b) Black",
            "c) Grey",
            "d) No colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Garnet is one of the very few ferro-magnetic minerals which do not give any streak. They are usually dark grey in colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "What is the form or structure of corundum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tabular, flaky",
            "b) Schistose, columnar",
            "c) Hexagonal, columnar",
            "d) Globular, tabular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The corundum is always found in the hexagonal, columnar crystals. The columnar crystals are of appreciable size of about 8 to 10 mm and are not uncommon. "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "The branch of geology which deals with various aspects of rocks is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Petrology",
            "b) Mineralogy",
            "c) Lithology",
            "d) Rockology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The branch of geology dealing with various aspects of rocks such as their formation, classification and occurrence is called petrology. "
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "What are the two conditions believed to be required for the formation of igneous rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low temperature and molten state",
            "b) Molten state and very high temperature",
            "c) Molten state and moderate temperature",
            "d) Crystallized state and moderate temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A very high temperature and a molten state are, two very important conditions for the original material from which the igneous rocks are believed to have been formed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "What is the state of lava or magma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid always",
            "b) Solid",
            "c) Gaseous",
            "d) Mixture of liquid, crystals and gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magma or lava from which igneous rocks are formed may not be entirely a pure melt: it may have a crystalline or solid fraction and also a gaseous fraction thoroughly mixed with it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Where are the volcanic rocks formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Under the surface of earth",
            "b) On the surface of earth",
            "c) Inside the core",
            "d) Between mantle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Volcanic rocks are the igneous rocks formed on the surface of the Earth by cooling and crystallization of lava erupted from volcanoes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is the grain size of volcanic rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very coarse",
            "b) Coarse",
            "c) Intermediate",
            "d) Very fine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the lava cools down at a very fast rate (compared to magma), the grain size of the crystals formed in the volcanic rocks is very fine, often microscope. "
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "The plutonic rocks are formed at depths below the earth’s surface ranging",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 100 km",
            "b) 100 to 200 km",
            "c) 7 to 10 km",
            "d) 1 to 5 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Igneous rocks are formed both from magma and lava. It may be mentioned that magma is actually a hypothetical melt. It has not been possible to see it at its place of occurrence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "The rock is coarse grained in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic rocks",
            "b) Plutonic rocks",
            "c) Hypabyssal rocks always",
            "d) Not found in igneous rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plutonic rocks are the igneous rocks formed at considerable depths, generally between 7-10 km below the surface of the earth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Pick the plutonic igneous rock.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Granite porphyry",
            "c) Syenite porphyry",
            "d) Marble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of a very slow rate of cooling at the depths, the rocks resulting from magma are coarse grained. These rocks get exposed on the surface of the earth as a consequence of erosion of the overlying strata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The rocks which exhibit mixed characteristics of volcanic and plutonic rocks are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermediate rocks",
            "b) Mixed rocks",
            "c) Hypabyssal rocks",
            "d) Secondary rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Granites, Syenites and Gabbros are a few examples of Plutonic rocks. They occur in good abundance in both the Peninsular and extra-Peninsular India. "
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Porphyries are examples of which type of rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic",
            "b) Plutonic",
            "c) Hypabyssal",
            "d) Sedimentary rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hypabyssal rocks are the igneous rocks which are formed at intermediate depths, generally up to 2 km below the surface of the earth and exhibit mixed characteristics of volcanic and plutonic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Which is the most dominant constituent of igneous rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Al2O3",
            "b) SiO2",
            "c) CaCO3",
            "d) CaO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Porphyries of various composition are examples of hypabyssal rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "The mineral most abundantly present in the igneous rocks is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micas",
            "b) Titanium",
            "c) Iron",
            "d) Felspars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In terms of chemical composition, Silica is the dominant constituent of the igneous rocks. Second comes the Alumina. "
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "What is the approximate percentage of silica present in the igneous rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 26%",
            "c) 59%",
            "d) 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In terms of the mineralogical composition, Felspars are the most common minerals of igneous rocks. Even amphiboles, pyroxenes and quartz are present to some extent. Others are present only in subordinate amounts."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Pick the option which does not determine the texture of igneous rocks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour",
            "b) Size",
            "c) Shape",
            "d) Arrangement of the constituents within the body of the rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term texture is defined as the mutual relationship of different mineralogical constituents in a rock. It is determined by the size, shape and arrangement of these constituents within the body of the rock."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor explaining texture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind conditions",
            "b) Degree of crystallization",
            "c) Granularity",
            "d) Fabric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The following three factors will primarily define the type of texture in a given igneous rock: Degree of crystallization, Granularity and Fabric. "
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "The degree of crystallization where the constituents are very fine or glassy are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Holocrystalline",
            "b) Holohyalline",
            "c) Homohyalline",
            "d) Homocrystalline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Holohyaline is the term used, when, all the constituents are very fine in size and glassy or non-crystalline in nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "What is the term used when constituents are crystallized completely?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Holocrystalline",
            "b) Holohyalline",
            "c) Homohyalline",
            "d) Homocrystalline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Holocrystalline is the term used when all the constituent minerals are distinctly crystallized."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the range of grain size for coarse grained igneous rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Above 2 mm",
            "b) Below 2 mm",
            "c) Above 5 mm",
            "d) Below 5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the average grain size is above 5 mm; the constituent minerals are then easily identified with naked eye. These rocks are termed as coarse-grained rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Grain size 5mm to 1mm is termed as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coarse grained",
            "b) Intermediate grained",
            "c) Fine grained",
            "d) Medium grained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the average grain size lies between 5 mm to 1 mm it is termed as medium grained. The use of magnifying lens often becomes necessary for identifying all the constituent mineral components. "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The grain size involving use of microscope is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coarse grain",
            "b) Medium grain",
            "c) Fine grain",
            "d) Very coarse grain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the average grain size is less than 1 mm it is termed as fine grain. In such rocks, identification of the constituent mineral grains is possible only with the help of microscope for which very thin rock sections have to be prepared. "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "What is the term given when some granules are exceptionally large and few are small?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixed granular",
            "b) Equigranular",
            "c) Inequigranular",
            "d) Unequigranular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The texture is termed as equigranular when all the component minerals are of approximately equal dimensions and as inequigranular when some minerals in the rock are exceptionally larger or smaller than the other."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about granitic texture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The constituents are coarse grained",
            "b) The constituents are medium grained",
            "c) The crystals show euhedral to subhedral outlines",
            "d) The rock is microgranular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the granitic texture, the constituents are either all coarse grained or all medium grained and the crystals show euhedral to subhedral outlines. "
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "The number of equigranular textures are ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All those textures in which majority of constituent crystals of rock are broadly equal in size are described as equigranular textures. There are 3 types- Granitic, Felsitic and Orthophyric. "
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "The texture which the characteristics in between granitic and felsitic are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary",
            "b) Intermediate",
            "c) Orthophyric",
            "d) Transitional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Orthophyric texture is another type of equigranular texture, which is in between the granitic and felsitic textures. The individual grains are fine in size but not microgranular. "
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "What is the texture called when large-sized crystals are embedded in fine grained matrix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granitic texture",
            "b) Poiklitic texture",
            "c) Porphyritic texture",
            "d) Directive texture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The porphyritic texture is characterized by the presence of a few conspicuously large sized crystals (the phenocrysts) which are embedded in a fine-grained ground mass or matrix. "
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "The cause which is not influencing the porphyritic texture is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference in molecular concentration",
            "b) Change in physic-chemical conditions",
            "c) Relative insolubility",
            "d) Change in temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Porphyritic texture may be caused by any one or more of the following factors: Difference in molecular concentration, change in physic-chemical conditions and relative insolubility.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "What is the absolute reverse of porphyritic texture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poiklitic",
            "b) Granitic",
            "c) Felsitic",
            "d) Ophitic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Poikilitic texture is characterized with the presence of fine-grained crystals within the body of large sized crystals. In other words, it is just the reverse of the porphyritic textures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "What is the term when augite has inclusions of plagioclase felspar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poiklitic",
            "b) Granitic",
            "c) Felsitic",
            "d) Ophitic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the host mineral is identified as augite and the inclusions are of plagioclase felspars, the poiklitic texture is further distinguished as ophitic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which texture indicates the flow of magma during its formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equigranular",
            "b) Directive",
            "c) Intergrowth",
            "d) Intergranular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The development of ophitic texture in rocks is yet incompletely understood. It may be due to operation of factors for porphyritic texture but in a different manner. "
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Example of directive texture is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tracheod",
            "b) Granitic",
            "c) Trachytic",
            "d) Porphyritic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Those textures that indicate the result of the flow of magma during the formation of rocks are known as directive textures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The texture which involves polygonal or trigonal spaces in rocks is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directive texture",
            "b) Intergrowth texture",
            "c) Interstitial texture",
            "d) Intergranular texture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trachytic and Trachytoid textures are common examples of directive textures. The former is characteristic of certain felspar lavas and is recognised by a parallel arrangement of felspar; the latter is found in some syenites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "What is it called when two or more minerals crystallize simultaneously in a limited space?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directive texture",
            "b) Intergrowth texture",
            "c) Interstitial texture",
            "d) Intergranular texture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In certain igneous rocks crystals formed at earlier stages may get so arranged that polygonal or trigonal spaces are left in between them. These spaces get filled subsequently during the process of rock formation by crystalline or glassy masses of other minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Form of igneous rock where magma is injected and cooled along planes of host rocks is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discordant bodies",
            "b) Concordant bodies",
            "c) Parallel bodies",
            "d) Synchronous bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All those intrusions in which the magma has been injected and cooled along or parallel to the structural planes of the host rocks are called concordant bodies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Pick the type of concordant body among the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Batholith",
            "b) Extrusion",
            "c) Dykes",
            "d) Phacolith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The various types of concordant bodies are sills, phacoliths, laccoliths and lopoliths."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The type of concordant body whose thickness is much smaller than its length and width is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sill",
            "b) Phacolith",
            "c) Dyke",
            "d) Laccolith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is typical of sills that their thickness is much small than their width and length. Moreover, this body commonly thins out or tapers along its outer margins. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "The upper and lower margins of sills are relatively ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coarser grain size",
            "b) Medium grain size",
            "c) Finer grain size",
            "d) Can be of any size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The upper and lower margins of sills commonly show a comparatively finer grain size than their interior portions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Most common rocks composing the sills are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Marbles",
            "b) Shales",
            "c) Gabbros",
            "d) Granites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In length, sills may vary from a few centimeters to hundreds of meters. Minor and local projections from big sills may rise above into the overlying strata. "
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "The small sized intrusives that occupy bends in the folds are called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sills",
            "b) Lopolith",
            "c) Laccolith",
            "d) Phacolith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most common rocks composing the sills are intermediate and basic igneous rocks like syenites and gabbros. They may show aphinitic and porphyritic textures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The concordant bodies associated with structural basins are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sills",
            "b) Lopolith",
            "c) Laccolith",
            "d) Phacolith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phacoliths are concordant, small sized intrusions that occupy positions in the troughs and crests of bends called folds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "The shape arch or dome is shown by which type of concordant body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sills",
            "b) Lopolith",
            "c) Laccolith",
            "d) Phacolith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Those igneous intrusions, which are associated with structural basins, that are sedimentary beds inclined towards a common centre, are termed as lopoliths. They may form huge bodies of consolidated magma. "
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "What is the type of lava which leads to the formation of laccolith?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscous",
            "b) Non-viscous",
            "c) Partially crystallized",
            "d) Gaseous lava"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Laccoliths are concordant intrusions due to which the invaded strata have been arched up or deformed into a dome. The igneous mass itself has a flat or concave base and a dome-shaped top. "
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "What is the type of laccolith in which fracture is formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dyke",
            "b) Batholith",
            "c) Bysmalith",
            "d) Volcanic neck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Laccoliths are formed when the magma being injected is considerably viscous so that it is unable to flow and spread for greater distances. Instead, it gets collected in the form of a heap about the orifice of an eruption. "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "The intrusive bodies in which injection of lava occurs without any influence of dip and strike is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concordant bodies",
            "b) Discordant bodies",
            "c) Non-cordant bodies",
            "d) Uncomformities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All those intrusive bodies that have been injected into the strata without being influenced by their structural disposition (dip and strike) and thus traverse across or oblique to the bedding planes etc. are grouped as discordant bodies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "The example not belonging to discordant body is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dykes",
            "b) Volcanic necks",
            "c) Bysmaliths",
            "d) Batholiths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bysmalith is a type of laccolith which is again a type of concordant body and not a discordant body. The dykes, volcanic necks and batholiths are usually the widely studied types of discordant bodies."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which discordant body is columnar or column shaped?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dykes",
            "b) Volcanic necks",
            "c) Bysmaliths",
            "d) Batholiths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dykes may be defined as columnar bodies of igneous rocks that cut across the bedding plane or uncoformities or cleavage planes and similar structures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Texture shown by dykes is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equigranular",
            "b) Directive",
            "c) Intergrowth",
            "d) All types of textures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In composition, dykes are generally made up of hypabyssal rocks like dolerites, porphyrites and lamprophyres, showing all textures between glassy and phaneritic types. "
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "When the vents of quiet volcanoes become sealed with intrusions it leads to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dyke",
            "b) Batholith",
            "c) Extrusion",
            "d) Volcanic necks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dykes generally tend to occur in groups or sets. Thus, the term dyke-set is used for a couple of parallel and closely spaced dykes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "The bodies which show both concordant and discordant relations are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dykes",
            "b) Sills",
            "c) Batholiths",
            "d) Phacoliths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In some cases, vents of quiet volcanoes have become sealed with the intrusions. Such congealed intrusions are termed volcanic necks or volcanic plugs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "What should be the area and depth respectively, for an igneous body to be called a batholith?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 square km and depth not traceable",
            "b) 10 square km and depth up to 100km",
            "c) Not traceable and depth 10 km",
            "d) 50 km and depth 10 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Batholiths are huge bodies of igneous masses that show both concordant and discordant relations with the country rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "What is the term used for a batholith when surface area is less than 100 km?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dykes",
            "b) Stock",
            "c) Sock",
            "d) Sillets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dimensions of batholiths vary considerably but it is generally agreed that to qualify as a batholith the igneous mass should be greater than 100 square kilometres in area and its depth should not be traceable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Majority of batholiths show which composition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Felsitic",
            "b) Granitic",
            "c) Ophitic",
            "d) Directive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the surface area of batholith-like igneous mass is less than 100 km, it is commonly termed as stock. When such a stock has a roughly circular outline, it is further distinguished as a boss. "
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about granitization.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a set of processes rather than a single step",
            "b) It involves already existing sedimentary and other rocks",
            "c) It involves magmatic stage",
            "d) It doesn’t actually require magmatic stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In composition, batholiths may be made of any type of igneous rock. They also exhibit many types of textures and structures. But as a matter of observation, majority of batholiths shows predominantly granitic composition, texture and structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Granite belongs to which mode of occurrence of igneous rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic rocks",
            "b) Plutonic",
            "c) Hypabyssal",
            "d) Volcanic and hypabyssal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Granites may be defined as plutonic light coloured igneous rocks. These are among the most common igneous rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "The two most common mineral found in granites are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diamond and mica",
            "b) Mica and orthoclase",
            "c) Quartz and felspar",
            "d) Felspar and corundum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two most common and essential mineral constituents of granite are: Quartz and Felspar. "
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which is the most important accessory mineral in granite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Felspar",
            "b) Quartz",
            "c) Topaz",
            "d) Mica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the accessory minerals in granites, micas deserve the first mention. Both varieties are present in small proportions in most granites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The texture of granite is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equigranular",
            "b) Directive",
            "c) Inequigranular",
            "d) Intergrowth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Granites are generally coarse to medium grained, holocrystalline and equigranular rocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Syenites belong to which mode of occurrence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic rocks",
            "b) Plutonic",
            "c) Hypabyssal",
            "d) Concordant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Syenites are defined as igneous, plutonic, even-grained rocks in which alkali-felspars are the chief constituent minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "What is the usual colour of gabbro?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White",
            "b) Yellow",
            "c) Black",
            "d) Blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Syenites show textures broadly similar to those of granites, that is, they are coarse to medium-grained, holocrystalline in nature and exhibiting graphic, inter-growth or porphyiritic relationship among its constituents. "
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "What is the mode of formation of gabbro?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic",
            "b) Plutonic",
            "c) Hypabyssal",
            "d) Dykes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gabbros are usually found in black colour. Sometimes they are also found in other shades of dark grey and dark brown. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Pick the igneous rock whose mode of occurrence is volcanic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basalt",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Gabbro",
            "d) Syenite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gabbros are coarse-grained plutonic rocks of basic character. Plagioclase felspars of lime-soda composition are the chief constituents of gabbros. "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "What can be said about the grain size of pegmatite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine grained",
            "b) Medium grained",
            "c) Fine to medium grained",
            "d) Coarse grained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basalts are volcanic igneous rocks formed by rapid cooling from lava flows from volcanoes either over the surface or under water on oceanic floors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Pick the rock which is not volcanic in terms of mode of occurrence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Basalt",
            "c) Obsidian",
            "d) Pumice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pegmatites are exceptionally coarse-grained igneous rocks formed from hydrothermal solutions emanating from magmas that get cooled and crystallized in cavities and cracks around magmatic intrusions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "The igneous rock with glassy texture is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gabbro",
            "b) Pumice",
            "c) Obsidian",
            "d) Pegmatite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Granite is of plutonic occurrence whereas the rest, viz., Basalt, Obsidian. Pumice are volcanic in occurrence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "The igneous rock with very low specific gravity is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Pumice",
            "c) Gabbro",
            "d) Basalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Obsidian is of glassy texture and it is the distinct property of the igneous rock which makes it easier for its identification. "
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "The igneous rock with flow texture is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gabbro",
            "b) Pumice",
            "c) Rhyolite",
            "d) Basalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pumice has a low specific gravity whereas all the other igneous rocks have medium specific gravity. This property makes the igneous rock “pumice” very light. The main reason behind this is, pumice has many pores. "
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which rock is also called secondary rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) No class of rock is termed so"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks are also called secondary rocks. This group includes a wide variety of rocks formed by accumulation, compaction and consolidation of sediments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which is the rock present in the majority on the surface of earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rock",
            "b) Sedimentary rock",
            "c) Metamorphic rock",
            "d) No class of rock in particular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks are known to cover as much as 75 percent of the surface of the earth the rest being covered by the igneous rocks and the metamorphic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What are the mechanically formed sedimentary rocks also called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clastic rocks",
            "b) Non-clastic rocks",
            "c) Elite rocks",
            "d) Mech rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks are broadly grouped into three classes on the basis of their mode of formation: Mechanically formed or Clastic rocks: Organically formed rocks and chemically rocks which are called as Non-clastic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Detrital rocks refer to which type of sedimentary rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanically formed",
            "b) Organically formed",
            "c) Chemically formed",
            "d) Residual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the formation of the sedimentary rocks by a mechanical method, original hard and coherent rock bodies are gradually broken down into smaller fragments. This disintegrated, loosened material is called detritus. Hence, clastic rocks are often also called as detrital rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "The important phenomenon that happens during deposition is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Settling",
            "b) Erosion",
            "c) Sorting",
            "d) Blowing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most important phenomenon that happens to the sediments during their transport and deposition is sorting or grading according to their size, shape and density. "
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Deposition takes place in which conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ordinary pressure and temperature",
            "b) High temperature and low pressure",
            "c) High pressure and low temperature",
            "d) High pressure and high temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sorting or grading occurs during the deposition stage of the formation of sedimentary rocks and the deposition happens in layers in most cases. Deposition generally takes place under ordinary pressure and temperature conditions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The process not associated with diagenesis is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sediments get gradually converted to cohesive material",
            "b) Sediments get gradually converted to hard material",
            "c) Decaying occurs basically",
            "d) Might occur due to pressure or cementing material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of transformation of loose sediments deposited in the settlement basins to solid cohesive rock masses either under pressure or because of cementation is collectively known as diagenesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The process which involves pressure exerted by the load is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loading",
            "b) Welding",
            "c) Cementation",
            "d) Unloading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Welding is the process of compaction of the sediments accumulated in lower layers of a basin due to the pressure exerted by the load of the overlying sediments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The process other than welding which is studied under diagenesis is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Co-welding",
            "b) Cementation",
            "c) Pressurising",
            "d) Unloading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diagenesis is achieved by two methods. They are welding and cementation. Cementation is the process by which loose grains or sediments in a settlement basin get held together by a binding material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Rock salt may be formed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erosion",
            "b) Winds",
            "c) Continued evaporation",
            "d) Continued precipitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Limestone may be formed by precipitation from carbonated water due to loss of carbon dioxide. Rock salt may be formed from sodium-chloride rich seawater merely by the process of continued evaporation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Example of chemically formed sedimentary rocks is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gypsum",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Shale",
            "d) Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemically formed rocks are of two types: precipitates and evaporites. Examples are limestones, rock salt, gypsum and anhydrite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Pick the organically formed sedimentary rock.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Breccia",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Limestones are the best examples of organically formed sedimentary rocks. Generally, the evidence of the source material gets obliterated from these rocks with the passage of time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "How is the degree of packing in welding related to load of overlying sediments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly related",
            "b) Inversely related",
            "c) Not related at all",
            "d) Totally independent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Welding initially involves squeezing out of all or most of the water from in between the sediments, thus bringing them closer and closer and hence resulting in compaction. In fact the degree of packing of sediments in a sedimentary rock is directly proportional to the load of the overlying sediments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "The layered arrangement in sedimentary rocks is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mud cracks",
            "b) Stratification",
            "c) Rain prints",
            "d) Ripple marks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By stratification is understood a layered arrangement in sedimentary rock. This may be developed very prominently and can be seen from a distance of miles or in other cases may have to be ascertained after close examination of the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "The structure most prevalent to clastic rocks is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nodular structure",
            "b) Geode structure",
            "c) Concretionary structure",
            "d) Lamination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most prevalent structures of a clastic group of sedimentary rocks are the ones belonging to mechanical structure which are, stratification, lamination, cross beddings, rain prints etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Lamination is structure formed in which type of sedimentary rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine grained",
            "b) Medium grained",
            "c) Coarse grained",
            "d) Nothing in particular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lamination is a characteristic structure of fine-grained sedimentary rocks like clays and shales."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Each layer of a laminated structure of sedimentary rock is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strata",
            "b) Leaf",
            "c) Lamina",
            "d) Layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The individual layers of the laminated structure are called lamiae and are distinguished commonly on the basis of difference in colour. "
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a type of false bedding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Columnar",
            "b) Tabular",
            "c) Lenticular",
            "d) Wedge shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The common types of false bedding are, tabular, lenticular, wedge shaped. Columnar is not a type of false bedding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "The type of false bedding where top and bottom surfaces are parallel is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Columnar",
            "b) Tabular",
            "c) Lenticular",
            "d) Wedge shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tabular false bedding is a type of cross bedding in which the top and bottom surfaces of the deposit are essentially parallel, indicating its deposition in the same main channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Type of false bedding where the individual layers exist in well-defined sets of parallel layers is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Columnar",
            "b) Tabular",
            "c) Lenticular",
            "d) Wedge shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the case of wedge shaped cross bedding, the cross-bedding structure is highly complex: the individual layers exist in well-defined sets of parallel layers but these sets bear angular relationship to each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Type of bedding where sorting and arrangement has occurred based on grain size is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross bedding",
            "b) Lamination",
            "c) Graded bedding",
            "d) Mud cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In some stratified rocks the component sediments in each layer appear to be characteristically sorted and arranged according to their grain size, the coarsest being placed at the bottom and the finest at the top. "
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Graded bedding occurs due to which phenomenon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind settling",
            "b) Sunlight",
            "c) Gravitational settling",
            "d) Loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Normally, perfectly graded beds are the result of sedimentation in bodies of standing water where factor of gravitative settling from a mixed load is predominant process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Mud cracks are common in which type of sedimentary rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine grained",
            "b) Medium grained",
            "c) Coarse grained",
            "d) Not particular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mud cracks are common structural features of many fine-grained sedimentary rocks. The structure consists of polygonal or irregular cracks spread along the surface of an exposed sedimentary layer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "The bedding involving crater shaped depressions is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mud cracks",
            "b) Rain prints",
            "c) Ripple marks",
            "d) Sun cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rain prints are irregular, small crater-shaped depressions seen on fine-grained dried sediments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not provide evidence of shallow water environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamination",
            "b) Rain prints",
            "c) Ripple marks",
            "d) Mud cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mud cracks, rain prints and ripple marks when encountered in sedimentary formations are taken as confirmatory evidence of the formation having been deposited in a shallow water environment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Which structure resembles fish eggs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pisolitic",
            "b) Felsitic",
            "c) Oolitic",
            "d) Granitic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Oolitic structure is the structure where the concretions are of the size of fish eggs; the rock appears as an assemblage of fish eggs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Peanut structure is shown by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Limestone",
            "c) Shale",
            "d) Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pisolitic structure is another type of concretionary structure where the individual size of a concretion is like that of a peanut. Limestones and bauxite show both these structures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "The process not contributing to clastic rocks is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weathering",
            "b) Oxidation",
            "c) Erosion",
            "d) Deposition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mechanically formed sedimentary rocks undergo processes like- weathering, erosion, transport, deposition and diagenesis. Oxidation is considered under to be a non-clastic cause. "
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "What is the size required for a particle to be called gravel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 1 mm",
            "b) Lesser 1 mm",
            "c) Greater than 2 mm",
            "d) Lesser than 1 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All sediments and clastic fragments of rocks above the size of 2 mm irrespective of their composition and shape are broadly termed as gravels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "What is not true about silts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are coarser than sand",
            "b) They are finer than sand",
            "c) They are further divided into fine, medium and fine silts",
            "d) They are major constituents of shale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silts are very fine-sized particles of varying composition lying in the range 1/16 mm and 1/256 mm. they are further divided into three categories, fine, medium and coarse. The silts are the major constituents of rocks known as shales. "
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "What is the average grain size of rudaceous rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 1 mm",
            "b) Lesser 1 mm",
            "c) Greater than 2 mm",
            "d) Lesser than 1 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rudites or rudaceous rocks include all coarse-grained rocks of heterogeneous composition. The average grain size of the constituents in rudites is greater than 2 mm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Give an example for rudaceous rock.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breccia",
            "b) Shale",
            "c) Limestone",
            "d) Sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In rudaceous rocks gravels are held together in the form of a rock by natural cementing material. Breccias and conglomerates are important examples of rudites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Rudites are also called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arenites",
            "b) Psamites",
            "c) Lutites",
            "d) Psephites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rudites or rudaceous rocks are also called as psephites. Rudites are made up of boulders, cobbles and pebbles collectively known as gravels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "The arenaceous rocks have the grain size equal to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Silt",
            "d) Clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The arenites are also called as arenaceous rocks. These are made up of sediments of sand grade (2mm-1/16 mm). "
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "An example for arenite would be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breccia",
            "b) Shale",
            "c) Limestone",
            "d) Sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a particular rock, the sand grains of a particular size range may be predominating giving rise to coarse, medium and fine arenites. Sandstones, greywackes and arkoses are common types of arenites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of the following are finest grain sized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudaceous rocks",
            "b) Arenaceous rocks",
            "c) Argillaceous rocks",
            "d) Psephites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Argillaceous rocks are also called as lutites. Lutites may be defined as sedimentary rocks of the finest grain-size. They are made up of silt and clay grades. "
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Non-detrital rocks refer to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clastic rock",
            "b) Non-clastic rock",
            "c) Residual rock",
            "d) None of the types"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many times a clastic rock may be made of sediments of more than one grade. It is the dominant grade that is taken into consideration while classifying the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Pick the type of sedimentary not belonging to chemically formed rocks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxide rocks",
            "b) Carbonaceous rocks",
            "c) Ferruginous deposits",
            "d) Siliceous deposits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:The non-clastic rocks are also called non-detrital rocks. They are generally homogeneous in character, fine-grained in particle size and varying in chemical composition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Breccia is formed by which process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Chemical",
            "c) Organic",
            "d) Residual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Breccia is a mechanically formed sedimentary rock classed as rudite. It consists of angular fragments of heterogeneous composition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The type of Breccia which is also called crush-breccia is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basal Breccia",
            "b) Faulted Breccia",
            "c) Agglomeratic Breccia",
            "d) Rudite Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Faults Breccia is also called crush-breccia. Such rocks are so named because they are made up of angular fragments that have been produced during the process of faulting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The type of Breccia formed by sea water is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basal Breccia",
            "b) Faulted Breccia",
            "c) Agglomeratic Breccia",
            "d) Rudite Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This rock is formed by the sea waters advancing over a coastal region covered with fragments of chert and other similar rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Conglomerates belong to which group of sedimentary rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudaceous rocks",
            "b) Argillaceous rocks",
            "c) Arenaceous rocks",
            "d) Any group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conglomerates are sedimentary rocks of clastic nature and also belong to rudaceous group. "
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Conglomerates consist of which shaped fragments mostly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angular",
            "b) Sub-angular",
            "c) Rounded",
            "d) Edged"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conglomerates consist mostly of rounded fragments of various sizes but generally above 2 mm, cemented together in clayey or ferruginous or mixed matrix. "
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a type of conglomerate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basal",
            "b) Glacial",
            "c) Volcanic",
            "d) Faulted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sometimes the conglomerates are distinguished on the basis of source of the gravels, as: Basal, glacial and volcanic conglomerates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "The sedimentary rock which is arenaceous in nature is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conglomerate",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Breccia",
            "d) Shale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sandstones are mechanically formed sedimentary rocks of arenaceous group. These are mostly composed of sand grade particles that have been compacted and consolidated together in the form of beds in basins sedimentation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which is the dominant mineral in sandstone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mica",
            "b) Diamond",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Felspar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quartz is the most common mineral making the sandstones. In fact some varieties of sandstones are made entirely of quartz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "The texture of sandstone is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine-medium",
            "b) Medium-coarse",
            "c) Coarse",
            "d) Fine-coarse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sandstones are, in general, medium to fine-medium grained in texture. The component grains show a great variation in their size, shape and arrangement in different varieties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "The colour of sandstone not found commonly is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blue",
            "b) Red",
            "c) Brown",
            "d) White"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sandstones naturally occur in a variety of colours: red, brown, grey and white being the most common colours. The colour of sandstone depends on its composition, especially the nature of the cementing material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "The type of sandstone where cementing material is clay is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Siliceous sandstone",
            "b) Calcareous sandstone",
            "c) Argillaceous sandstone",
            "d) Ferruginous sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Argillaceous sandstones are among the soft varieties of sandstone because the cementing material is clay that has not much inherent strength. "
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "The term quartzite is associated with which type of sandstone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Siliceous sandstone",
            "b) Calcareous sandstone",
            "c) Argillaceous sandstone",
            "d) Ferruginous sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When silica is the cementing material in the sandstones it is called siliceous sandstone. Sometimes the quality of the siliceous cement is so dense and uniform that a massive compact and homogeneous rock is formed. This is called quartzite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Red Fort in India is built using which sedimentary rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) White Sandstone",
            "c) Red sandstone",
            "d) Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sandstones are most commonly used as materials of construction: building stones, pavement stones, road stones and also as a source material for concrete. The Red Fort of India is made up of red sandstones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Shales are generally characterized with distinct ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleavage",
            "b) Fracture",
            "c) Specific gravity",
            "d) Parting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shale is a finely-grained sedimentary rock of argillaceous composition. Shales are generally characterized with a distinct fissility (parting) parallel to the bedding planes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "The tendency of a rock to split into flat, shell-like fragments parallel to bedding is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleavage",
            "b) Fracture",
            "c) Specific gravity",
            "d) Fissility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The exact mineralogical composition of shales is often difficult to ascertain because of the very fine size of the constituents. "
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which type of shale involves both clastic and non-clastic sources?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Residual shales",
            "b) Transported shales",
            "c) Hybrid shales",
            "d) Quartz shales"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shales are characterized with a distinct property of fissility, which may be defined as “the tendency of a rock to split into flat, shell-like fragments parallel to bedding”. The fissility of shales is partly primary and partly secondary in nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Name the type of shale involving decay and decomposition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Residual shales",
            "b) Transported shales",
            "c) Hybrid shales",
            "d) Quartz shales"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In hybrid shales, materials derived both from clastic sources and non-clastic sources especially those from organic sources make up the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which sedimentary rock is present in majority on earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Breccia",
            "d) Conglomerate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Residual shales are formed from decay and decomposition of pre-existing rocks followed by compaction and consolidation of the particles in adjoining basins without much mixing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a use of shale?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Used in manufacture of bricks and tiles",
            "b) Used as source of alumina",
            "c) Used as paraffin",
            "d) Used as precious gemstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Of all the sedimentary rocks occurring on the surface of the earth, shales are the most predominant forming 70-80 percent of this group. These rocks occur in massive formations and beds extending over several hundred kilometres in many cases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "The non-clastic sedimentary rock chiefly made of carbonate of calcium is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limestone",
            "b) Sandstone",
            "c) Shale",
            "d) Breccia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Limestones are the most common sedimentary rocks from the non-clastic group and are composed chiefly of carbonate of calcium with subordinate proportions of carbonate of magnesium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Distinct texture shown by limestone is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheeting",
            "b) Lamination",
            "c) Fossiliferous nature",
            "d) Mud cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In view of the diverse ways in which the limestones are formed, these rocks show a variety of textures. The most important texture feature of limestones is their fossiliferous nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which type of limestone is non-marine is origin among the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chalk",
            "b) Kankar",
            "c) Shelly-limestone",
            "d) Argillaceous limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Kankar is a common nodular or concretionary form of carbonate material formed by evaporation of subsoil water rich in calcium carbonate just near the soil surface. It is non-marine in origin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "The major use of limestone is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary source material for manufacture of Portland cement",
            "b) Used in metallurgical industries as flux",
            "c) Used as building stone",
            "d) Used as a source of magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Limestones and dolomites find important applications in many industries and engineering practice. Thus, limestone is a primary source material for manufacture of Portland cement and for a variety of limes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "What is a metamorphosed sedimentary rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) Limestone",
            "c) Coal",
            "d) Dolomite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coal may broadly be defined as metamorphosed sedimentary rocks of carbonaceous character in which the raw material has mostly been supplied by plants of various groups. "
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The grade of coal with very low calorific value is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peat",
            "b) Lignite",
            "c) Bituminous",
            "d) Anthracite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peat is the lowest grade coal that constitutes of only slightly altered vegetable matter. It may not be even considered as a coal. It has very low calorific value, high percentage of moisture and is rich in volatile matter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The other name for brown coal is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peat",
            "b) Lignite",
            "c) Bituminous",
            "d) Anthracite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lignite is also known as brown coal and forms the poorest grade of coal with calorific value ranging between 6.00-8300 B.th.U. "
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "What is the hardness of the lignite grade of coal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 5.5",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lignite is compact and massive in structure with an upper specific gravity of 1.5 and hardness of 2.5 on Mohs’ scale of hardness. Some varieties of lignite may still show to a good extent the traces of original vegetable structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "The highest grade of coal is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peat",
            "b) Lignite",
            "c) Bituminous",
            "d) Anthracite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anthracite is considered the highest grade coal with fixed carbon ranging between 92-98 percent. It has highest calorific value in coals and burns without any smoke, as the volume matter is negligible."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "A civil engineer has to deal with which rock in the majority of cases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous rocks",
            "b) Sedimentary rocks",
            "c) Metamorphic rocks",
            "d) Ultra-basic igneous rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks cover a great part of the crust of the earth; they make up more than 75 percent of the surface area of the land mass. It is with these types of rocks that an engineer has to deal with in majority of cases. It is therefore, essential for a civil engineer to know as much as is possible about the salient features of these rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "What is the term used to express the process responsible for all the changes that take place in an original rock under the influence of changes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hibernation",
            "b) Herbination",
            "c) Metamorphism",
            "d) Metagenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metamorphism is the term used to express the process responsible for all the changes that take place in an original rock under the influence of changes in the surrounding conditions of temperature, pressure and chemically active fluids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "The factor not affecting metamorphism is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind conditions",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Chemically active fluids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The factors affecting the metamorphism of the rocks are temperature, pressure and chemically fluids. Wind conditions do not affect the metamorphism in any way. "
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Factors are also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary aspects",
            "b) Agents of metamorphism",
            "c) Agents of changes",
            "d) Tertiary aspects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metamorphic changes in the rocks are primarily the result of three main factors that are also sometimes called agents of metamorphism: heat, pressure and chemically active fluids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "The temperature up to which minerals in rocks are stable is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100° C",
            "b) 50° C",
            "c) 500° C",
            "d) 200° C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rocks are made up of minerals that are normally stable at temperature below 200° C. However when the temperature around these rocks changes due to one reason or the other, the mineral composition of the rocks undergoes some changes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Any given rock at some depth below the surface is subjected to pressure from how many sources?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any given rock at some depth below the surface is subjected to pressure from two sources: first, load of the overlying burden and second, from crustal movements. "
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "What is the pressure exerted during the crustal movements called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect pressure",
            "b) Directed pressure",
            "c) Secondary pressure",
            "d) Primary pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pressure from orogenic activity is generally lateral or horizontal and is commonly termed as directed pressure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "What is the direction of pressure exertion in load metamorphism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical",
            "b) Horizontal",
            "c) Inclined",
            "d) Horizontal or inclined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The load of the overlying burden acts generally exerts pressure in a vertical direction and the process of change in the structure of the rock is often referred as load metamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Water in which form is considered as single most important agent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid",
            "b) Liquid",
            "c) Gaseous",
            "d) Solid and liquid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Presence or absence of chemically active fluids within the body of the rocks (the pore fluids) or around them plays very important role in the process of all types of metamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Which rocks show severe degree of metamorphism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Situated near the plate boundaries",
            "b) Situated inside the boundaries",
            "c) Situated at the centre of the plates",
            "d) Irrespective of the place, the degree is same everywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water in the form of steam is considered the single most important agent. The water may be present in the minerals as water of crystallization or simply as pore fluid or it may be supplied externally by magmatic bodies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "The type of metamorphism in which heat factor has played an important role is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic metamorphism",
            "b) Thermal metamorphism",
            "c) Thermodynamic metamorphism",
            "d) Barometric metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal metamorphism is a general term including a variety of metamorphic processes in which the heat factor has played an important role. "
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which type of metamorphism is common in rocks close to magmatic intrusions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact metamorphism",
            "b) Pyrometamorphism",
            "c) Plutonic metamorphism",
            "d) Dyke metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Contact metamorphism is a common type of thermal observed in rocks existing close to the magmatic intrusions, injections and lava flows. "
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Type of metamorphism where part of country rock may get entrapped within magmatic body is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact metamorphism",
            "b) Pyrometamorphism",
            "c) Plutonic metamorphism",
            "d) Dyke metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pyrometamorphism is a type of thermal metamorphism in which case a part of country rock may actually get entrapped within a magmatic body. The effects result due to intense localized heating. "
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Metamorphism involving both temperature and load is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact metamorphism",
            "b) Pyrometamorphism",
            "c) Plutonic metamorphism",
            "d) Dyke metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plutonic metamorphism is a process of metamorphism that takes place due to equally important role of imposed loads and very high temperatures that become natural at those great depths. "
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Which kind of metamorphism is also called dislocation metamorphism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic metamorphism",
            "b) Thermal metamorphism",
            "c) Thermodynamic metamorphism",
            "d) Barometric metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic metamorphism is also called clastic metamorphism, mechanical metamorphism or dislocation metamorphism and is brought about by conditions in which pressure factor plays a dominant role. "
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "In which metamorphism there is almost no or little new mineral is formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic metamorphism",
            "b) Thermal metamorphism",
            "c) Thermodynamic metamorphism",
            "d) Barometric metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the dynamic metamorphism, there is no or very little formation of new minerals. These are the original textures and structures of the rocks that are partially or totally obliterated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Most prevalent kind of metamorphism is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic metamorphism",
            "b) Thermal metamorphism",
            "c) Thermodynamic metamorphism",
            "d) Barometric metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermodynamic is also referred as regional metamorphism and may be considered as the most important as well as prevalent type of metamorphic processes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Dynamothermal or thermodynamic metamorphism involves action of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Fluids",
            "d) Temperature, pressure and fluids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermodynamic metamorphism involves the development of large-scale changes in the structural and chemical constitution of the pre-existing rocks under the combined action of pressure, temperature and fluids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "When the pressure acting on rock is of hydrostatic type then it is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure metamorphism",
            "b) Load metamorphism",
            "c) Secondary metamorphism",
            "d) Clastic metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sometimes the pressure is of the type of hydrostatic type such as load of the overlying rocks. The process is then called load metamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "The kind metamorphism which occurs in the direction of mineralogical reconstitution is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic metamorphism",
            "b) Thermal metamorphism",
            "c) Thermodynamic metamorphism",
            "d) Barometric metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In all types of thermal metamorphism the change is generally in the direction of mineralogical reconstitution. These processes may induce changes varying from simple baking effect to complete or nearly complete recrystallization of almost all original minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "The metamorphic process involving formation of new minerals by chemical replacement of pre-existing minerals is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metagenesis",
            "b) Holomorphism",
            "c) Metasomatism",
            "d) Homosomatism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metasomatism may be broadly defined as a metamorphic process involving essentially formation of new minerals by the mechanism of chemical replacement of pre-existing minerals under the influence of chemically active fluids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Metasomatism occurs at which level and state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecular level and solid state",
            "b) Molecular level and liquid state",
            "c) Atomic level and liquid state",
            "d) Atomic level and solid state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The metasomatism replacement of minerals takes place at atomic level and in solid state. The chemically active fluids may be provided by various ways. "
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "When fluids in the gaseous form, the metasomatism is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrothermal",
            "b) Pneumatolytic",
            "c) Additive",
            "d) Expulsive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pneumatolytic is the process of metasomatism where the fluids are in the form of gases or vapours. "
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which is the structure with extremely fine rock mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Gneissose structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cataclastic structure is characterized by the development of extremely fine rock mass under the influence of severe crushing and shearing effects operating during metamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Give an example for a rock with cataclastic structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Schist",
            "b) Marble",
            "c) Slate",
            "d) Augen gneiss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The effect of shearing and crushing in the metamorphic rocks undergone metamorphism can be observed in rocks spread over wide areas. Rocks like crush breccia, mylonite and slate show this type of structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Structure involving flaky or rod-like structures is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Gneissose structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rock with schistose structure is made up of broadly parallel or sub-parallel layers or bands of flaky, platy or rod-like minerals making it very weak in the direction of parallelism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The structure which also has flaky appearance and bands other than schistose is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Gneissose structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In gneissose structure. Bands or folia of platy and flaky minerals alternate with those of equidimensional and granular minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Structure involving porphyroblasts is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Gneissose structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gneissose texture is indicative of an advance degree of metamorphism under combined action of high temperature, high pressure and active participation of fluids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "The structure similar to maculose is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Augen structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maculose structure is characterized by a spotted appearance of the rock that may be caused due to the formation of large-sized crystals called porphyroblasts within an otherwise fine grained rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which structure has lens-like shaped structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cataclastic structure",
            "b) Schistose structure",
            "c) Augen structure",
            "d) Maculose structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Augen structure is broadly similar to maculose type and is typical of metamorphic rocks in which the effects of crushing under pressure are clearly associated with recrystallization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "The metamorphic rocks showing granulose structure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gneiss",
            "b) Slate",
            "c) Schist",
            "d) Marble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In augen structure, some resistant minerals get deformed into thin, lenticular, lens like shapes giving a characteristic appearance to the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "What are the rocks showing granulose structure called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granolites",
            "b) Granulites",
            "c) Granilites",
            "d) Granites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The individual grains may be irregular in outline but are interlocking. Foliation is absent or negligible. Rocks with granular structure are termed as granulites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "The cleavage also called slaty cleavage is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow cleavage",
            "b) Fracture cleavage",
            "c) Fine cleavage",
            "d) Medium cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flow cleavage is also called flow cleavage because of its development in slates. This cleavage is developed during metamorphism by parallel arrangement of highly cleavable flaky and platy minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The cleavage involving microfractures is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow cleavage",
            "b) Fracture cleavage",
            "c) Fine cleavage",
            "d) Medium cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fracture cleavage is developed due to parallel orientation of very fine structures, often called microfractures, that may be developed in minerals of a rock undergoing dynamic metamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Slaty cleavage is result of which metamorphism of clays and shales?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal",
            "b) Dynamic",
            "c) Thermodynamic",
            "d) Barometric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is often difficult to distinguish between two types of cleavage in hand specimen. The cleavage structure is of great importance in field mapping of metamorphic rocks as it provides very useful information about structural feature like folding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Schistose is resulted due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recrystallization",
            "b) Reforming",
            "c) Reorientation",
            "d) Recrystallization and reorientation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Traces of bedding planes may be found as relict structures in some slates. The slaty cleavage is the result of severe type of dynamic metamorphism of clays and shales. "
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The term including both cleavage and schistosity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foliation",
            "b) Fracture",
            "c) Parting",
            "d) Reverbrance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Schistose results due to combines effect of heat and pressure during metamorphism involving both recrystallization and reorientation of platy minerals as irregular layers or bands. "
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Foliation generally results due to which metamorphism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic",
            "b) Thermal",
            "c) Thermodynamic",
            "d) Barometric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Foliation is a broader term explaining layered structure in metamorphic rocks and is often understood to include cleavage and schistosity. However, foliation in particular expresses segregation of minerals in an alternating manner. "
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Slate is originated from which rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Shale",
            "d) Basalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Slate is a product of low-grade regional metamorphism of argillaceous rocks like clays and shales. "
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Low grade schist is formed under what conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low temperature and local metamorphism",
            "b) High temperature and local metamorphism",
            "c) Low temperature and regional metamorphism",
            "d) Low temperature and regional metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Low grade schists are formed under conditions of regional metamorphism at low temperature. These are rich in minerals like albite, muscovite and chlorite that are unstable at high temperature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "What is the grain size of slate rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Coarse",
            "d) Very coarse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slate is an extremely fine-grained metamorphic rock characterized by a slaty cleavage by virtue of which it can be readily split into thin sheets having parallel smooth surfaces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "High grade schist is formed under what conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local metamorphism",
            "b) Regional metamorphism",
            "c) Displacement metamorphism",
            "d) Chain metamorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High grade schists are formed under conditions of regional metamorphism and atoms rich in minerals that are stable at high temperatures such as garnet. "
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Examples of high grade schist is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Talc- schist",
            "b) Garnet-schist",
            "c) Chlorite-schist",
            "d) Mica-schist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Garnet-schists, cordierite-schists and staurolite-schists are common examples of some high grade schists. "
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Special property of talc schist is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour",
            "b) Its structure",
            "c) Soapy feel",
            "d) Good odour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Talc schist is a low grade schist and its special property is that it gives a soapy feel when touched with bare hands. "
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Gneiss formed from sedimentary rock is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthogneiss",
            "b) Paragneiss",
            "c) Banded gneiss",
            "d) Augen gneiss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paragneiss are formed from the metamorphism of sedimentary rocks like sandstone. Orthogneiss formed as a result of metamorphism of granites and other igneous rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The similar type of rock to quartzite which is sedimentary is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compound quartzite",
            "b) Orthoquartzite",
            "c) Holo-quartzite",
            "d) Accu-quartzite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name orthoquartzite is used for a sedimentary rock of similar composition but having different origin, in which quartz grains are cemented together by siliceous cement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Marble is formed from which rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limestone",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Sandstone",
            "d) Shale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Marble is essentially a granular metamorphic rock composed chiefly of recrystallized limestone. It is characterized by a granulose texture but the grain size shows considerable variation in different varieties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Marble is composed of which mineral?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Felspar",
            "b) Mica",
            "c) Quartz",
            "d) Calcite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Marble is composed chiefly of mineral Calcite (CaCO3) in its crystallised form. Small amounts of many other granular minerals like olivine, serpentine, garnet and some amphiboles are also present in many varieties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "What is the colour of biotite schist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) White",
            "b) Black",
            "c) Red",
            "d) Blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the biotite is metamorphosed to form biotite-schist, the colour is not changed much and hence the colour of biotite-schist is also black. "
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "What is the special property test for identification of marble?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scratch test",
            "b) Alkali test",
            "c) Acid test",
            "d) pH test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the marble is rich in calcite, it readily reacts with acids and this itself it is a test to distinguish marble from other metamorphic rocks. Usually, HCl is used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Identify the metamorphic rock formed by thermodynamic method of metamorphism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slate",
            "b) Gneiss",
            "c) Schist",
            "d) Marble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gneiss is a unique metamorphic rock which is formed by the thermodynamic process of metamorphism. Whereas the other rocks are either formed by thermal or dynamic methamorphism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Pick the characteristic of gneiss which is wrong.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gneiss does not take polish",
            "b) Gneiss also comes in banded structure or texture",
            "c) Pink gneiss is also observed at many places",
            "d) Gneiss takes polish well"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gneiss is a metamorphic rock which sometimes is found to have bands. It is also found to appear in pink-grey colour. Gneiss is known to take excellent polish and hence used as blocks for construction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Quartzite is formed from which rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pure shale",
            "b) Pure Basalt",
            "c) Pure sandstone",
            "d) Pure Granite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Slate is an extremely fine-grained metamorphic rock characterized by a slaty cleavage by virtue of which it can be readily split into thin sheets having parallel smooth surfaces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "What is the mineral which contains a metallic element which can be economically exploited called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ore mineral",
            "b) Metallic mineral",
            "c) Eco-ore",
            "d) Eco-mineral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ore mineral is defined as a mineral which contains a metallic element in a quantity that can be exploited and extracted for use at an economical cost. "
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "The definition of ore is dependent on ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantity",
            "b) Size",
            "c) Colour",
            "d) Quality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Natural concentration of an ore mineral in a massive rock body is defined as an ore deposit. Hence the definition of an ore deposit is also size dependent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "The non-metallic minerals associated with ore minerals are called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-metallic minerals",
            "b) Metallic minerals",
            "c) Gangue minerals",
            "d) Flux minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A few non-metallic minerals are often found associated with an ore-mineral. These have be separated from the ore before the same is processed for extraction of the metal. These associated minerals are called gangue minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "How many types of rocks are there on the basis of time of formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On the basis of their time of formation relative to the host rock, the ore deposits are divided into two groups: syngenetic and epigenetic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "The deposits that have formed simultaneously with the enclosing rock are called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syngenetic",
            "b) Epigenetic",
            "c) Syncgenetic",
            "d) Sinclogenetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Syngenetic deposits are such deposits that have formed simultaneously with the enclosing rock. These are either of igneous or of sedimentary types. "
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Deposits that were formed subsequent to the formation of the host rocks are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syngenetic",
            "b) Epigenetic",
            "c) Syncgenetic",
            "d) Sinclogenetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Epigenetic deposits are those deposits that were formed subsequent to the formation of the host rock. Epigenetic deposits of igneous, sedimentary and metamorphic types are known. "
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The deposits occurring close to the roofs of magmatic masses _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magmatic deposits",
            "b) Pegmatite deposits",
            "c) Hydrothermal deposits",
            "d) Metasomatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pegmatite deposits are sometimes classified as a distinct group of magmatic deposits formed towards the end of crystallization process and such necessarily occurring close to the roofs of magmatic masses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an essential condition for hydrothermal deposits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly active fluids",
            "b) Highly enriched fluids",
            "c) Highly inactive fluids",
            "d) Suitable pathways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The three essential conditions for the formation of hydrothermal deposits are: highly active and enriched fluids, suitable pathways for their migration through the rocks, and suitable physic-chemical environment for their deposition to take place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Type of veins which are bodies of tubular shape in pre-existing fissures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fissure-veins",
            "b) Ladder-veins",
            "c) Gash-veins",
            "d) Stock works"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fissure-veins may be defined as mineral bodies of elongated or tabular shape deposited in pre-existing fissures. The original fissures may be parallel or intersecting, radial or fan-shaped in pattern and that is also the shape of the resulting ore bodies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The type of vein commonly found in igneous rocks is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fissure-veins",
            "b) Ladder-veins",
            "c) Gash-veins",
            "d) Stock works"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ladder-veins are commonly found in igneous rocks such as dykes and similar bodies and consist of transverse, roughly regularly spaced fractures that are filled with deposits of economic minerals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Gash-veins are generally found in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicate minerals",
            "b) Felspar minerals",
            "c) Metallic minerals",
            "d) Carbonate minerals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gash-veins are narrow, sloping and thick-bodies deposits of minerals deposited in solution-fissures or cracks of the host rock which is generally a carbonate rock like limestone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "When gravity is the agent of placing of deposit, the deposit is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deluvial deposit",
            "b) Aeolian deposit",
            "c) Alluvial deposit",
            "d) Beach placers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Deluvial placers is the term used when gravity is the agency involved; such placers would be found along the foot hills and talus slopes."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "The term used for the rock hydrothermal deposits that occur in veins of exceptionally small size, but in good number is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fissure-veins",
            "b) Ladder-veins",
            "c) Gash-veins",
            "d) Stock works"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The term, stock works, is used for hydrothermal deposits that occur in veins or fissures of exceptionally small size, but in good number, within a limited space, traversing the body of rock profusely. "
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which mineral is also used in chemical industry for manufacture of chromates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron",
            "b) Chromite",
            "c) Bauxite",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromite is a strategic mineral finding applications in metallurgy of alloy steels, as a source of metal chromium and as a refractory material. It is used in the chemical industry for the manufacture of chromates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The bauxite in India occurs primarily as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gibbsite",
            "b) Kaolinite",
            "c) Shieldite",
            "d) Karinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bauxite in India occurs primarily as gibbsite Al2O3, its percentage carrying between 40-60 percent and containing silica, iron oxides and titania as important accessory constituents. "
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The best grade chromite in India occurs in which state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Rajasthan",
            "c) Orissa",
            "d) Kerala"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The best grade chromite in India occurs in Orissa. Other states where chromite reserves have been found are: Karnataka, Bihar, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh. "
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Chromite is mostly of which origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous",
            "b) Sedimentary",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Any origin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromite deposits are mostly of igneous origin being associated with highly basic and ultrabasic rocks like periodotites and dunites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "State where copper is not mined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jammu and Kashmir",
            "b) Bihar",
            "c) Maharashtra",
            "d) Rajasthan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In India, copper is being mined from the states of Bihar, Rajasthan, Madhya Pradesh. Copper ores are also extracted in small volume in Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka and Sikkim. "
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Where is the Singhbhum copper belt located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Madhya Pradesh",
            "c) Sikkim",
            "d) Bihar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Singhbhum copper belt of Bihar is made up of epidiorite and quartz-chloride-schist as country rock in which chalcopyrite is the main copper sulphide and quartz, chlorite, biotite and apatite are the gangue minerals. The belt extends for about 15 km. "
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Hutti gold mines are located in which state of India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Madhya Pradesh",
            "c) Sikkim",
            "d) Bihar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Hutti Gold Mines are also located in Karnataka state in Raichur district where the gold lodes occur along fractures within chlorite schists and greenstones in a highly irregular manner. "
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "India is one of the chief producers of which of the following ores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gold",
            "b) Diamond",
            "c) Manganese",
            "d) Lead-zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: India is one of the chief producers of manganese ores in the world occupying 5th to 7th position and competing with Commonwealth of Independent States, South Africa and Brazil. There are three main ore minerals of manganese. "
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Which is the most common ore of lead?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sphalerite",
            "b) Galena",
            "c) Chromite",
            "d) Bauxite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most common ore of lead is Galena-PbS. Similarly, the most common ore of zinc is also sulphide, Sphalerite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "The place in India where Tungsten is extracted is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Kerala",
            "c) Gujarat",
            "d) Rajasthan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: India produces only small quantities of tungsten in Rajasthan. The source mineral is Wolfram which occurs in Rewat in the Degana area. "
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Asbestos is a fibrous variety of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chrysotile",
            "b) Cristile",
            "c) Christile",
            "d) Christine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The common asbestos is actually a fibrous variety of mineral Chrysotile-hydrous silicate of magnesium."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The amphibole varieties are found in which state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Bihar",
            "c) Orissa",
            "d) Rajasthan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The amphibole varieties anthophyllite and tremolite, are produced in Udaipur and Durgapur districts."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Which mineral is used in paints, rubber textiles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asbestos",
            "b) Barytes",
            "c) Corundum",
            "d) Quartz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mineral Baryte finds use in paints, rubber textiles and also in oil well drilling muds besides in chemical industry. "
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which state produces largest amount of barytes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerala",
            "b) Andhra Pradesh and Telangana",
            "c) Karnataka",
            "d) Orissa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Andhra Pradesh is presently the largest producer of barytes in our country. The mineral occurs in limestones spread over districts of Kuddapah, Kurnool and Anantapur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The pure variety of corundum is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emerald and ruby",
            "b) Ruby and Sapphire",
            "c) Sapphire and diamond",
            "d) Ruby and Coral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A high grade natural abrasive- corundum. The mineral finds use in grinding wheels. Its pure varieties form gems- the ruby and sapphire. "
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Dolomite is not used for/as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flux",
            "b) Refractory material",
            "c) Source in special cements",
            "d) Precious gemstones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dolomite is carbonate rock of wide occurrence in India and elsewhere and also with wide applications as a flux in metallurgy, as a refractory material and as source material in special cement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which mineral is used in manufacture of Sorel cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dolomite",
            "b) Magnesite",
            "c) Manganese",
            "d) Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnesite is one of the important refractory materials. Other uses of magnesite include in the manufacture of a special cement called Sorel cement, in chemical industry and also as a source of metal magnesium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Mica is of which origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous",
            "b) Sedimentary",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Erosional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mica mineral is of an igneous origin and commonly occurs in pegmatites in the form of thick sheets and masses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Gypsum commonly occurs as a mineral of which origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary",
            "b) Secondary",
            "c) Tertiary",
            "d) Quarternary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gypsum commonly occurs as a mineral of secondary origin associated with other sedimentary formations in the form of intervening layers, stringers and extended beds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "The only producer of diamond in India is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rajasthan",
            "b) Madhya Pradesh",
            "c) Bihar",
            "d) Orissa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India, diamonds have been produced only in Madhya Pradesh from the well-known Panna diamond mines. Here the mineral occurs in volcanic pipes mixed with primary magmatic rocks and also from the conglomerate deposits around the hill. "
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "The water which in a state of downward movement under gravity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Groundwater",
            "b) Vadose water",
            "c) Connate water",
            "d) Juvenile water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vadose water, which occurs from surface downwards up to a variable depth and is in a state of downward movement under the influence of gravity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "What is the process of movement downwards of vadose water called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infiltration",
            "b) Filtration",
            "c) Deposition",
            "d) Down-flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The movement of vadose water is commonly described as infiltration. The thickness of soil and rock through which the vadose water infiltrates is called the zone of aeration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "What is the upper surface of the zone saturation called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Water table",
            "d) Aquifuge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water table is the name given to the upper surface of the zone of saturation and is of fundamental importance in the study of groundwater reservoirs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about groundwater.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is turbid",
            "b) It is odourless",
            "c) It is free from pathogens",
            "d) It is coloured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Groundwater has a suitable composition in most cases and is free from turbidity, objectionable colours and pathogenic organisms requiring not much treatment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "What is the water obtained from precipitation called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meteoric water",
            "b) Connate water",
            "c) Juvenile water",
            "d) Secondary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The groundwater is relatively much safe from hazards of chemical, radiogenic and biological pollution to which surface water bodies are badly exposed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Water present in rocks from the time of their deposition is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meteoric water",
            "b) Connate water",
            "c) Juvenile water",
            "d) Secondary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Meteoric water is the water derived from precipitation (rain and snow). Although bulk of rainwater or meltwater from snow and ice reaches the sea through surface flows or run off, a considerable part of precipitation gradually infiltrates into the ground. "
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "What is usually the nature of connate water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sweet",
            "b) Odour",
            "c) Salty",
            "d) Odourless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Connate water is the water present in the rocks right from the time of their deposition in an aqueous environment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Juvenile water is also called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meteoric water",
            "b) Connate water",
            "c) Magmatic water",
            "d) Secondary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This connate water may be encountered in sedimentary rocks like limestones, sandstones and gravels. It is commonly saline in nature and is of no importance as a source for exploitable groundwater. "
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Some hot springs are derived from which water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meteoric water",
            "b) Connate water",
            "c) Juvenile water",
            "d) Secondary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Juvenile water is also called magmatic water and is of only theoretical importance as far as water-supply schemes are concerned. "
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "The vadose water which is lost to the atmosphere by transpiration and evaporation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil water",
            "b) Intermediate water",
            "c) Phreatic water",
            "d) Water table"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Juvenile water is the water formed in the cracks or crevices or pores of rocks due to condensation of steam given out from hot molten masses or magmas existing below the Earth’s surface. Some hot springs and geysers are clearly derived from juvenile water. "
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Which zone is a zone of non-saturation among vadose water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil water",
            "b) Intermediate water",
            "c) Phreatic water",
            "d) Water table"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The soil water is very important for the life and growth of the vegetable cover of the globe. It is lost to the atmosphere by transpiration and evaporation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which zones are together called zone of aeration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil water and intermediate zone",
            "b) Intermediate zone and zone of capillary water",
            "c) Zone of capillary water and phreatic water",
            "d) Soil water and phreatic water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intermediate vadose zone occurs immediately below the zone of soil water. It is in fact a zone of non-saturation: water in this zone is moving downwards under the influence of gravity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The zone of water which occurs only in fine particle size is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil water",
            "b) Intermediate water",
            "c) Phreatic water",
            "d) Zone of capillary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intermediate zone is generally of small thickness and may be even absent in many cases. The soil water and intermediate zones are sometimes collectively referred to as the zone of aeration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Which vadose water zone is also called the zone of saturation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil water",
            "b) Intermediate water",
            "c) Phreatic water",
            "d) Zone of capillary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The zone of capillary water, called capillary fringe is present only in the solids and rocks of fine-sized particles underlying the vadose zone. It is absent in the coarse sediments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "The rock mass which is capable of yielding the contained water economically __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Aquifuge",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aquifer is defined as a rock mass, layer or formation which is saturated with groundwater and which virtue of its properties is capable of yielding the contained water at economical costs when tapped. "
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not an example of the good aquifer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Gravels",
            "c) Limestones",
            "d) Sandstones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gravels, limestones and sandstones generally form good aquifers when occurring in suitable geological conditions and geographic situations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The formation which may be porous enough to hold enough quantity of water is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Aquifuge",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A rock body or formation which may be porous enough to hold enough quantity of water which by virtue of its other properties does not allow an easy and quick flow through it, is called an aquiclude. "
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Example for best aquiclude is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granites",
            "b) Gravels",
            "c) Compacted clay",
            "d) Sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aquiclude is to be treated as a practically impermeable rock mass. Compacted clay formation are the best example of aquicludes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Which rock formation is absolutely impermeable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Aquifuge",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aquifuge is an absolutely impermeable rock formation through which there is no possibility of storage or movement of water. "
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Granite and quartzite are examples of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Aquifuge",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aquifuge is almost free from pores and other interstices. Examples are compact interlocking granites and quartzites. "
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Which is the rock mass where partial perviousness is caused because of profuse jointing or cracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquifer",
            "b) Aquiclude",
            "c) Aquifuge",
            "d) Aquitard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aquitard is a less common term used sometimes for an aquifuge or aquiclude that has become locally leaky due to the development of partial perviousness caused because of profuse jointing or cracks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Aquifers are distinguished into how many types on the basis of physical conditions under which water can exist in them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two basic types of aquifers are distinguished on the basis of physical conditions under which water can exist in them: the unconfined aquifer and the confined aquifer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Which aquifer is called water table aquifer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unconfined aquifer",
            "b) Confined aquifer",
            "c) Ground aquifer",
            "d) Connate aquifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unconfined aquifer is also called a water-table aquifer, and is the most common type encountered in the fields. "
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "What is the pressure of upper surface of unconfined aquifer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very high pressure",
            "b) Lower than atmospheric pressure",
            "c) Equal to atmospheric pressure",
            "d) Greater than atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In unconfined aquifer, the upper surface of water or the water-table is under atmospheric pressure which may be acting through the interstices in the overlying rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "What is the isolated water table held by a small extension of impervious rock called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Underlying water",
            "b) Secret water",
            "c) Perched water",
            "d) Underwater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Perched water table is the term used for isolated water table in an aquifer held by a small extension of impervious rock within a large pervious tract. "
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "What is the upper surface of water in a confined aquifer called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary layer",
            "b) Secondary layer",
            "c) First layer",
            "d) Peizometric layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Supplies from perched water-table which are isolated reservoirs are often not reliable as source of water. "
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "At many places where is the piezometric surface with respect to the ground level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Below",
            "b) Same level",
            "c) Above",
            "d) Inclined to ground level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Naturally water held in confined type of aquifer is not under atmospheric pressure but under a greater pressure due to the confining medium. The upper surface of water in a confined aquifer is called piezometric surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "What is the speciality of the Artesian Water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Has a characteristic colour",
            "b) Has a characteristic odour",
            "c) Requires no pumping",
            "d) Requires special type of pumping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Artesian aquifer is, in fact, confined aquifer of such a geometry developed in suitable geological situations so that the mezometric surface is always above the ground level at many places when projected in elevation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Storage capacity of a reservoir depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Porosity of rocks",
            "b) Inter-connections",
            "c) Quality of solidity of rocks",
            "d) Porosity and inter-connections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When water is tapped from Artesian aquifers, it rushes up to and to great heights. Such wells are called Artesian wells, or flowing wells and the type of groundwater obtained from them, which often needs no pumping, as Artesian Water.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "What is the volume of voids in a rock mass expressed in percentage of total volume of rock called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Porosity",
            "b) Voids ratio",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Specific yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The storage capacity of a reservoir depends on the porosity of the rock on the one hand and the nature and inter-connections of the pores. "
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Which types of rocks are highly porous?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous",
            "b) Sedimentary",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Igneous and metamorphic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Porosity is defined as volume of voids in a rock mass expressed in percentage terms of the total volume of the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "What is the quantity of water that a unit volume of aquifer drains by gravity called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Porous volume",
            "b) Water yield",
            "c) Specific yield",
            "d) Unit yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentary rocks are relatively porous because there is a great variation in degree of packing on the one hand and in size, shape and arrangement of the grains on the other hand."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The term which is collectively responsible, along with specific yield, for total porosity of an aquifer is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unit yield",
            "b) Specific retention",
            "c) Unit retention",
            "d) Specific allowance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Porosity is a property of primary importance in determining the water bearing qualities of a rock. Only porous rocks can be aquifers but high porosity itself is not sufficient to ensure water yielding capacity of a rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Which sedimentary rock is told to be the best kind of formation for groundwater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Shale",
            "c) Gravel",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gravels are classed among the best kind of formations to yield groundwater. But these too show a great variation in their water bearing properties depending on the degree of assortment, packing and cementing of the grains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "The rock which shows great variation in water yielding capacity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Coal",
            "d) Marble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sandstones are the sedimentary rocks that show great variation in their water yielding capacity which is chiefly controlled by their texture and nature of the cementing material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "What is rated next to the gravels as water yielding materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Sands",
            "c) Granite",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sand beds or loosely packed sandstones are rated next to gravels as water yielding materials. "
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "The porosity range of limestone is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 to 75%",
            "b) 20 to 50%",
            "c) 10 to 40%",
            "d) 1 to 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The porosity of limestones varies from 1 to 20%. Hydraulic conductivity in highly karsted limestones may be as high as 100 m/day or even more, to be classed among the extremely permeable rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "What are the qualities required for glacial deposits to make good aquifers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform size and rounded nature",
            "b) Non-uniform and angular nature",
            "c) Uniform size and angular nature",
            "d) Non-uniform and rounded nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the glacial deposits are made up of sediments of uniform size and rounded nature, they present with best quality. When sufficiently thick and extensive, these may be depended as reliable groundwater reservoirs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "The igneous rock rich in cavities is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Basalt",
            "c) Gabbro",
            "d) Dolomite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Igneous rocks are either intrusive or extrusive in nature. The intrusive igneous rocks are dense in texture with all the component minerals very closely crystallized. The extrusive rocks exhibit great variation in their water bearing properties. "
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "When can a surface become porous and permeable or water bearing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weathered",
            "b) Weathered and wet",
            "c) Weathered and disintegrated",
            "d) Disintegrated and wet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Basic volcanic rocks like basalts, are characterized by greater gas content and high mobility at the time of eruption. "
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "The fractured and fissured metamorphic rock is similar in character to which igneous rock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic",
            "b) Plutonic",
            "c) Hypabyssal",
            "d) Dykes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In all igneous rocks, the surface zone when highly weathered and disintegrated may become quite porous and permeable and hence water-bearing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t control aquifer behaviour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind conditions",
            "b) Nature of the rock",
            "c) Structural disposition",
            "d) Climate conditions like precipitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As a storage reservoir, the aquifer behaviour is controlled by- the nature of the rock and its porosity, structural disposition, with regard to the recharge points or places, climate conditions like annual precipitation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "An aquifer can hold water _________ and the state of water is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permanently – State of flow",
            "b) Temporarily – State of flow",
            "c) Permanent – State of stagnancy",
            "d) Temporary – State of stagnancy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It must be remembered that an aquifer can hold water only temporarily, as the water is always in a state of flow in it. However, the rate of flow of water through an aquifer is very slow compared to surface waters."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The quantity of water that can be withdrawn annually and also the rate at which this withdrawal could be made without adversely affecting the inventory of the aquifer is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Annual yield",
            "b) Percent yield",
            "c) Operational yield",
            "d) Monthly yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The importance of groundwater in water supply system can hardly be over emphasized. It is in no way subordinate to that of surface waters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "When an aquifer is used to artificially recharge by making it pass through an intervening layer, the aquifer acts as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A cooling agent",
            "b) An aerating agent",
            "c) An odour agent",
            "d) A filter plant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quantity of water that can be withdrawn annually and also the rate at which the withdrawal could be made without adversely affecting the inventory of the aquifer, therefore, determine what may be called operational yield. "
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "When would the dam become irrelevant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the rocks are strong",
            "b) When the rocks are impermeable",
            "c) When the rocks are porous",
            "d) When the rocks are weathered to a certain extent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An aquifer may be made to serve as a filter plant when artificial recharge is made to pass through an intervening layer of rock, which acts as a natural filter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Which quality of rock should be known properly for the foundations of dams, reservoirs, etc.?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour knowledge",
            "b) Geological",
            "c) Hydrogeological",
            "d) History of the formation of rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A dam is built across a river primarily to store water in the form of a reservoir. The whole idea of a dam would become irrelevant if the foundations on which it is built are made of porous rocks or if a stretch of a reservoir rock is permeable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Groundwater is a source of trouble at which place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plains",
            "b) Slopes",
            "c) Rivers",
            "d) Lakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The position of the water table and hydrogeological qualities of rocks forming foundations and abutments of dams and reservoirs must be known. "
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "An associated protection of rising water-table is the development of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loss of nutrients",
            "b) Loss of good quality of water",
            "c) Salinity of water",
            "d) Increase in turbidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Groundwater is a major source of trouble for the stability of slopes. Many slope failures, especially in hilly regions are due to direct or indirect involvement of groundwater. "
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "The root system of crops in water-logged areas get __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decomposed",
            "b) Enriched with nutrients",
            "c) Photosynthesised",
            "d) Growth inhibited"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An associated trouble with rising water-table is the development of salinity of the soils. The rising groundwater may be rich in some undesirable salts that are left at or near the surface during its loss to atmosphere due to evaporation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The study of earthquakes is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eathquakology",
            "b) Tremology",
            "c) Seismology",
            "d) Quakegraphy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The science dealing with the study of earthquake in all their aspects is called seismology. It is interdisciplinary science, which is partly geology and partly physics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "The point of origin of an earthquake below the earth’s surface is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isocentre",
            "b) Isopoint",
            "c) Focus",
            "d) Epicentre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The place or point of origin of an earthquake below the surface of the earth is termed as its focus or hypocenter. It may lie from a few hundred meters to hundreds of kilometres below the surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "The point vertically above the focus is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epicenter",
            "b) Isocenter",
            "c) Epivector",
            "d) Isovector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The point or place on the surface vertically above the focus of a particular earthquake is termed as its epicentre. "
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "What is the location of maximum damage caused due to an earthquake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Focus",
            "b) Epicenter",
            "c) 100 km from epicenter",
            "d) Same everywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The epicenter is that place on the surface of the earth where the vibrations from a particular earthquake reach first of all. It is often the location of maximum damage in that event. "
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "What is the maximum depth of focus observed till date?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 km",
            "b) 500 km",
            "c) 700 km",
            "d) 1000 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As regards the distance from epicenter to focus, or depth of focus, it has been observed from the study of seismic records that no earthquake with a focus deeper than 700 km has been recorded so far. "
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "The seismic waves which are longitudinal __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary waves",
            "b) Secondary waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Love waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The P-waves are also called the primary waves, push and pull waves, longitudinal waves and compressional waves. These are the fastest of the seismic waves and are longitudinal in character. "
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The seismic waves which are also called transverse waves are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) S-waves",
            "b) P-waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Love waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The S-waves are also called secondary waves, the shear waves, the transverse waves or the distortional waves. These waves are transverse in character, like the light waves. "
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Which waves have helped geologists understand the nature of the earth’s core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-waves",
            "b) S-waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Love waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The S-waves would not propagate through a liquid medium at all. This is a proven fact with S-waves and has helped geologists a lot in understanding the nature of the core of the earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "What are the P and S waves collectively called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group waves",
            "b) Combined waves",
            "c) Body waves",
            "d) Duel waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The P and S-waves are sometimes collectively referred to as body waves because they travel deep into the body of the Earth before re-emerging on the surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "What are the surface waves called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-waves",
            "b) S-waves",
            "c) Long waves",
            "d) Transverse waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During each earthquake, elastic waves are generated at the focus. These waves are called seismic waves and they travel in all directions with their characteristic velocities. "
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Further classification of L-waves is done into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The L-waves are also called long waves, or surface waves because their journey is confined mainly to the near-surface layers of the Earth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Type of L-wave in which the particle is of a complex nature is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Love waves",
            "b) Shock waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Transverse waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The L-waves are comparatively sluggish and recorded only after the arrival of the P and S-waves. In character, the surface waves are of two main types- Rayleigh and love waves. "
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Type of L-wave in which the particle is in the direction of propagation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Love waves",
            "b) Shock waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Transverse waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rayleigh waves are the waves in which the displacement of the particle is of a complex nature, partly being in the direction of propagation and partly at right angles to it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which waves travel faster in non-layered homogeneous structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Love waves",
            "b) Shock waves",
            "c) Rayleigh waves",
            "d) Transverse waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Love waves are the waves in which the displacement of the particle is practically horizontal, that is, in the direction of propagation. The love waves tend to create shearing ruptures."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "The magnitude of the quake is based on what aspect of the wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Time period",
            "d) Intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The velocity of surface waves is controlled by the frequency of waves and the structure of the ground. In the homogeneous non-layered structures, Rayleigh waves travel fast and form the prominent L-waves. "
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Ritcher magnitude is the log to 10th base of maximum seismic amplitude recorded at what distance from epicenter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 km",
            "b) 50 km",
            "c) 100 km",
            "d) 200 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnitude is the term expressing the rating of an earthquake on the basis of amplitude of seismic waves recorded as seismograms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The term expressing the qualitative effect of earthquake is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Time period",
            "d) Intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Ritcher magnitude is the logarithm to the base 10 of the maximum seismic wave amplitude recorded on a seismograph at a distance of 100 km from the epicenter of a particular earthquake."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "What is the depth of focus in the shallow earthquakes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Up to 100 km",
            "b) Up to 200 km",
            "c) Up to 60 km",
            "d) Up to 150 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the shallow earthquakes, depth of focus lies anywhere up to 60 km below the surface. A great majority of the earthquakes in the past had been of this type. "
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "How many types on the basis of depth of focus are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three classes of earthquakes are recognized on the basis of depth of focus: shallow, intermediate and deep seated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "60 – 300 km focus distance is seen in which type of earthquake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow earthquake",
            "b) Intermediate earthquake",
            "c) Deep seated earthquake",
            "d) Tertiary earthquake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intermediate earthquakes originate between 60 and 300 km below the surface. These are rare in occurrence but their effects are felt over large areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "The type of earthquake very rare in occurrence is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shallow earthquake",
            "b) Intermediate earthquake",
            "c) Deep seated earthquake",
            "d) Tertiary earthquake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deep seated earthquakes originate between 300 and 700 km, and are very rare phenomena. "
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which class of earthquakes are most destructive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class A",
            "b) Class B",
            "c) Class D",
            "d) Class E"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Earthquakes of class A are highly destructive whereas those of class E are not of any significance in relation to engineering structures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "How many types of earthquakes are classified based on the cause of origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two broad classes of earthquakes distinguished on the basis of the cause of origin. They are- tectonic earthquakes and non-tectonic earthquakes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Which earthquake is caused due to faulting or relative displacements of blocks of the crust of the earth along rupture planes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tectonic earthquakes",
            "b) Shallow earthquakes",
            "c) Class-A earthquakes",
            "d) Non-tectonic earthquakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tectonic earthquakes are caused due to faulting or relative displacements of blocks of the crust of the earth along rupture planes. Most commonly, the major earthquakes are of tectonic origin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Earthquakes originating due to volcanic eruptions or landslides are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tectonic earthquakes",
            "b) Shallow earthquakes",
            "c) Class-A earthquakes",
            "d) Non-tectonic earthquakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non-tectonic earthquakes owe their origin to causes distinctly different from faulting such as volcanic eruptions, atomic explosions or due to landslides and subsidence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "The number of classes of earthquakes based on magnitude of Ritcher scale are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is customary to mention earthquakes by its magnitude on the Ritcher scale. Sometimes earthquakes are grouped into five classes on the basis of magnitude. "
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which earthquake is local in nature and rarely occurring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic earthquake",
            "b) Shallow earthquake",
            "c) Collapse earthquake",
            "d) Intermediate earthquake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In volcanic eruptions, huge quantities of lava are thrown out suddenly under great pressure and with a big bang, causing tremors all around volcanic earthquakes, as these are called, are rarely felt outside the regions of active volcanoes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which theory is acclaimed as a satisfactory explanation about the cause of earthquakes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic Rebound theory",
            "b) Clastic theory",
            "c) Tremors theory",
            "d) Seismology theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The collapse earthquakes are invariably of local nature and rare occurrence. These are caused when a portion of ground collapses suddenly because of removal of support from below due to the natural processes of rock wastage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "The phase during which the stored elastic energy is released is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparatory phase",
            "b) Rupture phase",
            "c) Post failure phase",
            "d) Tertiary phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Elastic Rebound Theory propounded originally by H.F.Reid in 1906 is, at present, widely acclaimed as a satisfactory explanation. It was proposed by him, on the basis of elaborate studies of San Francisco Earthquake of 1906 that it was related to displacement along the San Andres fault. "
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Foreshocks are often recorded in which phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparatory phase",
            "b) Rupture phase",
            "c) Post failure phase",
            "d) Tertiary phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rupture phase takes place along the fault and all or part the stored elastic energy is released as seismic waves and also transformed into heat or potential energy. Main shock is the characteristic of this phase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The phase which involves restoration to state of equilibrium is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparatory phase",
            "b) Rupture phase",
            "c) Post failure phase",
            "d) Tertiary phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The preparatory phase is the phase in which a non-hydrostatic stress field is created in a certain region around a fault; the direction of the preparatory phase is to ultimately define the size of the actual earthquake. A number of “foreshocks” are often recorded during this phase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Earthquakes occur at which portion of plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Middle portion",
            "b) Along the boundaries of plates",
            "c) Along the equidistant lines of plates",
            "d) At the centre point of the plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The post failure adjustment is the phase during which the medium is restored to a state of equilibrium involving series of “after shocks” which are simply a manifestation of release of residual strain from the rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "The plate movements at boundaries are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very rapid",
            "b) Fast",
            "c) Moderate in speed",
            "d) Very slow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Already exhaustive data has been collected to show that earthquakes occur along the boundaries of plates moving apart each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Rocks behave as ________ masses towards operating stresses.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inelastic",
            "b) Elastic",
            "c) Isotropic",
            "d) Anisotropic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tectonism involving earthquakes is related to those boundaries, which are stressed and where stress is released by way of thrust faulting, block faulting or transcurrent faulting. The inner regions of plates are by and large free from tectonic earthquakes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Structures built on which land have to withstand greater risk during earthquakes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid mass",
            "b) Loose soil",
            "c) Strong rocks",
            "d) Unfractured mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Structures built on loose soil or sediments or weak rocks will have to withstand greater risk compared to those founded on solid bed rocks in the same region, other things being the same. "
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "What do the rocks undergo during seismic shocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tension",
            "b) Expansion",
            "c) Strengthening",
            "d) Compaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Structures built on loose soil are more risky, due to the fact that soil particles undergo a lot of compaction during seismic shocks thereby causing settlement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "What should be the type of foundation for concrete and masonry buildings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous",
            "b) Discontinuous",
            "c) Shallow foundation",
            "d) Isolated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Foundations for concrete and masonry buildings should be excavated to the same level throughout the building, and should be, as far as possible of continuous type. "
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "What is the characteristic of walls for quake resistant buildings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy weight",
            "b) As thick as possible",
            "c) Light weight",
            "d) Acoustic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The walls should be unless properly designed for resisting lateral forces, as light in weight as possible and made up of wood or light weight concrete. "
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "What should be maintained in cross walls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuity",
            "b) Discontinuity",
            "c) Intersections",
            "d) Gaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Continuity of crosswalls should be maintained as far as possible and in such a way that different parts of the building behave as integrals of the same structure and not at random. "
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which type of roofs gives better resistance against shocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sloped roofs",
            "b) Thached roofs",
            "c) Flat roofs",
            "d) Straw roofs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stronger and resistant walls should be designed with reinforced rather than plain concrete. "
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which of the following need not be avoided for construction of quake resistant buildings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform height",
            "b) Chimneys",
            "c) Heavy weight walls",
            "d) Discontinuous foundations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flat, RCC roofs give better resistance against shocks compared to the sloping roofs or those designed with different slope angles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "In a storage dam, how many forces have to be considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As far as possible, uniform height should be given to the structure. The rest of the options have to be avoided as much as possible, as they are risky for the construction of quake resistant buildings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "To avoid shearing, dam has to be placed as far as possible from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joints",
            "b) Folds",
            "c) Intrusions",
            "d) Faults"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A dam is subject to a more complex system of forces during an earthquake compared to a multi-storeyed building. The risk factor has to be of a higher order."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "What is the downgrade movement of mass along no definite surface called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flowage",
            "b) Sliding",
            "c) Subsidence",
            "d) Earthquake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By flowage is understood a downgrade movement of mass along no definite surface of failure. Mass involved in this type of failure is primarily unconsolidated or loosely packed or rendered so by natural processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "In which type of flowage, failure is not easily perceptible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid failure",
            "b) Quick failure",
            "c) Slow failure",
            "d) Moderate failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flowage is further distinguished into slow and rapid flowage. In the slow flowage, failure is not easily perceptible. The ground may be moving downslope at such low rates as few centimeters a year or even less."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "In which type of flowage, failure is easily visible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid failure",
            "b) Quick failure",
            "c) Slow failure",
            "d) Moderate failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In rapid flowage, however, the movement of failing mass may be easily visible and the mass may travel a few metres or more a day. The conditions causing flowage in the two classes may be closely related or entirely different. "
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "What is a type of mass failure in which a superficial mass fails by moving as a whole along a definite surface of failure called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flowage",
            "b) Sliding",
            "c) Subsidence",
            "d) Earthquake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A true landslide is a type of mass failure in which a superficial mass fails by moving as a whole along a definite surface of failure. The surface of failure may be planar or semi-circular in outline. "
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "What is the characteristic of the mass above and below a landslide respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both stable",
            "b) Both unstable",
            "c) Unstable and stable",
            "d) Stable and unstable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is often characteristic of a landslide that the mass above the failure surface is unstable whereas the material lying below this surface is generally stable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "What type of landslide may undergo landslide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock fragments",
            "b) Loose soil",
            "c) Whole blocks",
            "d) Any type of mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sliding may involve material of any composition, shape and of varying degree of consolidation: Loose soil, rock fragments and whole blocks or slabs of rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "What is the character of the surface of shear in hard, brittle and coherent mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curved",
            "b) Planar",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Undulated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the mass involved is hard, brittle and coherent, such as massive igneous, sedimentary and metamorphic rocks, shear surfaces are broadly planar in character. "
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "What is the character of the surface of shear in loose, inherently weak rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curved",
            "b) Planar",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Undulated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In unconsolidated deposits, loose, inherently weak rock masses and weathered top surface, sliding commonly takes place along curved shear surfaces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Type of landslide where surface of failure is planar is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translational",
            "b) Rotational",
            "c) Rock toppling",
            "d) Longitudinal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface of failure is generally planar in character, speed of failure is quite rapid and the nature of mass involved in failing may be rock mass, rock slabs, debris and soil cover or even a mixture of all of them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "What is the characteristic sloping surface in rotational slides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curved",
            "b) Planar",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Undulated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In rotational slides, the failing surface is generally curved in character and the speed of failure is also quite rapid. Because of the nature of the failing surface, the movement of the mass takes the form of a sort of rotation, rather than translation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Type in which falls are involved rather than sliding is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translational sliding",
            "b) Rotational sliding",
            "c) Rock toppling and falls",
            "d) Subsidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rock toppling and falls are grouped along with slides although there may be little or no sliding involved in their failure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Sinking or settling of the ground in almost vertical direction naturally is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flowage",
            "b) Sliding",
            "c) Avalanche",
            "d) Subsidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Subsidence is defined as sinking or settling of the ground in almost vertically downward direction which may occur because of the removal of natural support from the underground or due to compaction of the weaker rocks under the load from overlying mass. "
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "What movements is observed in all cases of subsidence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal",
            "b) Shearing",
            "c) Vertical",
            "d) Inclined movement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The net result in each case is that the surface material is natural ground or artificial fill- suffers a sinking downward movement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "In which type of slide, weather conditions play a very important role?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translational sliding",
            "b) Rotational sliding",
            "c) Rock toppling and falls",
            "d) Subsidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In rock toppling and falls, the weather conditions play a very important role compared to other types of sliding. The precipitation, frost action leads to changes in the rocks and lead to rock toppling and falling. "
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Translational sliding is quite common in slopes made up of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rocks",
            "b) Cohesive soils",
            "c) Rocks and non-cohesive soils",
            "d) Rocks and cohesive soils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In translational slides, the sliding is quite rapid and the nature of mass involved in failing may be a rock, rock slabs, debris etc. These slides are quite frequent on slopes made up of rocks and cohesive soils. "
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "The factors that cause the failure are generally grouped into how many?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the factors that facilitate mass failure in one way or another are generally grouped in two headings: Internal factors and External factors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "The causes which tend to reduce the shearing strength of the soil are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal factors",
            "b) External factors",
            "c) Extensive factors",
            "d) Weather factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Internal factors include such cases, which tend to reduce the shearing strength of the soil or rock mass by virtue of which it had remained stable at a given position on the ground. "
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Nature of slope includes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of material and angle of mass",
            "b) Mass of material and type of material",
            "c) Type of material and shape of mass",
            "d) Mass of material and angle of mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nature of slope includes two important characters of the slope. By nature of slope is meant here the type of material of which the land mass is made up and the angle at which this particular mass is inclined with the horizontal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "The force which helps to retain the position of mass in space is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compressive resistance",
            "b) Tensile resistance",
            "c) Shearing resistance",
            "d) Bending resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most important force among the forces by virtue of which it can retain its position in space is undoubtedly the shearing resistance of the mass. "
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "The force which tends to induce failure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shearing resistance",
            "b) Force due to gravity",
            "c) Force due to compression",
            "d) Force due to loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the forces that tend to induce failure in a mass, the most important is the pull due to gravity which acts through the weight of the material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "The angle of slope up to which the materials are stable in a slope is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear angle",
            "b) Angle of failure",
            "c) Critical angle",
            "d) Sub-angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As, when and where the forces tending to induce failure dominate over those tending to resist failure, the mass becomes unstable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "In the recent times what other aspect of the slope is considered for its stability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The type of rocks in the slope",
            "b) The type of land mass below the slope",
            "c) Height of the slope",
            "d) Length of the slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It has been observed that most materials are stable up to a certain angle of slope. This is called the critical angle of slope or also called as angle of repose and varies from 35° for unconsolidated sediments to 90° for perfectly crystalline unjointed rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Solvent action can been seen in rocks which are made of _______ minerals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Active",
            "b) Inactive",
            "c) Soluble",
            "d) Insoluble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In fact much importance has been attached in recent times to the height of the slope in addition to the angle of slope for determining the factor of safety. "
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a failure due to the role of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in pore pressure",
            "b) Accumulation of water at the back of the rock",
            "c) Accumulation of water at the front of the rock",
            "d) Lubrication effect of the rock mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The various causes of rock mass due to the role of water are: Increase in pore pressure, accumulation of water behind the rock mass, lubrication of water etc. Water cannot get accumulated in front of the rock and if it does happen in some conditions, it does not contribute greatly to the failure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "The rock which can be stable even with vertical slopes is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sandstone",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Shale",
            "d) Chalk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crystalline igneous rocks like granites and gabbros and massive metamorphic rocks like marbles, quartzites and gneisses may be stable even with vertical slopes, whereas the same cannot be said about chalk. "
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which type of sandstone is more stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cemented with siliceous material",
            "b) Cemented with argillaceous material",
            "c) Cemented with ferruginous material",
            "d) Cemented with calcareous material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sandstones for instance, occur in a great variety of types. Fine textured, dense and massive sandstones with siliceous cements may be very stable even at vertical slopes whereas the same rock with ferruginous, calcareous and clayey cements may become unstable at angle of 60° or even less. "
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "What can be said about stability of slope when the layers are horizontal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable up to 45°",
            "b) Stable at all angles up to 90°",
            "c) Unstable up to 45°",
            "d) Unstable at all angles up to 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The layers horizontal layers: Such rocks forming the slopes of the natural valleys and artificial cuts are stable at all angles up to 90°. When they fail, it may be due to the presence of secondary jointing or related fractures. "
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "What has to be considered while giving cuts in stratified rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Risk factor",
            "b) Complication factor",
            "c) Safety factor",
            "d) Dip factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dip factor has to be kept in mind while giving cuts in stratified rocks. it may be possible to explain that cuts parallel to the dip of the rocks are more safe and stable compared to those parallel to the strike of layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "Which zones are most potential surfaces for rock slips?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth surfaces",
            "b) Rough surfaces",
            "c) Shear zones",
            "d) Tensile zones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In metamorphic rocks derived from stratified sedimentary rocks, the direction of cleavage with respect to the original bedding may cause a complex system of weak planes. As such slips may be of common occurrence in the slopes made of the above metamorphic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an external factor for failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composition of the mass",
            "b) Role of water",
            "c) Geological structures",
            "d) Removal of vegetation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shear zones are most potential surfaces for rock slips, especially when lubricated with water due to soft character of the shear zone material. "
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method of control of mass movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Afforestation",
            "b) Retaining wall",
            "c) Chemical treatment of rocks",
            "d) Deforestation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The widely adopted methods for control of mass movements include, construction of retaining walls, chemical treatment of rocks, rock bolting and to some extent afforestation can avoid mass movements, but, deforestation promotes mass movements. "
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "While devising a monitoring system, what has to be kept in mind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factor of safety",
            "b) Cost-benefit ratio",
            "c) Stress factor",
            "d) Dip factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In devising a monitoring system, the cost-benefit ratio has to be kept in mind in all the cases because such systems are invariably expensive. "
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Which of the following might not reduce the chances of infiltration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cooling the slope material",
            "b) Oiling the surface of slopes",
            "c) Electro-osmosis of the slope material",
            "d) Heating of the slope material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oiling of the slope surfaces, electro-osmosis and heating of the slope material have been also used in different countries to stabilize slopes by reducing chances of infiltration during heavy rains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Retraining structures may prove exceptionally successful when?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ground is too fine",
            "b) The sliding mass is likely to remain wet",
            "c) The movement is of deep nature",
            "d) The sliding mass is likely to remain dry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Retaining structures may prove exceptionally successful where- the ground is neither too fine nor too plastic; the sliding mass is likely to remain dry and the movement is of a shallow nature and limited extent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "When might the retaining walls prove to be not costly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the movement is of deep nature",
            "b) When the movement is of unlimited nature",
            "c) When the movement is shallow in nature",
            "d) When the rocks are too heavy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Retaining walls may prove costly failures when they are designed to resist slides of great volume and thickness or long rising slopes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Pneumatically applied mortar or concrete is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grout",
            "b) Gunite",
            "c) Geo-polymer concrete",
            "d) Geniter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gunite, is pneumatically applied mortar or concrete. The mixture of cement and sand (1:3) with little water is applied on the face under pressure and is known to develop sufficient strength on settling and hardening."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method of slope treatment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing drainage systems",
            "b) Flattening the slope",
            "c) Decreasing the load",
            "d) Digging rock traps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually the slope treatment methods include, flattening the slope to ensure stable limits, decreasing the load and also digging rock traps in the form of ditches at the foot of a slope and providing benches at proper intervals. Providing a drainage system is a drainage method. "
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Which type of trees and plants are more effective in reducing infiltration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tropical",
            "b) Deciduous",
            "c) Temperate",
            "d) Plantation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Afforestation of potentially unstable slopes reduces the risk of their failure considerably. Vegetation cover, especially of deciduous trees and plants reduces the quantity of infiltration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "A solid barrier constructed at a suitable location across a river valley to impound water is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reservoir",
            "b) Dam",
            "c) Bridge",
            "d) Retaining wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A dam may be defined as a solid barrier constructed at a suitable location across a river valley with a view of impounding water flowing through that river."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not an objective for the construction of the dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To make sure rains occur periodically",
            "b) Generation of hydropower energy",
            "c) Providing water supply for domestic and industrial purposes",
            "d) Providing irrigational facilities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dams are constructed for achieving any one or more of the following objectives: generation of hydropower energy; providing water for irrigation facilities; providing water supply for domestic and industrial purposes; fighting droughts and controlling of floods; providing navigational facilities. "
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "The criteria to classify a dam as a large dam is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of the crest of the dam lesser than 500 m",
            "b) Capacity of the reservoir less than 1 million cubic meters",
            "c) Maximum flood discharge less than 2000 cubic meters/second",
            "d) Capacity of the reservoir not less than 1 million cubic meters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Following conditions are necessary to classify a dam as large dams: length of the crest of the dam not lesser than 500 m; capacity of the reservoir not less than 1 million cubic meters; maximum flood discharge not less than 2000 cubic meters/second. "
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which state in India has the most number of large dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Orissa",
            "c) Maharashtra",
            "d) Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The greatest number of large dams are in Maharashtra (1508), followed by Madhya Pradesh (752); Gujarat (365), Karnataka (213), Orissa (149), Rajasthan (128) and Uttar Pradesh have a single large dam till the twentieth century."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Which is the longest dam in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hirakud dam",
            "b) Bhakra dam",
            "c) Krishnarajasagar dam",
            "d) Nagarjun sagar dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The longest dam is the Hirakud dam having a height of 59 m and length of about 5 km and built across Mahanadi in Orissa. "
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Which is the tallest dam in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hirakud dam",
            "b) Bhakra dam",
            "c) Krishnarajasagar dam",
            "d) Nagarjun sagar dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tallest in India is the Bhakra dam with a height of 226 m and length at the crest of 518 m, located in Himachal Pradesh. "
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Which type of dam usually has a triangular profile and can resist the forces by its own weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dam",
            "b) Arch dam",
            "c) Geotechnical dam",
            "d) Embankment dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A gravity dam is a solid masonry or concrete structure, generally of a triangular profile, which is so designed that it can safely stand against a pre-calculated volume of water by virtue of its own weight. "
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "What is very critical about gravity dams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength of the concrete used",
            "b) Strength of the masonry used",
            "c) Strength of the rock foundation",
            "d) The type of water stored in the reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the forces arising in a gravity dam as due to the thrust of the impounded water and the massive weight of the dam material- are assumed to be directly transmitted to the foundation rocks. Hence the strength of the foundation rocks is the most critical factor. "
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Type of dam where the forces acting on the dam are transmitted onto the abutment rocks is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dam",
            "b) Arch dam",
            "c) Geotechnical dam",
            "d) Embankment dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The upstream face in a gravity dam may be vertical or inclined. Similarly, the axis of the dam may be straight or curvature may be induced in the design of the dam. "
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which type of dam cannot be constructed even on the rock foundations which are not sufficiently strong enough?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dam",
            "b) Arch dam",
            "c) Geotechnical dam",
            "d) Embankment dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An arch dam, as the name implies, is an arch-shaped solid structure mostly of concrete, which is designed in such a way that a major part of the thrust forces acting on the dam are transmitted mainly by the arc action, on to the abutment rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "How many types of arch dams are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two main types of arch dams are: The constant radius arch dam and the variable radius dam. "
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "The type of arch dam in which upstream face is vertical is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant radius arch dam",
            "b) Variable radius arch dam",
            "c) Vertical arch dam",
            "d) Inclined arch dam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The constant radius arch dam is an arch dam in which the radius of curvature throughout the structure is constant and upstream face is vertical. "
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "An arch dam having a curvature both in horizontal and vertical alignment is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant radius arch dam",
            "b) Variable radius dam",
            "c) Cupola",
            "d) Cipalo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An arch dam having a curvature both in horizontal and vertical alignment is often called a cupola dam. "
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Pick the wrong statement about arch dams.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arch dams are heavier compared to other types",
            "b) Arch dams offer many advantages over other dams",
            "c) Arch dams are quite thin walled compared to gravity dams",
            "d) Arch dams are lighter in weight compared to other types"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ideal situation, arch dams offer many advantages over other types of dams. Arch dams are quite thin walled compared to gravity dams and hence lighter in weight. "
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Arch dams are best suitable for which site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat lands",
            "b) Plateaus",
            "c) Narrow valleys",
            "d) Very wide valleys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arch dams are better suited for narrow valleys with strong and uniformly sloping walls or abutments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "The arch dam in India is situated in which state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karnataka",
            "b) Gujarat",
            "c) Kerala",
            "d) Maharashtra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Idukki dam in Kerala is an important arch dam of our country. "
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "The dam which generally is of trapezoidal shape is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dams",
            "b) Arch dams",
            "c) Cupola dams",
            "d) Embankment dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Embankment dams include a variety of non-rigid structures which are built over wide valleys with varying foundation characteristics from easily available materials such as earth and rock fragments. These are generally of trapezoidal shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "The dam which can be constructed even on glacial deposits is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dams",
            "b) Arch dams",
            "c) Embankment dams",
            "d) Cupola dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main advantage of the embankment dams is that they can be constructed on weak foundations such as unconsolidated weak-river or glacial deposits. "
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "The Hirakud dam in India is which type of dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity dams",
            "b) Arch dams",
            "c) Cupola dams",
            "d) Embankment dams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Hirakud dam in Orissa is one of the longest embankment dams of our country. "
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "The compacted core is generally made of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shale",
            "b) Clay",
            "c) Limestone",
            "d) Coal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An embankment dam is constructed as a homogeneous construction but very commonly, with a properly compacted core of impervious material such as clay. "
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "When a site is said to be sound, which of the following character is not desirable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong",
            "b) Impermeable",
            "c) Stable",
            "d) Permeable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Technically, the site should be as sound as possible: strong, impermeable and stable strong rocks at the site make the job of the designer much easy: he can evolve best designs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Rocks are inherently which type of materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isotropic",
            "b) Anisotropic",
            "c) Homogeneous",
            "d) Non-homogeneous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rocks are inherently anisotropic materials, showing variation in properties in different directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "When is the strength of sound rock always greater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When stresses are normal to bedding planes",
            "b) When stresses are parallel to bedding planes",
            "c) When stresses are inclined at 45° to bedding planes",
            "d) When stresses are inclined at 60° to bedding planes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The strength of sound, unfractured stratified rock is always greater when the stresses are acting normal to the bedding planes than if applied in other directions.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "The most unfavourable strike direction is when the beds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strike parallel to axis of dam and the dip is upstream",
            "b) Strike parallel to axis of dam and the dip is downstream",
            "c) Strike normal to axis of dam and the dip is downstream",
            "d) Strike normal to axis of dam and the dip is upstream"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most unfavourable strike direction is the one in which the beds strike parallel to the axis of the dam and the dip is downstream. It must be avoided as far as possible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method for dam construction when a shear zone is encountered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Construct on shear zone",
            "b) Grouting the shear zones",
            "c) Try and avoid the site as much as possible",
            "d) Excavation and back filling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally small scale fault zones and shear zones can be treated by grouting. But in the case of major shear zones, weak material would be excavated and the space backfilled with hard material like concrete up to the required depth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "In synclinal bends, dams placed on which part would run risk of leaking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upstream limb",
            "b) Downstream limb",
            "c) Core",
            "d) Sloping side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In synclinal bends, dams placed on the upstream limbs would run the risk of leakage from beneath the dam. "
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "What aspect of the joint has to be thoroughly studied before construction of a dam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geometry of the joint",
            "b) The depth of the joint",
            "c) Nature of the joint",
            "d) The texture of the rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geometry of joints, their intensity, nature and continuity with depth, all must be thoroughly established and their effects on the site rocks evaluated and remedial measures taken in advance."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Which joints have to be established with greater care?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet joints",
            "b) Mural joints",
            "c) Micro joints",
            "d) Columnar joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Occurrence of micro-joints has to be established with still greater care as such joint systems, if left untreated, could be source of many risks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Artificially created water storage basins with storage capacity that may range from a few thousand cubic meters to thousands of millions cubic meters are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lakes",
            "b) Ponds",
            "c) Pools",
            "d) Reservoirs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reservoirs may broadly be defined as artificially created water storage basins with storage capacity that may range from a few thousand cubic meters to thousands of millions cubic meters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Depending on the purpose of storage, reservoirs are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depending on the purpose of storage, reservoirs are classified into three main categories: Storage and conservation reservoirs; Flood control reservoirs; Distribution reservoirs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Which reservoirs are used to feed the canal systems for irrigation and power generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage and conservation reservoirs",
            "b) Flood control reservoirs",
            "c) Distribution reservoirs",
            "d) Drought control reservoirs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Storage and conservation reservoirs, are the ones where river water is stored by creating barriers or dams in its path and is then released from gated or ungated outlets. These feed the canal systems for irrigation and power generation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "The reservoirs for small storage and short period of time are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage and conservation reservoirs",
            "b) Flood control reservoirs",
            "c) Distribution reservoirs",
            "d) Drought control reservoirs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Distribution reservoirs are actually small storage reservoirs that hold water supplies in a water supply system for short spells of time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Reservoirs involving large sluice gates are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Storage and conservation reservoirs",
            "b) Flood control reservoirs",
            "c) Distribution reservoirs",
            "d) Drought control reservoirs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flood control reservoirs are provided with large sluice ways to discharge the inflow received by the reservoir during a flood up to a volume that could be safely accommodated in the channel downstream. "
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "The level up to which the reservoir shall be full of water is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High level",
            "b) Maximum level",
            "c) Pool level",
            "d) Surface level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pool level, indicated the designed level up to which the reservoir shall be ‘full of water’ at a particular point of time. There is, thus, the maximum pool level, the minimum pool level and the normal pool level."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "The measure of the volume of water that can be drawn from a given reservoir in a certain interval of time is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface yield",
            "b) Drawable yield",
            "c) Reservoir yield",
            "d) Pool yield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reservoir yield is a measure for the volume of water that can be drawn from a given reservoir in a certain interval of time and is also expressed in terms of safe or guarantee yield, secondary yield and design yield etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Volume of water in cubic meters available between minimum pool level and normal pool level is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Useful storage",
            "b) Dead storage",
            "c) Surcharge storage",
            "d) Specific storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Useful storage is defined as, volume of water in cubic meters available between minimum pool level and normal pool level. "
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "What is the volume of water which is available between maximum reservoir level and normal pool level called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Useful storage",
            "b) Dead storage",
            "c) Surcharge storage",
            "d) Specific storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surcharge storage is defined as, the volume of water which is available between the maximum reservoir level and normal pool level. "
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "What is the shape of valley usually preferred for a reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) U-shaped",
            "b) V-shaped",
            "c) Flat lands or plains",
            "d) U or V-shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The valley could be a U-shaped glacial valley, or a V-shaped river valley or a broader synclinal valley. Flatlands and plains cannot make convenient places for reservoirs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "During which condition, permeability of rocks have to be given more importance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When general water is much above the top reservoir level",
            "b) When general water table is much below the minimum water level",
            "c) When general water table and top water level of the proposed reservoir are almost same",
            "d) When general water table is slightly above the top reservoir level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the general water table is much below the minimum water level in the reservoir, permeability of the rocks along the base and the flanks is taken into consideration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Which is the ideal condition for a reservoir?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When general water is much above the top reservoir level",
            "b) When general water table is much below the minimum water level",
            "c) When general water table and top water level of the proposed reservoir are almost same",
            "d) When general water table is slightly above the top reservoir level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The general water table of the area and the top water level of the proposed reservoir are almost the same. This is an ideal situation ensuring a no loss no gain condition but generally not available on a large scale."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Heavy load of sediments to reservoirs would reduce __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow of water in that area",
            "b) Effective storage",
            "c) Total life of reservoir",
            "d) Total life and effective storage of reservoir"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The run off and slope wash would contribute heavy load of sediments to the reservoir after every rain. This would obviously decrease the effective storage capacity of the reservoir on one hand and its total life on the other hand. "
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Which among the following need not be given prime importance during geological investigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Groundwater conditions",
            "b) Wind conditions",
            "c) Structural constitution",
            "d) Trend and rate of weathering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since reservoirs are essentially water storage basins, the area should possess such geological characteristics that favour holding of water in the basin so created. Such characters are: topographic suitability, ground water conditions, permeability and structural stability and also trend and rate of weathering."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Removal of silt is usually __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time consuming",
            "b) Energy consuming",
            "c) Money consuming",
            "d) Time, energy and money consuming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Removal of silt or methods of sedimentation control may be so much time and energy and money consuming that the economy of the project is sometimes threatened. These facts prove the complicated nature of the problem. "
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "The major problem in a reservoir over time which may affect the storage capacity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leakage",
            "b) Silting",
            "c) Reduction in rainfall",
            "d) Weathering of side slopes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentation of reservoirs with the passage of time is the most important problem to solve in reservoir design. Uncontrolled sedimentation will lead to the indirect failure of the project by gradually reducing the storage capacity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Pick a method to control silting.",
        "Options": [
            "a) By grouting",
            "b) By reducing water level",
            "c) Construction of check dams",
            "d) By constructing lining on the rock foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Important methods of treatment include better reservoir designs, installation of check dams at the inlet points and water-shed improvement by forestation on an extensive and intensive scale. "
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "The underground routes or passages driven through the ground without disturbing overlying soil cover are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bridges",
            "b) Passages",
            "c) Tunnels",
            "d) Sub-routes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tunnels may be defined as underground routes or passages driven through the ground without disturbing the overlying soil or rock cover. Tunnels are driven for a variety of purposes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Type of tunnels which are excavated to divert the traffic load of whatsoever type from surface to subsurface routes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic tunnels",
            "b) Hydropower tunnels",
            "c) Public utility tunnels",
            "d) Delivery tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The traffic tunnels include all tunnels which are excavated to divert the traffic load of whatsoever type from surface to subsurface routes for a short length with a view of facilitating the flow of traffic at a desired speed, maximum convenience and at minimum cost. "
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Pick the tunnel which is not a sub-group of traffic tunnels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Railway tunnels",
            "b) Sewage tunnels",
            "c) Highway tunnels",
            "d) Pedestrian tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The railway tunnels, the highway tunnels and the pedestrian tunnels are the main sub-groups of traffic tunnels. A few navigational tunnels also fall under this category. "
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "Tunnels associated with hydropower generation are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy tunnels",
            "b) Power tunnels",
            "c) Generation tunnels",
            "d) Hydropower tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During twentieth century most of the tunnelling has been in connection with hydropower generation. Such tunnels are aptly called “hydropower” tunnels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Type of hydropower tunnel where water is conveyed under gravity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discharge tunnel",
            "b) Pressure tunnel",
            "c) Supply tunnel",
            "d) Delivery tunnel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In most cases hydropower tunnels are driven through rocks for the purpose of conveying water under gravity from one point to another. In such cases, they are called discharge tunnels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Type of hydropower tunnel where water is conveyed under high pressure to turbines is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discharge tunnel",
            "b) Pressure tunnel",
            "c) Supply tunnel",
            "d) Delivery tunnel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The other type of hydropower tunnels are those which feed water under great pressure to turbines and are distinguished as pressure tunnels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "Underground excavations for carrying pipes, sewage etc. fall under which type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic tunnels",
            "b) Hydropower tunnels",
            "c) Public utility tunnels",
            "d) Delivery tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Public utility tunnels include a variety of underground excavations made for specific purposes such as for disposal of urban waste (sewage tunnels), for carrying pipes, cables and supplies of oil, water etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Subway and tube railways are studied under which type of tunnels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic tunnels",
            "b) Hydropower tunnels",
            "c) Public utility tunnels",
            "d) Delivery tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Subways and tube railways also fall in the category of excavations but they are, in most cases, not tunnels in the strict sense because they are excavations made in the ground and then covered from the top. "
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Method of placing tubes in public utility tunnels is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Covering method",
            "b) Digging method",
            "c) Slash and cover method",
            "d) Cut and cover method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The method of placing the tubes or tracks is called cut and cover method and not tunnelling in which, top cover remains undisturbed and intact during the excavation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Geologically, how many classes of tunnels are recognized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Geologically speaking, only two classes of tunnels are recognized: tunnels driven through rocks (rock tunnelling) and tunnels driven through soil, loose sediments or saturated ground (soft-ground tunnelling)."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Selection of excavation method depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of rocks",
            "b) Nature of rocks and ground",
            "c) Texture of rocks and ground",
            "d) Weather conditions of the place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Choice of the right method will, therefore, be possible only when the nature of the rocks and the ground all along the alignment is fully known. This is one of the most important aim and objects of geological investigations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which outline is preferred for weak rocks with unequal lateral pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D-shaped",
            "b) Horse-shoe shaped",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Rectangular shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In self-supporting and strong rocks, either, D-shape or horse-shoe shape may be conveniently adopted but these shapes would be practically unsuitable in soft ground or even in weak rocks with unequal lateral pressure. In those cases, circular outline may be the first choice. "
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "Lithology does not affect which parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of tunnel",
            "b) Method of tunnelling",
            "c) Strength and extent of lining",
            "d) Cost of the project"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Information regarding mineralogical composition, textures and structures of the rocks through which the proposed tunnel is to pass is of great importance in deciding: the method of tunnelling, the strength and extent of lining and, thus the cost of the project. "
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "What occurs due to falling of big rock blocks or sides due to release of stresses during tunnelling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rock fall",
            "b) Rock bursts",
            "c) Blockage",
            "d) Water rush"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rock bursts that occur due to falling of big rock blocks from roofs or sides due to the release of stresses or falling of rock block along fractures already existing in these rocks often cause many accidents. "
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Pick the rock considered as soft rocks for tunnelling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Gabbro",
            "c) Basalt",
            "d) Shale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rocks considered as hard and crystalline are granites, syenites, gabbros, basalts and all the related igneous rocks, sandstones, limestones, dolomites, quartzites etc. However the soft rocks include shales, friable and poorly compacted sandstones, chalk and porous varieties of limestones and dolomites, slates and phyllites with high degree of cleavage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which type of rocks requires double lining, i.e., temporary and permanent lining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hard rocks",
            "b) Crystalline rocks",
            "c) Soft rocks",
            "d) Non-crystalline rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In most cases, the soft rocks are not self-supporting. Hence, temporary and permanent lining becomes necessary that would involve extra cost and additional time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Which type of strata is rare in occurrence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical strata",
            "b) Horizontal strata",
            "c) Inclined strata",
            "d) Jointed strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Horizontal strata are rare in occurrence for longer tunnels. If they are countered for small tunnels or short lengths of long tunnels, horizontally layered rocks might be considered quite favourable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Layers dipping at angles up to 45° may be called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moderately inclined strata",
            "b) Steeply inclined strata",
            "c) Half inclined strata",
            "d) Semi-inclined strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The layers that dipping at angles up to 45° may be said as moderately inclined strata. The tunnel axis may be running parallel to the dip direction, at right angles to the dip direction or inclined to both dip and strike direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "When can the rocks act as a natural arch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tunnel axis parallel to dip direction",
            "b) Tunnel axis normal to dip direction",
            "c) Tunnel axis inclined to dip direction",
            "d) Tunnel axis parallel to strike direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the tunnel axis may be running parallel to the dip direction, the layers offer uniformly distributed load on the excavation. The arch action is said to happen, where the rocks at roof act as natural arches transferring the load onto sides."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "In synclinal condition, low pressure areas are found at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Core",
            "b) Crust",
            "c) Mantle",
            "d) Outline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In anticlinal folds, loads of rocks at the crust are transferred by arch action to a great extent to the limbs which may be highly strained. These conditions are reversed in synclinal folds. In such cases, rocks of core regions are greatly strained. "
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included under preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Knowing the general topography of the area",
            "b) Knowing the lithology of the area",
            "c) Knowing the structural condition of the rocks",
            "d) Driving the pilot tunnels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The preliminary surveys include: Knowing the general topography, the lithology, hydrological conditions in the area and structural condition of the rocks. Driving pilot tunnels, bore-hole drilling are considered under detailed surveys. "
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Folded rocks are often best storehouses of which of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Juvenile water",
            "b) Magmatic water",
            "c) Artesian water",
            "d) Connate water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Folded rocks are often best storehouses for artesian water and also ideal as aquifers. When encountered during tunnelling unexpectedly, these could create uncontrollable situations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Which type of geological structure can be rectified by grouting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joints",
            "b) Folds",
            "c) Faults",
            "d) Inclined strata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In many cases, problems created by jointing in rocks due to jointing can be grouting. In other cases, lining of the tunnel in the fractured zones might have to be applied. "
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "The branch or study which deals with behaviour of rocks under applied forces is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil mechanics",
            "b) Rock mechanics",
            "c) Lithology",
            "d) Geology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rock mechanics deals essentially with behaviour of rocks under applied force fields in natural as well as in laboratory conditions. Rock mechanics has developed at such a fast pace during last it has already become a compulsory part of advanced civil engineering practice. "
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "Which material can be used as a roofing material among the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slate",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Marble",
            "d) Gneiss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slates used in many areas as roofing material for ordinary constructions and in pavements also fall in the category of building stones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "Which type of compressive strength is taken as the most important index property of stones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Confined",
            "b) Drained",
            "c) Undrained",
            "d) Unconfined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stones like all other solids fail when subjected to loads beyond their strength. The failure takes place under compressive, tensile and shear forces at different values. It is however, the unconfined compressive strength, which is taken as the most important index property of stones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "What is the maximum force expressed per unit area, which a stone can withstand without rupturing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear strength",
            "b) Tensile strength",
            "c) Compressive strength",
            "d) Bending strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compressive strength is also sometimes referred as crushing strength of a stone and may be defined as the maximum force expressed per unit area, which a stone can withstand without rupturing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "What is not true about unconfined test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is also called tri-axial test",
            "b) The specimen has no lateral support",
            "c) The specimen has no lateral restraint",
            "d) It is also called uniaxial test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The load at failure divided by the area of cross-section of the sample gives the unconfined compressive strength of the rock. The value is termed unconfined or uniaxial because the test specimen has no lateral support or restraint and is being compressed only along one axis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Which rock possesses very high compressive strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous",
            "b) Sedimentary",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Sedimentary and metamorphic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Igneous rocks being crystalline in character, compact and interlocking in texture and uniform in structure possess very high compressive strengths compared to sedimentary and metamorphic rocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of a stone to withstand bending loads called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bending strength",
            "b) Shear strength",
            "c) Transverse strength",
            "d) Lateral strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transverse strength is defined as the capacity of a stone to withstand bending loads. Such loads are only rarely involved in situations where stones are commonly used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Ratio between the total volume of the rock pore spaces and the total volume of the rock sample is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Void ratio",
            "b) Porosity",
            "c) Pores ratio",
            "d) Bulk density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Numerically, porosity is expressed as the ratio between the total volume of the pore spaces and the total volume of the rock sample and is expressed commonly in percentage terms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Pick the stone which is objectionable for use in moist conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Marble",
            "c) Gabbro",
            "d) Limestone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sandstones and limestones may show varieties as high absorption values as 10% or more. Selection of such highly porous varieties of stones for use in building construction, especially in moist situations, would be greatly objectionable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "The density of the rock with natural moisture content is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry density",
            "b) Wet density",
            "c) Bulk density",
            "d) Natural density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bulk density is the density of the rock with natural moisture content. It is assumed that in such cases all the pore spaces are not filled with water. "
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Ease with which stone can be extracted and dressed is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consistency",
            "b) Workability",
            "c) Easability",
            "d) Permeability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Many otherwise sound building stones like granites and other coarse grained igneous rocks are poor in fire resistance. These may become unsuitable for use in heat intensive situations."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about granite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very high crushing strength",
            "b) Low absorption values",
            "c) Takes good polish",
            "d) High absorption values"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By workability of a stone is understood the ease in the effort and the economy with which it can be extracted from its natural place of occurrence and finally given a proper shape called dressing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Limestone can be used as facing stones at situations where __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air is polluted with industrial gases",
            "b) Along sea coasts where sea water-rich winds can attack them",
            "c) Less chemical exposure and mild weather",
            "d) The place has very harsh weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Granites show very high crushing strength, low absorption value, least porosity, interlocking texture, variety of appealing colours and capacity to get brilliant polish. "
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "The resistance offered by a stone against rubbing action is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rubbing resistance",
            "b) Abrasive resistance",
            "c) Frictional resistance",
            "d) Shear resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Use of limestone as facing stones, even if quite strong, should be avoided in situations where- the air is polluted with industrial gases, such as in industrial towns; along sea coasts where sea-water-rich winds can attack them directly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a desirable of a road stone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrophobic in nature",
            "b) Sufficient hardness and toughness",
            "c) Durability at the place of use",
            "d) Hydrophilic in nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abrasive is more a qualitative than quantitative property and may be broadly defined as the resistance, which a stone offers to rubbing action of one kind or another. "
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "The property which defines the resistance of stone to rubbing and grinding action under the wheel of the traffic is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasive resistance",
            "b) Crushing resistance",
            "c) Hardness",
            "d) Specific gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Following are most important properties a good road stone should possess- sufficient hardness and toughness; durability at the place of use; cementation capacity; non-swelling or hydrophobic property. "
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Common bitumen is generally of which nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anionic",
            "b) Cationic",
            "c) Neutral charge",
            "d) No charge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hardness is defined as the resistance of stone to rubbing and grinding action under the wheel of the traffic as also due to mutual attrition. It is known that the aggregates of roads and pavements undergo repeated shaking movements under the traffic load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "The basic igneous rock which is dark coloured and has been extensively used as road materials is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite",
            "b) Gabbro",
            "c) Basalt",
            "d) Syenite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Marbles have sufficient strength to beam building loads and at the same time can be given any desirable shape because of their low hardness. Marble can take a brilliant polish. "
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "The test which is conducted by an indirect method usually is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compressive strength test",
            "b) Shear strength test",
            "c) Bending strength test",
            "d) Tensile strength test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Common bitumen is generally anionic in character. Any aggregate having electrolytic property will behave as hydrophobic or water repelling and vice-versa. This holds well in aggregates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "What is the term that refers to a continuous belt or zone of rocks that has suffered complex deformations through geological ages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plateaus",
            "b) Valleys",
            "c) Mountains",
            "d) Lakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In geological sense, the term mountain refers to a continuous belt or zone of rocks that has suffered complex deformations (Like folding and faulting) through the geological ages. These may or may not be having high relief at present. "
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "What is the term used for a linear type of mountainous structure characterized with two slopes on opposite slides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mountain range",
            "b) Mountain belt",
            "c) Mountain system",
            "d) Mountain family"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term mountain range is used for a linear ridge type mountainous structure characterized with two slopes on opposite sides and commonly (not necessarily) culminating in peaks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "When a number of mountain ranges and ridges continue for extensive distances for thousands of kilometres maintaining their characteristic features throughout, the term used is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mountain range",
            "b) Mountain belt",
            "c) Mountain system",
            "d) Mountain family"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a number of mountain ranges and ridges continue for extensive distances for thousands of kilometres maintaining their characteristic features throughout, the resulting complex structure is called a mountain belt or chain.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "How any broad classes of mountains are recognized based on mode of origin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two broad classes of mountains are recognized on the basis of their mode of origin tectonic mountains and relict mountains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "The class of mountains most common in geographic distribution and often very complicated in geological structure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relict mountains",
            "b) Residual mountains",
            "c) Tectonic mountains",
            "d) Artificial mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tectonic mountains owe their origin to severe intern forces the oregenic forces arising from within the Earth. These mountains are the most common in geographic distribution and often very complicated in geological structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "The mountains not belonging to tectonic mountains are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Residual mountains",
            "b) Volcanic mountains",
            "c) Fault block mountains",
            "d) Folded mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mountains considered under the tectonic mountains are volcanic mountains, fault block mountains and the folded mountains. Residual mountains are totally belonging to a different class of mountains.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "Mountains which have been formed by the age-long erosion and weathering of pre-existing surface features of the Earth are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic mountains",
            "b) Folded mountains",
            "c) Fault block mountains",
            "d) Relict mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Relict mountains are the ones which have been formed by the age-long erosion and weathering of pre-existing surface features of the Earth like plateaus, plains and of even original complex tectonic mountains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "Mountains resulting from the depression of blocks of the Earth crust on a large scale due to faulting are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic mountains",
            "b) Folded mountains",
            "c) Fault block mountains",
            "d) Relict mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mountains resulting from the depression or elevation of blocks of the Earth crust on a large scale due to faulting; these elevated structures are commonly called fault block mountains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Which mountains are called as complex mountains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic mountains",
            "b) Folded mountains",
            "c) Fault block mountains",
            "d) Relict mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The folded mountains are also called as complex mountains. During and after their formation, these mountains have been repeatedly, bent, wrapped and faulted leading to the present day most complicated structures exhibited by them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Pick the mountain which does not belong to folded mountains.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mount Agung",
            "b) The Alps",
            "c) The Himalayas",
            "d) Appalachian system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Mount Agung is an example of a volcanic mountain whereas the rest are folded mountains. "
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "Which type of mountains are common in the Basin and Range province of US?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic mountains",
            "b) Folded mountains",
            "c) Fault block mountains",
            "d) Relict mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The side blocks in faulted mountains may be of mountainous heights. Horst and Graben are often complimentary structures. This type of mountains are typical in occurrence in the Basin and Range province of U.S.A. "
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "A depression or hollow of considerable area extent surrounded on the side by two or more elevated tracts is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valley",
            "b) Mountain",
            "c) Pit",
            "d) Crest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A valley, in the geomorphic sense, is a depression or hollow of considerable area extent surrounded on side by two or more elevated tracts. Valleys may be the result of age-long erosion along the medial parts of elevated tracts, or, these might have been produced from a gradual or abrupt subsidence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "The type of valley most common on Earth is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rain valleys",
            "b) Erosional valleys",
            "c) Wind valleys",
            "d) Tectonic valleys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The erosional valleys are the most common types of valleys on the Earth. Erosional valleys may be the result of the stream erosion and glacial erosion. They are accordingly named as River valleys and Glacial valleys. "
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "The river valleys are typically of which shaped sections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C-shaped",
            "b) D-shaped",
            "c) V-shaped",
            "d) O-shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A river valley is the result of down-cutting and bank erosion by the river. Since most of the river erosion processes are concentrated along the bottom of a river channel, especially in the mountainous regions, the resulting river valley has a typical V-shaped cross-section. "
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "What is the weathering of the exposed walls by physical and chemical processes followed by slippage of weathered products into river below under the action of gravity called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass slipping",
            "b) Mass wasting",
            "c) Rocks wasting",
            "d) Debris wasting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Weathering of the exposed walls by physical and chemical processes followed by slippage of weathered products into river below under the action of gravity and rainwash, the process is called mass wasting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "The modification of valley walls by undercutting, weathering and erosion is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incision",
            "b) Deposition",
            "c) Denudation",
            "d) Enudation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Incision is the down-cutting along the base of the channel by the river itself and denudation is the modification of valley walls by undercutting, weathering and erosion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "The type of valley formed when incision is a major process and denudation is almost absent is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saw cut valleys",
            "b) V-shaped valleys",
            "c) Flat-floored valleys",
            "d) Glacial valleys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Saw cut valleys arise when incision is the major process and denudation is either absent or negligible. A very narrow, almost vertical-walled valley is produced. "
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "Deep saw cut valleys with slightly opened up tops indicating some denudation are specially referred as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canyons",
            "b) Canons",
            "c) Gorges",
            "d) Gorgeous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Exceptionally deep saw cut valleys with slightly opened up tops indicating some denudation are specially referred to as Gorges. These are quite common and impressive features of the major Himalayas Rivers in their mountainous tracts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "Types of gorges where the strata involved in down cutting is essentially horizontal or nearly so are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canyon",
            "b) Gorgeian",
            "c) Flicklops",
            "d) Lockiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Canyons are those types of gorges where the strata involved in down cutting is essentially horizontal or nearly so. The Grand Canyon of Colorado is a well-known example. "
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "The type of valley formed when the incision and denudation are approximately equal __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saw cut valleys",
            "b) V-shaped valleys",
            "c) Flat-floored valleys",
            "d) Glacial valleys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The V-shaped valleys may be said to have established a broad equilibrium between the down cutting, slope-denudation and their load carrying capacity. The valleys may or may not be symmetrical in their transverse profile depending upon the type of rocks on the slopes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "Valleys in which the incision becomes negligible and denudation of slopes is major process are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saw cut valleys",
            "b) V-shaped valleys",
            "c) Flat-floored valleys",
            "d) Glacial valleys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the formation of V-shaped valleys, the incision and denudation are approximately equal. In such cases, the valley profile assumes a typical V-shape. "
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "Depending upon the extent of incision and denudation occurred during the formation of a valley, how many broad classes of valleys are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the incision becomes negligible and denudation of slopes is the major process, the result is a flat-floored valley. It is the common profile of a valley in the lower reaches of a river. "
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "Which is the largest lake in the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lake Superior",
            "b) Dal Lake",
            "c) Caspian Sea",
            "d) Wular Lake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The famous Dal Lake and the Wular Lake are only 16 and 30 square kilometres in area respectively, whereas, the Caspian Sea, considered as the largest lake on the Earth, has an area 4,36,000 square kilometres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "Lakes can be free from salt because of the presence of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporating agents",
            "b) Salts are absent",
            "c) Presence of a regular outlet from the lake",
            "d) Enclosed area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lakes in which water is almost free from salts are called fresh water lakes. This becomes possible because of the presence of a regular outlet from the lake. "
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "Wular lake in Kashmir receives water from which river?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sutlej",
            "b) Narmada",
            "c) Brahmaputra",
            "d) Jhelum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Wular Lake of Kashmir is fresh water; it receives river Jhelum at one end which drains out from the other end near Baramullah. "
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "Which is the largest fresh water lake in the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lake Superior",
            "b) Dal Lake",
            "c) Caspian Sea",
            "d) Wular Lake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lake Superior is crescent shaped and is considered as the largest fresh-water lake, area wise (82,477 km2), whereas lake Baikul is considered as the deepest fresh-water lake with greatest volume (23,000 km2) of water in it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not cause for saline lake presence of an outlet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High content of salts",
            "b) Absence of an outlet",
            "c) Excessive rate of evaporation",
            "d) Presence of an outlet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water of such lakes is characterized with a high content of salts. This becomes possible due to absence of an outlet and/or an excessive rate of evaporation, which leads to the heavy concentration of salts in the lake water."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Caspian sea is which type of lake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large lake",
            "b) Fresh-water lake",
            "c) Saline lake",
            "d) Stream lake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The biggest lake, the Caspian Sea, is a lake belonging saline type. In other cases, the salinity of the lake is easily attributed to the dry climate, which causes precipitation of salts that form layers along the bottom and banks of the lakes."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "Pick the lake not belonging to salt water type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lake Geneva",
            "b) Lake Urmia",
            "c) Salt lake",
            "d) Lake Chad"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lake Geneva is a fresh water lake, whereas the rest are saline lakes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Basins formed due to faulting, folding are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic basins",
            "b) Tectonic basins",
            "c) Glacial basins",
            "d) Ground water basins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many basins are formed due to faulting, folding and other crustal movements. Such basins aptly called Tectonic basins. Depression of a central block in between two parallel faults, graben is an ideal site for a lake. "
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "Tectonic lake basins are of what nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permanent",
            "b) Temporary",
            "c) Very short-lived",
            "d) Semi-permanent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tectonic lake basins are commonly rectangular in outline and semi-permanent in nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "What is the outline of volcanic basins commonly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Circular",
            "c) Ellipse",
            "d) Tube-like"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Craters of extinct volcanoes are excellent depressions to serve as lake basins. Volcano created basins are commonly circular in outline. "
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "The Dal and Wular lakes are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volcanic basins",
            "b) Glacial basins",
            "c) Fluviatile basins",
            "d) Groundwater basins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The well-known Dal and Wular Lakes of Kashmir are believed to be detached and modified meander loops of the Jhelum. Similar lakes are also found in the delta of the Mississippi River. "
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "The doline type of lakes are carved out of which rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mica",
            "b) Granite",
            "c) Limestone",
            "d) Sandstone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The doline type of lakes are simple circular depressions carved out of limestone by solution action. The Deep Lake of Florida is an example. "
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "What is the stage when the bankfull stage is crossed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overflow stage",
            "b) Flood stage",
            "c) Dead stage",
            "d) Excess stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Normally, the river flows much below bankfull stage; abnormally; however, the bankfull, the stage may be crossed when the river is said to be in a flood stage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "The distance water travels in a unit time is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed",
            "b) Unit speed",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Acceleration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Velocity is defined as the distance water travels in a unit time within its channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "What is the term defining the capacity of a river to transport the material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Competence",
            "c) Flow type",
            "d) Fluvial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Competence defines the capacity of a river to transport the material and is represented by the largest size of a particle that can be transported at a given velocity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "The term which is a function of cross-sectional area of the channel and flow velocity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Competence",
            "c) Discharge",
            "d) Stream line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Discharge is defined as the volume that passes at a given point in the channel in a unit time. It is a function of cross-sectional area of the channel and flow velocity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "The mechanical loosening and removal of the material from the rocks due to pressure exerted by the running water is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient",
            "b) Weathering",
            "c) Hydraulic action",
            "d) Cavitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydraulic action is the mechanical loosening and removal of the material from the rocks due to pressure exerted by the running water. The higher velocity, the greater is the pressure of the running water and hence greater is its capacity to bodily move out parts of the rock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not true about cavitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It occurs everywhere",
            "b) It is distinct process",
            "c) It is a rare process",
            "d) It is observed where river water acquires exceptionally high velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cavitation is a distinct and rare type of hydraulic action performed by running water. It is particularly observed where river water suddenly acquires exceptionally high velocity such as at the location of a waterfall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "What is the principal method of stream erosion and involves wearing away of the bedrocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic action",
            "b) Abrasion",
            "c) Attrition",
            "d) Corrosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is known that where stream velocity exceeds 12m/sec, the water pressure developed at the impinging points equals vapour pressure and there is spontaneous change from liquid to vapour state and back to liquid state at that point. "
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "The term for wear and tear of the load sediments being transported by a moving natural agency through the process of mutual impacts is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic action",
            "b) Abrasion",
            "c) Attrition",
            "d) Corrosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Abrasion is the principal method of stream erosion and involves wearing away of the bedrocks and rocks along the banks of a stream or river by the running water with the help of sand grains, pebbles and gravels and all such particles that are being carried by it as load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "Factor which doesn’t affect velocity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient of the channel",
            "b) Volume of the water in the stream",
            "c) Type of water flowing",
            "d) Roughness of the channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Attrition is the term used for the term for wear and tear of the load sediments being transported by a moving natural agency through the process of mutual impacts and collisions which they suffer during their transport. "
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "The variously shaped depressions of different dimensions that are developed in the riverbed are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potholes",
            "b) Cavities",
            "c) Dents",
            "d) Craters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Potholes are variously shaped depressions of different dimensions that are developed in the riverbed by excessive localized erosion by the streams. "
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "Magnificent jumps made by a stream or river water at certain specific parts of their course where there is a sudden and considerable drop in the gradient of the channel are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streams",
            "b) Hydraulic jumps",
            "c) Waterfalls",
            "d) Knick-jumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A valley may be defined as a low land surrounded on sides by inclined hill slopes and mountains. Every major river is associated with a valley of its own. "
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "The most common type of flood plains are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat flood plains",
            "b) Simple flood plains",
            "c) Compound flood plains",
            "d) Complex flood plains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Waterfalls are magnificent jumps made by a stream or river water at certain specific parts of their course where there is a sudden and considerable drop in the gradient of the channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "Alluvial deposits of roughly triangular shape that are deposited by major rivers at their mouths are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deltas",
            "b) Backwaters",
            "c) Lakes",
            "d) Streams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Convex flood plains are the most common type and are associated with many major rivers of the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "A typical delta is made of how many layers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Deltas are defined as alluvial deposits of roughly triangular shape that are deposited by major rivers at their mouths, i.e., where they enter a sea. "
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "The condition not favouring the formation of delta is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absence of strong sea currents",
            "b) Presence of good quality of load",
            "c) Slope of seashore where the stream enters must be gentle",
            "d) Presence of strong sea currents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A typical simple delta is commonly made of three layers of which only the top layer may be sub aerial, that is exposed on the surface. "
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "Places of steep drops in elevation in the course of a river are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depressions",
            "b) Cavities",
            "c) Knickpoints",
            "d) Nickopoints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fore-sets are the intermediate layers and often show very steep inclination. The fore-set beds are made up of thick layers of sand and clay. "
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "The gently sloping land part that remains partly submerged under seawater is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continental shelf",
            "b) Continental bench",
            "c) Beach",
            "d) Continental slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Continental shelf is the gently sloping land part that remains partly submerged under seawater. It may be only a narrow strip or quite an extensive area stretching for hundreds of kilometres. "
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "The slope starting from the farthest end of the continental shelf and continuing up to sea floor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continental belt",
            "b) Continental bench",
            "c) Beach",
            "d) Continental slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Continental slope is the slope starting from the farthest end of the continental shelf and continuing up to sea floor. It may be gentle or very steep in gradient varying between 1 in 4 to 1 in 6. "
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "The type of waves that are characteristic of deeper portions of the sea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory waves",
            "b) Translatory waves",
            "c) Littoral waves",
            "d) Lateral waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oscillatory waves are characteristic of deeper portions of the sea. In such waves, each particle moves in a circular orbit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "The type of waves that are characteristic of shallower portions of the sea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory waves",
            "b) Translatory waves",
            "c) Littoral waves",
            "d) Lateral waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Translatory waves are typically of shallower depths in the sea and abound along the seashore. They are commonly produced after the oscillatory waves break and rush forward."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "Bodies of seawater of considerable volume moving along and parallel to the shore are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory waves",
            "b) Translatory waves",
            "c) Littoral currents",
            "d) Lateral currents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Littoral currents are the bodies of seawater of considerable volume moving along and parallel to the shore. "
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "The bodies of seawater moving backwards to sea after having reached and struck the seashore are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillatory waves",
            "b) Translatory waves",
            "c) Littoral currents",
            "d) Rip currents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rip currents are bodies of seawater moving backwards to sea after having reached and struck the seashore. They often move below the surface of the sea and reach varying distance up to the middle to the sea. "
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "Charles Darwin classified coral reefs into how many classes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Charles Darwin, who was the first to study and classify the reef deposits recognized the following three types: fringing reefs, barrier reefs and atolls. "
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "Peculiar type of ridge-like marine deposits that have been formed due to accumulation of dead parts of certain of sea-organisms are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limestone",
            "b) Coral reefs",
            "c) Pearl",
            "d) Gorges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coral reefs are peculiar types of ridge-like marine deposits that have been formed due to accumulation of dead parts of certain of sea-organisms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "The type of reefs that occur from a distance of shore and have flat-topped ridges are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fringing reefs",
            "b) Barrier reefs",
            "c) Atolls",
            "d) Deposited reefs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The barrier reefs are the most common type of reefs and occur at a distance from the shore or the island running in the form of parallel, flat-topped ridges. "
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "Type of reef with an annular, circular or semi-circular coral reef surrounding a lagoon is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fringing reefs",
            "b) Barrier reefs",
            "c) Atolls",
            "d) Deposited reefs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An atoll is essentially an annular, circular or semi-circular coral reef surrounding a central body of water that is as usual called a lagoon. In a typical atoll, the ring made of coral deposits may be continuous or discontinuous, more often broken at places."
    }
]